[Music]
All right. So, today was Apple's big
software event for 2025, WWDC. And it
was a really, it was actually a really
interesting one. I was kind of wondering
how this would go cuz in this landscape
of AI, AI, AI, everyone's talking about
Gemini and GPT everywhere where it feels
like Apple is being left behind. They
could kind of go one of two ways. They
could either double down on Apple
intelligence and just lean right in like
everything's fine, everything's going to
plan, or they could shelf some of that
stuff, but show a whole bunch of other
stuff and hope that that's good enough.
So, now we've seen the keynote and I've
gotten to try a lot of these software
features and think about them a lot. And
they definitely did the second thing.
Don't get me wrong, there's much more
other stuff than AI versus what like
Google was doing earlier. But I do think
that that other stuff was actually kind
of a lot. And so maybe you can leave a
comment below if you agree with me after
you subscribe, of course. But this is
everything you need to know about WWDC
2025. So first of all, they always talk
about all of their OSS, all their
platforms this year, and they are now
all unified in their version number just
to keep it simple. So instead of having
iOS 19, iPad OS 19, tvOS 19, Mac OS 16,
Watch OS 12, and Vision OS 3, they're
now just doing version 26 for
everything. kind of the same thing
Samsung just did with their phones in
2020. How they match the year even
though it's a year ahead. Cool. Easy.
And everything is getting this fresh
glassy coat of paint over everything to
be unified as well. So, it's more
obvious in some places that I'll show
you and less noticeable in some others,
but in general, they're calling this
liquid glass. And they're treating
basically every window, every dialogue
box, every icon, every sidebar that they
possibly can as like a piece of physical
glass that's mostly transparent to the
things below it. Even the lock screen
clock and some text, some fonts are
clear and transparent. So, we might as
well start here with iOS 26 because this
is the biggest one. All of the icons are
slightly updated. The lock screen clock
is just this big glassy clear time that
adapts to the size of what's behind it.
Once you unlock the iPhone, overall like
zoomed out, it doesn't look that
different. It's slightly different, but
they also kept showing this clear home
screen setup where all of the widgets
and icons are all clear. This is a new
option. And I don't know about this one.
I mean, it is new and you can do that if
you want to or never turn it on if you
don't want to. But I just think that's a
it's a little much and readability might
be kind of tough. But beyond the liquid
glass thing, there are also some new
features like they redesigned the camera
app really for the first time in a
decade plus. It's now going to be super
simplified to just photo and video
buttons and the shutter. And then
there's a whole bunch of hidden UI. So
you have to swipe to reveal the
additional modes. And those still work
the way they did before. But then also
the frames per second and resolution
settings are also super hidden. you have
to know to hit that little button up
there in the corner to change to 30 or
60 fps, which is a really interesting
choice there. I mean, especially on an
iPhone where you kind of have to assume
Apple knows which things people click
most of the time. This kind of implies
that nobody ever changes a lot of these
things. The swipe up to reveal a lot of
those settings. Most people will never
see that. But hey, you're watching this
video, so now you know that the live
photos setting toggle is there under
that swipe. So, good for you. There's
also uh a new FaceTime app with a new
landing page to quickly hit up your main
contacts. And then also the phone app is
updated to bring voicemail and miss
calls and contacts all into one unified
place. Kind of like that. And they've
also matched or copied. You could say it
however you want. Matched or copied. But
they've matched two of my favorite Pixel
features from the dialer from the phone
app, which is call screening and hold
for me. Those are the Pixel feature
names. So now in iOS 26, there's a
feature that can automatically screen
unknown numbers and it'll answer the
call for you and then transcribe
whatever the person says before trying
to ring you and showing you who's
calling, which is interesting because
the Pixel would let me choose that for
every single call manually. But then
also the hold assist feature is a
no-brainer. Just waits on hold for you
while you do other things and when it's
time to come back, it rings you again.
Both super useful. And there's also a
couple iMessage features like you can do
native polls inside of iMessage. Now,
typing indicators and group chats will
show you which person is typing, which
is sweet. And you can add pictures as
backgrounds for each of your iMessage
chats. None of this is groundbreaking or
unheard of, but it is nice that they're
finally adding it. And then I would say
the most AI focused thing here is
translate. And I I feel like there's
like a storm of like a video idea
brewing where I might have to make an
entire essay about how this is the year
of live translation. It's just happening
all at once now. Uh but yeah, in short,
Apple added live translation to
FaceTime, to messages, and the phone
app. And it it works basically as you'd
expect with the ondevice AI models. If
you turn it on during a phone call, you
can hear a person speak in their own
language, and then it gets translated
and read in your language. And then if
you want to speak back, it gets
translated again and read back in
another voice to that person. It's a
little laggy, but it gets the job done.
There's also a little bit more stuff in
maps and in Apple Music and a new games
app. Uh I plan on breaking all of this
down in a dedicated best new features of
iOS video. Definitely get subscribed if
you want to see that right when it comes
out. I always do this when the public
beta rolls around. So that's coming
soon. But my main concern from seeing
Apple's demo videos and playing with it
a little bit myself is readability. this
glass aesthetic. It looks cool
sometimes, but it also is a little hard
to read sometimes. Like, I get that the
clear and glassy sheen is very modern
and it looks like Vision OS and it's
fresh, but also there's a reason that we
add backgrounds to things in the video
world a lot, even if it's subtle,
because it's to provide more contrast to
make things easier to see. Just basic
stuff. and there were so many bits of
text like notifications or menus or even
UI elements that just looked kind of
harder to read. Now, the OS is supposed
to adapt to it by giving light things
dark backgrounds and dark things light
backgrounds, but sometimes you'll have
like a half light half dark background
and that's where things get weird. So,
I'm curious how this is going to play
out. Now, some of the other smaller
updates, Watch OS 26 also got a lot of
these glassy UI elements, and it's
noticeable. There's big touch areas and
reflections and glassy buttons galore.
And you can also definitely feel that
fresh coat of paint. But beyond that, I
really like the new wrist flick gesture,
which is just that. So, if you ever get
a notification and you don't want to do
anything with it, you know how it just
kind of sits on the watch for a while,
you can just flip it and it goes away.
So, if you're getting a notification,
you don't care, flip it. you're getting
a phone call, you don't want to accept
the phone call, dismiss it. If you got
an alarm that's starting to ring or
anything else like that you don't want
to be on your screen, just flip your
wrist and it goes away. I think I'll be
doing this all the time. And the other
big thing is this uh workout buddy,
which feels I'm going to describe it as
Spotify DJ but for Apple Watch workouts.
Like it's basically a new customizable
high energy voice that talks to you at
various times that it thinks you need
some energy or motivation during your
workout just by telling you stuff like
random stats like your heart rate or
your mile splits or hey this is your
third workout of the week. Great job.
Keep it up. Stuff like that. Uh still no
group fitness challenges though. I'm
going to just keep saying that every
year because every year I think they're
going to do it and every year they don't
do it. Still no group fitness
challenges. But then there was tvOS 26.
That also got new liquid glass. And I'll
be honest with this one. I barely notice
it here. But apparently the icons are
shimmering a little differently
allegedly. Uh but also just more content
obviously. Otherwise, not a huge upgrade
there. But then there's Mac OS 26, which
is also called Tahoe. And this one,
yeah, this one you notice this one's got
way more very clear elements to it. And
some of it kind of can look cool. Others
I really don't like as much personally.
And I I thought this again about some
older versions of Mac OS, so I'm sure
we'll get used to it, but like the
control center with the super
glassified feels a little more cartoony
buttons. I'm just not a huge fan of
that. You can also do clear widgets,
clear dock, and the menu bar is
completely clear at the top, which is
also sweet. Makes your screen feel
bigger. And so, yeah, there's there's
some stuff to get used to here. I think
I like some of it. It's just not totally
like winning me over yet. One really
good feature now though is live
activities, which is already a nice
thing on the iPhone. If you have an
iPhone and a Mac, it'll show up in the
little menu bar in the Mac when
something is like happening, a delivery
or a flight information, whatever it is,
you can click on it and that'll view
that convenient information from the
live activity. And then if you want to
click on it again, you can bring up the
whole iPhone mirrored app to keep track
of that live activity. Makes a lot of
sense. Nice continuity feature. Anyway,
the Mac also gets the new phone app. So,
you know, your voicemail and everything
in one place and the hold for me, all
those features. But the number one
biggest update I'm interested in on the
Mac is actually the new Spotlight. Now,
some of you might not care about
Spotlight, but some of you are
productivity nerds like me because
you're subscribed to a tech YouTube
channel. And you might already know
about this, but my favorite productivity
app on the Mac, and it has been for
years. Every fresh new Mac, I install it
first, is called Raycast. And it's it's
basically Spotlight on steroids. It lets
you open apps, but also do shortcuts and
do window management and find files and
do even more useful things like viewing
my clipboard history. So now Apple comes
out and shows us the new spotlight in
Mac OS 26 and it does almost all of that
stuff. This is what we call in the
industry getting sherlocked. Basically,
Apple showed a whole bunch of really
cool stuff you can do now with the new
spotlight. It's got this sweet animation
which separates out things like file
searches or Siri shortcut searches. You
can do shortcuts from the keyboard to
open actions inside of certain apps and
perform them straight up entire strings
of commands without even opening an app
or touching your mouse. Real power user
stuff. Productivity nerd stuff right
here. It doesn't do fully every single
thing that I've done with Raycast. like
in Raycast I can tab over and and start
a new search or conversation with GPT or
Gemini or a bunch of other stuff. The
spotlight doesn't do that yet, but who's
to say if next year they might add that
feature or might slowly start doing all
the things that Raycast does. It's an
interesting step. It's definitely
better. But then, okay, Vision OS, this
is where all the glass came from. This
is technically only the third version of
Vision OS, but now it's Vision OS 26.
And there's some smaller updates to this
one, but I think the new widgets, even
though they're kind of silly and not
really that functional, I think they're
awesome. I think they're super cool.
Basically, you can pin these things to
persistent locations and customize the
size and depth and color of them exactly
how you want. So, they showed things
like clocks and weather widgets and
picture frames, but then they have these
like really convincing location pinning
plus all the reflectivity and depth that
they always have. And I just I don't
know. I thought it was super cool. I was
sold. But really, this is also pinned
with the fact that Vision OS or the
Vision Pro will remember where you put
your Windows now all the time, like
through a reboot and everything, which
it didn't do before. It was one of my
biggest complaints I talked about in the
original Vision OS review. So, yes, it
will remember where you put your windows
and where you put your widgets. The
updated fidelity of the personas also,
uh, it was it's inevitable. Like, we
just knew they were going to continually
get more and more photorealistic, so
they showed another pretty big jump. Not
sure if you're going to have to do
another scan to get the updated Persona,
but either way, looks much better and
less cartoon ghosty. And there's also
they added PlayStation VR2 sense
controller support which no doubt will
be much better for some of the more
precise controls in certain games. Uh
there's also a new Jupiter environment.
So you're on one of Jupiter's moons with
Jupiter in the sky above you. Cool. They
also added native 360 video support
playback for cameras from GoPro, Insta
360, and Canon. It's pretty cool. We're
still hoping to see like more
highquality 360 content for these
headsets to view. There's some on
YouTube, but not a ton. But then the
biggest, most interesting update of the
day by far to me was iPad OS 26. This
was fascinating because, you know, every
iPad Pro video for the last 6 years or
however long it's been has always said
the same thing. It's great. It's amazing
hardware. It's very powerful, but it's
still an iPad. Meaning, it's still going
to have lots of limitations. And we
never really expect Apple to add those
really computer-like extra features
because they make computers, too. Why?
They're a business. They're not going to
cannibalize their own products. They're
not going to overlap that stuff. So,
there's iPads and then there's
computers. But with this update, I feel
like they they they use the word game
changer, which they use that word all
the time. But I actually feel like this
genuinely fit the bill because they
added things multitasking, file
management, things straight from the
Mac. So, yes, it still has the liquid
glass, of course. It has the new phone
app, the new lock screen, all the new
icons and widgets and all that, but then
this whole new multitasking and
multi-wind system where in any app, you
can just grab that handle in the bottom
right corner and shrink it in and make
the app whatever size you want
immediately to a floating window. And
then you can just start stacking
floating windows and and putting them
side by side and messing around with
window management very very freely. I'm
sure there's a limit to how many windows
you can have open. I got as many as four
open at the same time. But not only
that, they added this three dot window
control to the corner of each window,
the stop lightss that we have straight
from the Mac, so you can minimize or
change the shape of any app, just like
on a Mac. And on top of that, there's a
new literal Mac menu bar at the top of
the screen just giving you file, edit,
view, menu, help, just stuff that you
see in Mac apps. There's also a
redesigned cursor that seems a lot more
like a Mac cursor. It's less of a
floating blob that had like the aim
assist that we had before. Now it's just
a normal mouse. There's also a new files
app that lets you sort through things
with different ways, the same way you
would with the Finder app on a Mac.
There's now like you can have downloads
in your doc. There's all kinds of things
that I mean as someone who's used a Mac
for years.
Uh feels exactly like a Mac. There is
even an audio input selector built in
now for all media apps, which sounds
like such a small thing, but do you know
how hard it's been to change your
microphone input source on an iPad for
all these years? It's like they're
they're choosing now to add it. Great.
Also, background activities. So, if
you're exporting something from Final
Cut Pro for iPad, you can close the
Final Cut Pro app and do other things
and the export will continue in the
background just like a computer. So,
yeah, as a computer user, I'm
fascinated. This moves the iPad,
especially like the most powerful iPad
Pro, way further on the spectrum of
compelling laptop alternatives for
certain people. It certainly doesn't do
everything. Obviously, it still doesn't
have multiple profile support. There are
some basics that we're still going to be
missing, but I never thought that they
would go this far. And it definitely
feels like in lie of some other AI
stuff, they took a lot of wishlist
things that people have been talking
about with the iPads and gave them to
us. But speaking of that, I mean, the
real question is, were all of those
features enough to, you know, tide us
over, to distract us from the lack of AI
stuff? I looked at the transcript and if
if the transcript that I have is
accurate, they said the word
Siri times in that entire 90minute
keynote. So that clearly wasn't a big
focus. And to me, it just feels like
Apple's AI strength, if they have one,
is really much more in how well
integrated their features are. It's not
going to be how good the AI is. It's
just how plugged in they are to their
ecosystem. Like a lot of features they
showed us do use AI, but they aren't
necessarily branded as AI or Apple
intelligence all the time. And then also
some of this Apple intelligence stuff is
slowly taking steps forward, including
them making their own foundational
models available for developers to have
access to those ondevice models and
build more AI features into their apps.
Now, are those going to be the best
models in the world? No, probably not.
At least not right now. but they are on
device and local and can be used offline
and will probably be the fastest since
they don't have to go to the internet
and back. So, you can probably expect
many more apps to have little AI
features built into them, whether it's
just summarizations here and there or
shortening things that were longer,
things like that. Now, as for the big
LLM Siri upgrade that we kind of in the
background knew was taking too long,
they had a statement at the very
beginning of the keynote. If you
blinked, you might have missed it, but
the statement was, "This work required
more time to reach our high quality bar,
and we look forward to sharing more
about it in the coming year,
2026." We'll see. I just like that they
added the onscreen capabilities for
visual intelligence. So, it was just
from the camera feed before, but now,
you know how every Android phone has
circle to search? Well, yeah. Now, with
screenshots, the iPhone's going to get
that, too. This was a fascinating WWDC.
I am very excited to dig into these
betas and see what's actually good,
what's new about them. Stay tuned for
those videos. But let me know in the
comments what you think. Thanks for
watching. Catch you guys in the next
one. Peace.