10 Km  The sound of the explosion was heard far away
and pieces flew up to 400 metres away.  Whichever
soldier was using the mobile phone at night, he got
shot because the sniper was
shooting by looking at the light.   A
tunnel had been built beneath the entire area of ​​Kathua and Sama districts.  But Satyapal
Malik complicated the matter by saying that no,
I had said to get him airlifted from there.   I am
messaging the police saying hi jaanu.
Using two accounts from Pakistan, ₹1 lakh was
transferred there.
All those who crossed the border brought more than 20 kg of RDX on their backs.
In the video of Adil, Adil was
just talking.  Later it became known
that someone else was speaking from behind.
When the intimate photos of Insha and Umar were shown from inside the mobile,
Shakir got shocked and
revealed everything.   The
soldier was standing with a gun on the border, not for his home land.
[Music]
See,
in today's time, along with physical health, it is also important to take care of oral health.
And your teeth come first in oral health.
If your teeth are crooked
or have gaps between them, food gets
stuck in them and is not easily cleaned.
Due to which, the
risk of cavities and gum diseases increases due to the increase in bacteria
and sometimes
your confidence also remains low due to crooked teeth.  Now the
best solution to this problem is Tootsie teeth
aligners.  These aligners fix your misaligned teeth in 6 to 12 months.   It is
very comfortable to wear and is
completely invisible.  And the best part is
that these aligners are removable.  So no food
restrictions.  Take off the aligners, eat whatever you want
and wear them back.  The
process of ordering these aligners is also quite simple.
All you need to do is visit Toothsee’s website and
book a teeth scan.  You can get the scan done at home
or by visiting Toots C’s pan India Experience
Centers.
Your aligners are delivered to your home a few days after the scan.
More than 3 lakh
people have found their dream smile with the help of Toothsee.  The
next number is yours.
Start your teeth straightening journey with a
free teeth scan and doctor consultation.  The
link is in the description.  So let's
come back to the topic.  See,
due to the Kandahar hijacking incident on 31 December 1999,
India had to leave Masood Azhar
inside Afghanistan.  Now Masood Azhar was
released in Afghanistan
but after 2 months of his release, that is
in March 200, he reached
Bahawalpur in Pakistan and after reaching here,
Pakistan's ISI gives a grand welcome to Masood Azhar.
A rally was also taken out and
standing in this rally, Masood Azhar
officially launched Jaish-e-Mohammed
and said that the people of Jaish-e-Mohammed will
separate Kashmir from India.
Now Jaish-e-Mohammed was launched
and for the next 5 years after its launch,
Jaish-e-Mohammed
recruited Kashmiris.  Got training etc. from ISI etc.
Many attacks were carried out and the
Parliament attack etc. all
happened within these 5 years.  And
in the years to come, Jaish-e-Mohammed
changed its model and its way of working from time to time in Kashmir.  But the only priority of Jaish-e-Mohammed was to
hire young Kashmiris, train them and carry out
attacks in India.  Because the
message through it was that Kashmiris are
standing against India and
Pakistan has nothing to do with it.
So in the coming years, Jaish-e-Mohammed had established
its foothold in Kashmir.
But after this, by the year 2015, something
different happened.  Before this, those who
became commanders etc. used to
live in hiding inside Kashmir.  Used to keep a low profile.
But at this time Burhan Wali
showed his militancy in a new style.
He was the first militant who, instead of hiding,
posted openly on social media.   Used to
challenge Indian forces.  He used to
post before attacking.  And because of this,
it became very famous in Kashmir within a very short time.
And this pushed
young Kashmiris towards militancy in a very short time.
Now
Burhanwani's way of working
suited Jaish-e-Mohammed very much.  But
before Jaish-e-Mohammed could think of anything, Burhanwani was killed
by Indian forces on 8th of July 2016.
And because of this the
atmosphere inside Kashmir became very bad.
And this was the time when Masood Azhar
decided that this is the best time to launch
more attacks inside Kashmir.  Now Masood Azhar
was in Pakistan and
inside Pakistan, Masood Azhar had five most trusted
people.  Umar Farooq, Usman Haider, Talha
Masood, Ismail Alvi who is also known as Lambu Bhai.
and Abdul Rashid Ghazi.  So these
five guys were great trustees of Masood Azar.
And among these five, Talha,
Usman and Umar were from Masood Ahar's
family.  He had nephews.  So when
Burhan Wani died, Masood Azhar
sent Talha Masood from Pakistan to Kashmir in the beginning of the year 2017
and made him the commander of the South Division of Kashmir.
Talha was given the task to get as
many young
Kashmiris as possible to join Jaish-e-Mohammed in this area
and expand the network of OGWs.
See, OGW means over ground worker.
Jaish Mohammed had
created a network of local people inside Kashmir.  These
included those Kashmiris who did
not want to take up arms openly against the Indian Forces.
But providing shelter to the
other terrorists in Kashmir who fought against the Indian forces
, providing them the
location and small intel about the Indian forces,
handling logistics, arranging safe houses,
all these tasks were done by OGWs.
So Jaish-e-Mohammed
wanted to expand this network further.  He used to play very important roles.
Whenever the OGW network is
strong, the attack becomes easier.
And Jaish-e-Mohammed preferred to
hire local drivers, people running shops in local markets as OGWs because it becomes easier to get OGWs to perform their tasks through such people
and there is less suspicion on them.  Now
see, Adildar enters in the same year i.e. in 2017.
Which
is the root of this entire Pulwama attack.  So see, there is
a village in Kakapura area of ​​Pulwama district of Jammu and Kashmir.
Gundibag.  There is a school here, Government
Higher Secondary School, and
Adildar was studying in 12th class in this school.
At that time no one had thought that
this boy studying in 12th was going to launch
such a big attack in the future.  In
this school, apart from Adil,
he had two more friends.  Tausif and Wasim, out
of these Tausif was completely brainwashed.
His elder brother had also
joined militancy.  Just a few
days ago.  He too was shot by the Indian forces,
so Tausif
plays a very important role in influencing Adil and Wasim about
how wrong the Indian Army is doing.  So, see, these three were
studying in this school and
what happens is that one day, Adil was coming from school
and by mistake, the
Indian forces pick him up in a stone pending case.  She
keeps it for a few days and then
leaves it.  Now there were many other reasons behind picking him up
because when Burhan Wani was killed,
Adil and his two friends used to go for
protests daily and would pelt
stones at Kakapura and Lethpura and then
return home. So, in all this,
they have been arrested several times for stone pelting and were
put in jail and then
released after some time.
Similarly, one day Adil was shot in his leg
and because of the bullet injury,
he was on bed rest for several months and was
admitted to the hospital and because of this he
missed school as well. Now, after a few months,
Adil's heart gets better but
after recovery, he does two things.  One even drops
out of school altogether.  The second
Ansar comes in contact with Ghazwat ul Hind
and joins it.  She also
fights against the Indian Government and at the same time she had to
run the household.  So what does Adil do?
He had a neighbour.  He had a wood cutting mill
in which wooden boxes were made.  So
Adil started working here.  So ever since he
came in touch with the people of Ansar Ghazwat ul Hind.  His entire mind had been washed.
Now he worked in the wood mill for a few days
and then one day when Adil was working inside this wood mill, there was
an
electrician named Mudasir Khan.
Adil comes in touch with it.
He was actually an OGW of Jaish-e-Mohammed.
And this influences Adil and
convinces him to join Jaish-e-Mohammed.
And at that time, Ansar Ghazwat ul
Hind was short of weapons and
resources.  So
because of this Adil joined Jaish-e-Mohammed.
But when Adil joined Jaish-e-Mohammed, the
same day Mudasir had
told the commanders of Jaish-e-Mohammed
that Adil could be very useful for our mission.  He is a
very genuine boy
and is filled with anger
towards the Indian Forces.  Now all these
things were going on and a few days later, i.e. on the
sixth of November 2017, the Indian
forces made Talha, who was sent by Masood Azhar, the
commander, and killed him in an encounter.
Now this thing which had happened was Masood's
nephew and Masood was
very frustrated about this.  When this incident
happened, in the midst of this incident,
Masood Azhar had also organized a rally etc. inside Pakistan.
In which he had said in front of everyone
that he will take revenge from the Indian Forces
and will give a befitting reply.  And to
take revenge for Talha, Masood
called Usman and Umar from his four trustees and told them that
now after Talha, you both have to
go to Kashmir and take this fight forward and
take revenge.  These Usman and Umar were the
sons of Ibrahim Attar, the mastermind of the Qadaar hijacking.
Both of them were also nephews of Masood.  So at this time
they had decided that first
Usman would cross the border and
then Umar would go and whenever they
crossed the border, they used to do it on the night of new moon, so on
11 January 2018, Usman was the first to
cross the LOC from Hiragar Sector and
reach Kashmir and after going to Kashmir, he became the
commander of the South Kashmir area.
This Usman who had arrived had
one speciality.  He was a very good sniper.
It could locate its target at night based on the mobile light.
And as soon as
Usman reached Kashmir, Indian
forces noticed a pattern that those
officers who were using mobile phones at that time were the
ones who were shot at.  So,
3 months after Usman's arrival, on 13th April 2018,
Masood Azar also sends Umar.
You must remember this name, Umar.
He is the mastermind of this entire Pulwama attack.  At
that time these people used to cross the border wearing dark colours.
So what does Omar do
?  Wearing a grey Calvin Klein T-shirt, he reaches
Kashmir using a tunnel from Sukhmal side in Pakistan.  Now
look, your question would be that how are
these people crossing the LOC so easily and
reaching Kashmir.  Is there no one to stop
them?  So look, the
entire area of ​​LOC is very
complicated and in order to go from one
side to the other, Jaish-e-Mohammed had built many 3
metre wide and 25 metre deep multiple
tunnels below the LOC, no matter how many borders you build or fencing you do.
These people used light cement in between while making it so that
it does not get compressed and they used to plant trees etc. at the entry and exit points.
So it would become
very difficult to catch these tunnels.
This is the border of Kathua and Sambha districts.
In this entire area,
Jaish-e-Mohammed had built many tunnels.  It was
also very difficult to stop this.  And
when these tunnels were caught,
Pakistani products were also found inside these tunnels
where terrorists used it.  Once a
bottle of Fanta from Gujranwala, Pakistan was
also found.  So using these tunnels,
Umar reaches Bainula in Kashmir.
And as soon as Umar reaches there there
was an OGW Ashaq Ahmed Naingr.  He was already
waiting there with a truck.  There were
sacks of flour inside this truck and he was
waiting with them so that
he could hide among those sacks.  There was one Mahajan Flour Mill.
From there he got all these sacks of flour
filled.  So in this way, Umar and Usman
both reach Kashmir.
At that time there was an OGW named Abbas Rather in Kashmir.
Its purpose is to
arrange safe houses for terrorists inside Kashmir.
It had a very big network.  And
whenever Jaish-e-Mohammed used to send any terrorist from PoK, it
was Abbas who was responsible
for stopping them and whatever arrangement was made for changing their safe house from time to time,
Abbas used to look after it all.  So
he was the one who had made the arrangements for Usman and Umar also.
Umar used to change two-three safe houses
after a few days but
after that there was a Kashmiri named Shakir Basar.   He
makes his house a safe house
and stays there for a long time.   The
entire planning happens here.  Everything etc
gathers here.  He will come forward now.
Now when Umar was changing safe houses,
once there was this man named Peer Tariq Ahmad.
When his house was made a safe house and he stayed there, then
as per the rule, the safe house has to be
changed after every some time.
But what happened was that Umar fell in
love with Insha, the daughter of Pir Tariq.  So he
starts staying here more often.  Umar
also gave Insha a Redmi Note 5 Pro mobile.
And at this time, all the phones he had
bought were
bought from Gulshan Mobile Shop in Bilal Badgam.  And
after some time,
these people also included Insha in their mission.  This
is his photo from that time.  Now, on the other hand, Adil had
also joined Jaish-e-Mohammed
and
what Jaish-e-Mohammed does for a major attack is that Adil and
with him were 70 other young Kashmiris.  They
call them for training in POK
and their training is
held in Balakot and Bahawalpur.
Now as soon as this thing happens, after this on
March 19, 2018, Adil and all his school friends
disappear from their homes.
Adil's family
searches for him for many days.  But when it is not found,
a report is filed at Kakapura police station in Pulwama district.  And
everyone was searching for him for about 10-15 days.
And then in the first week of April,
Adil's photo suddenly appears on social media
in which Adil is standing with an AK-47 and in it
he announces that he has now
joined Jaish-e-Mohammed and
also tells his code name as Waqas Commando of Gundibag.
Now when this image came, the Indian forces did
not take it seriously and
put it in the C category list of terrorists.
Those in A category are more dangerous.
Those in C category are less dangerous than that.
But this Adil of C category was going to
make a big splash in the future.
Now after this, Adil and his friends
reach PoK.  And
after reaching PoK, their specialized
training starts.  And when this entire
training was going on, his trainer at that time
was Abdul Rashid Ghazi.  And
whenever the training started, it was their
choice as to which category you want to
select.  There are two categories one ist
shaadi and the other is inggi masi.
In this department, one gets training to be a suicide bomber
and in Ingmasi, all the work of suicide fighters etc. is done.
Adil had
selected this marriage category.
Here I was taught how to make this etc.
Driving with a loaded RDX was
taught and the entire training was completed
here.  And when the entire
training was going on, Abdul Rashid
Ghazi, who was their trainer, liked Adil the
most because he had
more hatred
for the Indian Forces than the others.  Secondly, he was even
ready to sacrifice his life.  And Adil was a local from the place where Jaish-e-Hamad
's leadership was planning to attack.
So he knew every inch of it.
So when Adil's training is completed,
he also crosses the Jammu Sambha Sector
border and
comes back to Kashmir.  Now from here,
Usman, Umar, Adil all had reached Kashmir
and now after this the attack was about to happen.
Well, there was one more thing in this, all the
people who were coming after crossing the border, NIA has
also mentioned this in its charge sheet
that these people were bringing with them in
small quantities in their bags, military grade RDX,
which is not available in the open market,
around 20 to 25 kg. For example,
when Umar had come, he had brought 25 kg of RDX with him
and all this was at
different locations inside R Kashmir, the
OGWs used to handle it and all these
things that I am telling you,
you will find the link of it in the description, I am
not telling anything out of my own will and see, now
after this comes the date 30th October
2018 and on this day Usman who was a sniper and used to
attack by seeing the light of the mobile was
killed by the Indian Forces.  Now when he was
killed by Indian forces, it
was a big turning point due to which the
planning of Pulwama attack got further
triggered.  Masood Ahar's two most
important family members.  The first one, Talha and the
second one, Usman, both of them were killed.  And
as soon as Masood Azar comes to know about this thing,
Masood was very angry that day and
he also sends a recorded message of 3 minutes 49 seconds
to Umar.  This voice note basically
says that there is no need to wait anymore.  Revenge must be
taken as soon as possible.  And on top of the voice note
itself he named this entire operation as ‘
Kiss Operation’.  Meaning a revenge
operation.  And then after this, Masood Azhar,
after talking to Umar, sends his close
trusted bodyguard Mohammad Ismail,
also known as Lambu Bhai,
to Kashmir.  He also carries 11 to 12 kg of
RDX on his back and
reaches Kashmir.  And Masood Azhar gets approval for a
VBID
vehicle borne improvised explosive
device based Fida.
Look, all the militants etc. who
enter Kashmir, it is in their hands to fire a bomb or if there is
an informer of an Indian agency and they want to
kill him, then they do not need approval for that.
They
can take on the spot decisions themselves.  But whenever a major
military attack has to be carried out on a large convoy,
approval is required from the leadership of Jaish-e-Mohammed and Pakistan's ISI as well.  So as soon as
this plan gets approved, all these
people who had reached Kashmir,
start planning for VBID based Fida.
And Adil Dar is
selected to execute this entire attack
and the
money needed for this entire attack is deposited by Masood
Azar in two bank accounts Alt Bank and Meezan
Bank with Rs 10 lakh which
reaches Umar through hawala.
Some more transactions had taken place during the investigation.
This cheque book which was seized is a
copy of that. The money which they had
transferred and circulated through the chat is the
original copy of that WhatsApp chat.  So
according to the plan, Adil would
use the car to launch a
VVID attack on the army convoy and
for this, these people started collecting all the material
so that a bomb could be made.  The
attack had to be bigger.  So for so many
days, they were bringing RDX from PoK in small quantities to
different places in Kashmir, and
Umar
started collecting it at one place through his handlers.  And
what do they do along with it?  Pulwama,
Kuno, Avantipura, Lethpura had cement
mines where gelatin sticks were used.
These are basically a commercial
explosive.  These also are very less in number when there is a need to make a blast.
So what do these people do?  They take help from local OGWs
and collect 500 gelatine sticks in batches of 5 to 10 kg by
smuggling them.
The sticks
he had collected had '
Super Power 90' written on them and along with these
he also collected other things like 30 kg silver
aluminium powder, weighing machine, 80 kg ammonium
nitrate and a blue coloured plastic drum from Kakapura market.
They ordered ammonia through Amazon and when
all the things had arrived, these people had to decide
where it would be assembled.  So
Umar mainly used to stay at Shakir's house
or go to Insha's house.  So
Umar decided to make a bomb at Shakir's house.
And whatever stuff they had brought for him, there was
a store on the roof of Shakir's house.
Started collecting it right there.
And along with this, Shakir was there
on whose roof they were collecting all these things.
It also had a furniture store above the highway.
So Umar made Shakir sit at the furniture shop
and he was given the task to
note down the movement of all the army convoys coming on the highway in a notebook on a daily basis and
pass on the information about everything.
So this is what Shakir Daily used to do.  He used to
note down everything and occasionally he would go to
nearby areas on his scooter.  He used to
make videos there and within a very short time,
Shakir had remembered everything.
He had found out that the blue truck with
khaki trapulins carried luggage.
Officers are in white gypsies.
Soldiers travel in blue buses.
And along with this, when Cornvoy is about to arrive, the
ROP team arrives.  He had
noted down everything and used to
send every detail to Umar.  So one day on
27th January 2019, Shakir
sends a video of the location of NH 44 highway
to Umar.  And Umar would have loved this location
as it also had an empty service lane around it.  There
was less barricading.  So here it was
very easy to take any unknown car on the highway.
So these people fix this location
so that whenever anyone comes to this place, they will
attack.  Well, while they were
doing all these things here, on the other hand the Indian
intelligence agencies were getting back to
back intelligence.  The first input
came on January 2, 2019.  What mission is Jaish-e-Mohammed going to
work on
in South Kashmir?  This entire information was sent to the Jammu
and Kashmir Director General of Police and
Inspector General of Police the same day.
But nothing happened that day.
Next day again Indian agencies
prepared a complete report named
Impending Danger.  In this he had mentioned
that some big attack could happen in the CRPF camp.
Then after 4 days, input came
that local youths were going to attack using some IEDs.
In this way, on January 18,
input came that 20 terrorists had reached Avantipura
and were about to attack.  Similarly, on
January 21, January 24, even
a day before the day the attack was to take place, an
input had come.  In this way, a total of 11 intelligence
reports came that a major attack was about to happen.
You can pause the screen and read
what was exactly written
in those intelligence reports.  But no
action takes place.  Now after this
all the material was collected.
But a car was also needed for the attack.  So
in the last week of January, Umar was
an OGW named Sajjad.  He gives him the task to
buy a car in which
two large containers can fit.
What does Sajjad do?  He buys
a 2011 model PL Blue Eco car with registration
number JK03C186 for ₹1,85,000
and immediately after purchasing it,
he
erases the chassis number of the car.  He takes it to Shakir's house where the entire
assembly was to take place and parks it there.
Now what happens next is that Umar comes to
know from one of his sources that
a large convoy of CRPF is going to arrive on the Sixth of February 2019.
So whatever these people were
making, they sped up the whole process
a lot.  Umar was the one who was making this entire
bomb because Umar had taken
training in making VBID in Sangin, Afghanistan.  So Umar himself
assembled the entire bomb.  Everyone else there was
helping.  So after this,
he started coating
ammonium
nitrate gelatin sticks
with ammonium powder, layer by layer, in a blue container and an orange container and adding them to the container layer by layer.  A
total of 200 kg of
explosives was prepared and 40 kg was
put into an orange container and 160 kg was
put into a blue container and fitted in the middle seat of the car
and the main
switch which operated it was
placed near the steering wheel of the car.  Now the entire car was
ready.  Now these people were just
waiting for the exact date of the CRPF convene and said
that they would do it on the day they would know.
They had no regrets during the time they were making it.
He was not scared at all, in fact he
even had fun while making it.   While
making the film, they used to apply silver aluminium powder
on their hair, face and clothes and then get their
photographs taken.  This
is his original photo.  While this whole process was going on,
these people were also mentally
preparing Adil so that Adil does
not back out at the last moment.  And in case
Adil backs out,
he had kept a man named Yawar Ahmed Nazar
ready as a backup.  They had to show this entire track in
such a way that the youth of Kashmir is
doing this because they are fed up with the Indian Government.  Pakistan has
no role in this.  And for this reason they had
already decided that they would
get a video made from Adil in advance and
release it after the attack.  So
what they do for this is that on 27th January 2019,
Umar takes Adil to Insha's house.  He
gives a script to Adil that a
video has to be made and after reading this script he has to
speak like this.  Adil is made ready.  The
M4 rifle is handed over.  A
banner of Jaish-e-Mohammed is put up at the back.
And after that the video making starts again.
This is that image.
You will also find the full video on YouTube.  But
a problem arises while making the video.
Adil was not able to speak the script that is in the video.
When Adil is unable to speak even after trying a lot.
So these people keep Adil in the video
and put someone else's voice over.
That's why Adil was just talking in the video.  The
script was read by someone else.  So
this was going on here on this side.
What was happening on the other side was that when soldiers go
on holiday, after coming back
they
gather at the transit camps and then
go to their respective postings through the convoy.  Similarly, this
Jammu Transit Camp is
situated behind the Jammu Railway Station.  Here the
CRPF jawans who were returning from holidays were
gathering and it was decided
that after arriving here,
in the first week of February, their convoy would be
sent towards Srinagar via NH 44 Highway.
They had to go towards Srinagar from Jammu Transit Camp.
This Jammu transit camp,
where soldiers were gathering, had a
capacity of 1000 soldiers.  But he
was stopped here.  There were many reasons for that.
Firstly, intelligence reports were coming in that
Cornway could be attacked.  Secondly, there were
some sensitive dates at this time also.  Like
Fifth of February.  Kashmir Solidarity Day is celebrated on this day.
And then, on 9th and 11th February, the
death anniversaries of Maqbool Bhatt and Afzal Guru were coming, these were
very sensitive dates.  So at
this time the chances of attack
increases significantly.  So due to this, they were being
stopped and it was being decided on which
date they should be sent.  But the problem was that
due to the delay, the soldiers present at the Jammu transit camp were
gathering beyond their capacity.
So after multiple meetings
it was decided that the
CRPF convoy will be sent on Sixth of February 2019.  There will be
no further waiting.  And
then as soon as this date is decided on the Fourth
of February 2019, heavy snowfall starts on this very day
and the
snowfall does not stop even on the next day i.e. Fifth of February
and because of this the NH 44 highway gets
blocked.  Secondly, on the same day i.e. on
Fifth of February 2019,
Masood Azhar held a rally in Peshawar, Pakistan.  In that
also he talked about an attack in Pulwama.
This cornboy had to pass through the same area.
So after seeing all these things the convoy was
stopped and the number of soldiers at Jammu transit
camp was increasing.  Now when
this situation was happening, the then Governor of Jammu and Kashmir,
Satyapal Malik, had
later said in an interview that at
that time he had told the government to get the
airlift done.  But he
said that the government did not listen to him.  Now
after this the snowfall stops and by 13th of
February the NH 44 highway is cleared.
And then when there is no option
left, the date is fixed that on
14th of February 2019, the CRPF
convoy will leave from Jammu Transit Camp.
And when all this is finalised,
then on the same day, 13th of February 2019, the CRPF
unit is also informed that
your convoy has to leave at 3:30 in the morning the next day.
This convoy had
CRPF soldiers in 78 buses.  Which is
271 Km through NH 44 highway.  Had to complete the journey of.
Normally the cornvoys are
not so big but for so many
days, because of the wait, the crowd had become very
large.  So that is why
permission was granted for this big convoy.  Now on the
next day i.e. on 14th February 2019 at
3:30 in the morning, CRPF buses, 15
trucks, two ITBP buses, a spare bus,
recovery van, ambulance and at the end, the
head assistant commandant of the convoy
started getting ready to leave in his white gypsy.
And just before this convoy left,
two things happened.  In this convoy, bus
number five, which was blue in colour and had the number
HR 490637, was going to be
attacked later.
Head Constable Kripal Singh was to drive it
and as his daughter was getting married, he had
applied for leave.  So everyone was
discussing that if by mistake there is
snowfall again then they might miss their daughter
's wedding.  So at such a time
Jaimal Singh said to himself that
I will drive the bus in his place.  You should not
take the risk of your daughter's marriage.  Secondly, in the same bus
number five,
CRPF constable Thaka Belkar from Ahmednagar, Maharashtra was also going to get
married after 10 days.  So he had
taken leave.  So
their leave gets approved just before the convoy departs.
So at the last moment they got
off from bus number five and this coincidence was such that
later both their lives were saved.  Now the
CRPF convoy had to leave from here in some time.
Whenever a convoy leaves,
before it leaves, as per the rules, there are
anti-sabotage checks which are done by the road
opening parties i.e. the accused.
What happens in this is that
soldiers are sent on the convoy route.
First the accused checks the entire route and secures
that there is no issue etc.
After the accused says okay, the convoy
leaves.  So when this convoy also had to leave, the
team of the accused went out to check the NH 44 highway.
This team of the accused had been investigating the
10 Km area of ​​NH 44 till Hathi Mod on the highway for years.
It had to be checked from 262.2 milestone to 272.2 milestone.  So the accused
's team checks this route and takes position at a total of 10 points.
And one point
which Laddu Board had at 272 milestone.
Here Assistant Sub Inspector Mohan
Lal was seated with his team at 7:15
so that if any suspicious activity is seen then
immediate action can be taken.  Now this was going on here.  On the
other hand, Umar had got his vehicle ready and was
waiting for the CRPF
convoy to arrive on NH 44.  Then what happens is
that Shakir Basir who was
doing Reiki etc. from his furniture shop.  When its sight falls on NH 44,
it sees that the accused is being
deployed.
Seeing the accused he understands that the convoy is going to arrive today.
He immediately calls Umar from there and tells him to
get ready and immediately Umar and
all his people get ready.  Now the
convoy starts moving from here and
after some time the convoy crosses the Shyama Prasad
Mukherjee Tunnel and reaches Peera.  There
was no problem till now.
Earlier, in the area called Peera, the convoy used to stop here and have
lunch etc.  But so much
intelligence input had come.  So considering it a prone
area, those who used to stop here for lunch did
not stop here.  Now when this convoy was
moving, the local traffic around it was
also moving along.  This happened long
before the fact that when the cornvoy was on,
local traffic was not allowed due to security
reasons.  But in 2003, the Jammu and Kashmir
Government strongly opposed this and the
traffic used to travel on the entire road due to the cornvoy.  So this rule was removed at that time.
So that's why the local
traffic was also moving around the buses of Cornvoy.
Because at that
time, the more important thing than the lives of the soldiers was that people should
not be late.  Now after this, at 2:02, the
convoy turns left from the highway and reaches Kazigund Transit
Camp.  There was no problem even here.
After reaching the Qazigund transit camp, the CRPF soldiers who were
posted in Anantnag, Kulgam and Shopian
areas disembark there.  Now
after this, the rest of the convoy had to
move ahead and the area ahead was very
sensitive.  The history of this area has
been that most of the attacks have taken place on
Cornvoy.  Therefore, a rule was already
made that whenever the
cornboy passes through this area, he will travel only in a semi-bullet proof bus,
otherwise he will not go.  But the
problem was that there was only a 15 cm bullet
proof bus and the crowd was very large.
So for this, normal buses were also allowed to go ahead.
Bus number five was
not bullet proof.  And while we were leaving this Qazigund
transit camp, another
thing happened.  When the convoy started moving forward from here, the
CRPF constable Surendra Yadav, who was sitting in bus number five,
his friend was
forcefully calling him from behind and asking him to come
near him and he too got annoyed and got
down and went to his friend.
He had no idea at that time
that his life was going to be saved by this one thing
because within a few moments everything in this bus number five was going to be
destroyed and
after Surendra Yadav got down, there were 39 soldiers inside this bus.
Now at 2:42 the convoy had
left Qazigund transit camp.  Someone was
listening to a song.  A soldier was on a video call
and some people were talking among themselves and at the same
time, the accused's team was supporting the entire convoy at
different strategic points
and both sides of the highway were standing on alert
and the convoy was moving ahead.  Now, on the
other hand, Umar sends Adil away in the
car that was with Shakir.
And after walking a little further,
when Hajibal Bridge arrives, Shakir
hugs Adil here and Adil takes
off his watch and gives it to Shakir as a token that
when I die, this will remind you of me.
And then after this,
Adil drives alone from Hajibal Bridge to attack.  Let
me explain the entire map to you once.
This entire area is
within Pulwama district.  This
is the complete NH 44 highway here.  The CRPF convoy was moving from this
side, from Jammu Transit towards Srinagar.
Next to it, there is a road which was connected to NH 44
from here.  This point is called Laddu turn.
ASI was here and the
other road was coming here from Hajibal Bridge.
Now Adil moves across this bridge.  On the
other hand, the CRPF convoy was
moving on NH 44.  Now from here Adil
moves ahead on this road.  But further ahead it
can see the police barricading etc.  So it takes a U-turn and here the
entry from Ladu turn
takes the direction towards NH 44.  By then one or two
CRPF buses had left.  I had
told you in the beginning that ASI Mohan Lal was
sitting at the Laddu turn point and monitoring it.  So as soon as they
see a car, they get alert
and they notice that this car, which is
Adil's, is moving forward at a very abnormal speed
and is
trying to enter the convoy and the
style in which the car was moving makes them suspicious of this car.
At 2:50, after seeing the car,
a coded message 44 starts flashing on the wireless frequency and CRPF walkie-talkie.
This is a high alert signal.
Everybody becomes alert.  ASI Mohan
Lal immediately stops him by blowing the whistle.
But Adil doesn't stop the car, instead he
speeds it up.  While chasing the car, ASI Mohan Lal
also started firing at it.  And as
soon as the firing starts, this car
leaves bus number three and hits bus number five.
Then he starts moving left and right
and at 3:15 he reaches the 272 milestone.  If I
talk about the exact location,
it hits near Ledpura village in Pampore tehsil of Pulwama district of Jammu and Kashmir.
The attack was so massive that bus number five was
completely destroyed.  The buses in front and behind
also get damaged.  When the explosion happened,
10 Km.  The sound of the explosion was heard from a distance.
Pieces of the bus and body parts of soldiers fell up to a distance of 500 to 600 meters.
I cannot tell you much.
From the photo of the bus you can guess
what might have happened to the soldiers sitting inside.  39
CRPF jawans and one ASI Mohan Lal who were
pursuing the attackers; total 40 soldiers were martyred
and more than 20 were injured.  This was
not a normal thing.  This was a very big attack.  Now
as soon as this happens in Pulwama, the
rescue team, Counter Terrorism Tactics,
CTT, local CRPF,
CFSL, Central Forensic Science Laboratory from Chandigarh and Delhi,
all these teams reach the location to
find out how it happened and who did it, nothing was
left, everything had
turned into small pieces.  Now when the search operation
started, the CFSL team at that time
found the crankshaft of a car.
They immediately called the
expert team of Maruti company which does technical inspection,
so that it could be found out to
whom Maruti had sold the car.
At the same time, lab results also revealed
what material was used.  What
type of person was I?  Everything had come to the fore.  And
what did the spokesperson of Jaish-e-Mohammed do after some time on the same day, 14th February 2019 at 4:30 pm?  There is a news agency in Srinagar
named Global News Service.
Sent him a video on WhatsApp.
He sent the same video of Adil and this
video started going viral very fast.
This video also reaches the security forces.  As soon as the Indian forces
saw the video, they understood that
Adil was in the video because they had
arrested him several times before and had kept
him in the C category list.  When we
got the full report, we found out
that he had also crossed the border and gone to PoK.   I have
also taken training etc.  Everything about him becomes
known, how much he has brought
into Kashmir.  This entire case was being
led by Manipur cadre IPS Rakesh Palwal.   The
video was not getting synced
and because of this they were doubting whether the
attack was carried out by someone else from Pakistan and they just got the
video made by Adil from Kashmir so that
it appeared that the attack was carried out by a Kashmiri youth.
So after this the video was
sent to the FBI of America on the same day and the
FBI helped in this and told that the
WhatsApp account from which Adil's video was sent belongs to
a lady in Kashmir, Jameela, there was a
SIM issue on her ID and
along with this it also came to light that
voice over has been done in this video.  Now the Indian
agency arrived to look for Jameela.
So it came to light that he had already died.  The
FBI
tracked the location of the WhatsApp account user.  So this
location turned out to be Muzaffarabad, across the LoC,
and it also came to light that those who
planned Pulwama
were in touch with him, and from here, for the first time, we
get a small official proof that
Pakistan is also involved in this.  Now as soon as the
name of Pakistan came up, Pakistani
actors and singers were banned.  India
stopped trading.  The Financial Action Task Force (FATF) of G7 nations has
put Pakistan in the grey list.  And the
leaders of different political parties of India used their Brahmastra
which caused maximum damage.
He condemned it in strong words.  Now,
when all these things were being investigated,
Maruti people also
sent the report of the crankshaft in which the number was
erased from many places, but even after that, they were able to
find it and the engine number was also found out.
You can see it on the screen.   The
car used in the attack was
bought and sold seven times.  And
what do Indian agencies do?  I
started catching the wires of the car along with the line
and when I reached the last wire, I
found out that Danish Rashid had
sold this car through Sajjad Maqbool Bhatt
and had taken a commission of ₹ 15,000.  Now when
Sajjad's name came up and the Indian agency
went to arrest him, he was missing from his house
and he too had
posted a photo on social media with an AK-47 in Burhanwani style and had
gone towards PoK.  Now when Sajjad is
also not found, the investigation
stops again.  There was a lot of
anger all over India.  The agencies had to catch him in a very short time
and it was
not possible just by taking the name of Pakistan.  Solid proofs also had to be collected.
Now after this, Rakesh Balwal of NIA
thought that a search operation should be started
in the areas around the place where this incident took place.
Maybe we can find something in it.  But the
problem here was that this area was a little
sensitive.  Whenever such search
operations are carried out here, stone pelting
etc. starts.
But Rakesh Balwal takes special permission from Delhi
and then on 20 January 2019,
100 NIA officers and 400 CRPF soldiers
take him with them and start the search operation
and this thing works.  The
key to a car was found in the snow next to the Jhelum River, 250 metres from where the incident took place.
10261 was written on it and
some bone pieces were found next to it.
Rakesh Balwal immediately matches those bone pieces
with the DNA of Adil's father and it
matches.  So this confirms
that this attack was
carried out by Adil and the details of the car through which it was done had
already been revealed.  But it
could not be ascertained which mastermind from Pakistan was involved in this.
Because it was
not known at all where the RDX came from.  Because
RDX is not found in such fields that
some local Kashmiri takes it and
blows up the car.  So the
most important task was to find out who were the people from Pakistan behind this.
Umar, who had done all this,
changed his location and disappeared.
Rest of this search operation and
investigation was going on here.  At the same time, the
Air Force entered Pakistan and struck the
Khyber Pakhtun area of ​​Balakot where
terror camps of Jaish-e-Mohammed were operating.
There were air strikes etc. also there.  So
what happens after this is that inside Kashmir,
Indian forces are encountering the
handlers of Jaish-e-Mohammed one after the other.
Meanwhile, on June 18,
2019, Sajjad Bhatt, who had arranged the Eco car, was
also found.  He is also
killed in Marhama Bijhara area.
But as you already know the
main guy behind this was Umar.  He
was still alive.  And the manner in which Umar was killed is a
big coincidence in itself.  What
actually happened was that Umar had been
threatening the policemen several times before this attack.  Umar from Random Number was
once a police officer in Pulwama long ago.  I
sent him a message on WhatsApp.
So an emoji of a pistol was made in it
and below it was written, Hi jaanu, I will
come to your house and kill you.  And
after sending this message this number was switched off.
So that police officer had saved this number
with 'Hi Jaanu' and got it tracked by the cyber cell.
And this message that Umar had
sent later on proves to be costly for him.
Because after this attack,
Umar needed the numbers to talk urgently.
So what did Omar do?
After the attack, i.e. on 27 March 2019, Umar
opens his 'Hi Jaanu' number and
as soon as the number opens, the
message 'Hi Jaanu' gets reflected in the monitoring system of the cyber cell
and Umar's location, which was
Sutsu Kalan, South West of Nowgam, was
detected towards Batgam and then
Umar is killed at this location.
Now Umar was killed but the Indian
forces had no idea that
they had accidentally killed the mastermind of Pulwama.
Because Umar's name
in Indian records was Idrish Bhai
and he had created a fake ID in the same name.
When he was encountered, an
M4 rifle and iPhone Samsung Note S9 Plus were
recovered from him.  But he had broken both these phones
before the encounter took place.
So the police did
not take this encounter seriously.  Everyone's focus was on
finding the mastermind of Pulwama.
And the broken mobile phones etc. that were found with Umar were
kept as is at the Jammu and Kashmir Police Station.   Didn't
even get any check done.  So what I mean to say is
that at this time the Indian agencies were
searching for the person who had already been killed.
Searched for it for many months.
But when nothing was found, then
in July 2019, NIA head Rakesh
Balwal, fed up, said that nothing was being found like this.  Let's
open old cases.
Maybe we can get some lead from that.  Now after this
all the old cases start getting opened.
But Rakesh Balwal's attention
goes towards this 'Hai Jaanu' case of Idrish.  They feel
that this Idrish Bhai could be a big fish.
And they say this
because when his encounter took place, an
M4 rifle was recovered from him.  Which is generally
used by the leadership of Jaish-e-Mohammed.  The rest of them
carry AK-47 and he also
wore clothes like Addas T-shirt etc.  So they
think that this person could definitely be a big commander.
Now when the case was reopened,
Rakesh Balwal sent the phones found at the time of Umar's encounter to
India's top computer forensic and
cyber security agency CERT-IN for analysis.  The
team of CertainTeed
worked hard for several days to extract each and every detail of the phone
and while they were extracting these details
, they seemed to have hit a huge jackpot.
Before breaking these mobiles, Umar had
deleted all the data but
as soon as we buy a new mobile,
he fetches the data of the old mobile from the cloud.  So the same thing happened in this case also.
In this way, Certain's team obtained
more than 100 GB of data from 2014 till date.
16 hours of voice notes related to the planning of Pulwama, text
messages, videos of the reconnaissance of the location,
everything was found.  And as soon as this comes to light, the
NIA team reaches there and
analyses all the data for the next 14 hours and
then they find out that Idrish
Bhai is none other than the
nephew of Pulwama mastermind Masood Azhar and the
mastermind behind the hijacking of the plane is
his son Umar who made it and then
got the attack done by Adil, this is his Pakistani
ID card and this is a photocopy of his cheque book.
Was RDX used?
Through which route was the RDX collected?
How was the entire attack coordinated?
100 calls were also received at the time of this attack.   When
NIA traced these numbers, it was found that these numbers were being
used in different cities of Pakistan and
coordination was going on from the same numbers at that time also.
A voice note was also found in which
someone was coordinating with Umar at the time of the attack
and was also asking him to destroy the mobile and
make a video.  NIAO
thought it was the Roff Python uncle from Pakistan.
So NIA matched this voice sample with the
voice sample of Rauf Chacha available in open source.
So it was an exact match.  And
this became a big proof of Pakistan's
involvement.  Along with this, intimate photos of the
mastermind Umar
with Insha in Kashmir were also
found inside this mobile.  When he was
making it, he used to get himself photographed with silver etc. applied on his face.
I found those photos.
Another photo was found in which the car from which the attack took place was
parked in front of a house.  That
was Shakir Basir's house where it was prohibited.  So the
NIA team reaches his house.  The location of his house
was Kausar Colony Bahawalpur and
on 7 December 2019, Shakir Basir was arrested.
And there were many photos of Umar and Insha in the mobile.
So the NIA team
reaches Insha's house and when they reach Insha's house, the
NIA finds a red-black colored
wooden almirah.  The same almirah
which was seen under the Jaish-e-Mohammed banner in Adildar's video.
So NIA
arrests Insha and her father Peer Tariq Shah on 3 March 2020.  Similarly,
19-year-old Owais
Ul Islam, who was preparing for NEET through Amazon account, was also arrested on March 7, 2020.
Who was providing all the goods from Amazon account.
Similarly, Mohammad Abbas,
who had a huge network of safe houses, was
caught.  Bilal Kuchhe was caught through Gulshan Mobile Shop.
He, who used to
work with Adil, had also gone to PoK.   In
this way, all the people who were involved in Kashmir were
caught and then they were made to reveal every single thing.
Initially Insha was
calling Umar her brother and was refusing.
But when NIA showed the photos and voice notes,
Insha also had to accept all these things
and she told each and every thing.  Shakir was the
toughest among all these people.  He was
not telling anything.  But
what does Rakesh Balwal do after some time?
Shows Shakir the intimate photo of Umar and Insha.
So Shakir was very shocked about this thing.
Because he considered Umar to be very
good.  Umar was married.
So Shakir was so hurt by this thing that
after some time he told the whole planning to NIA.
And then on 25th of August 2020,
NIA decodes the whole case and
files a charge sheet of 13,800 pages in the NIA court
and there is a crackdown all over Kashmir.
And everyone who was involved in this
gets punished.  And in the end, let me tell you once again that whether it is
crooked teeth or
gaps between the teeth,
you can fix every single teeth misalignment issue with the help of tooth aligners.
That too in just 6 to 12 months.  Don’t
forget to click on the link in the description to book your free teeth scan.  Thank you.
[music]