[MUSIC] What's the difference between the cheapest and the most expensive IPL tickets
[MUSIC]
[APPLAUSE]
?  Six of my teammates went to watch IPL matches.
Delhi, Kolkata and
[music]
Bengaluru.  Three out of six people
went for the cheapest tickets but the remaining three went for the most
expensive.
[ __ ].  We wanted to compare everything in these stadiums.
Come on brother, see what I
do now.  We will compare five things for each ticket.
Ticket booking experience
finally.  So the ticket is here.  Seats and Views
Seats are kind of here.  The view is
good but hopefully people will vacate it
later.  Eat?  Ok.  I don't have a sweet
tooth.  Butt Gulab Jamun, Ulala.  Condition of the toilets.
So the wash experience is a little better
actually.  What is the extremely dirty washroom and
most importantly, what are the vibes like and for
all these things we will give a rating out
of five.  Some people got box seats with
lounge access.  It was crazy-crazy.   The
other poor souls had to sit on concrete.  The
people sitting in front are
not sitting on any seats.  They are sitting on the floor below.
So let's cover IPL
experience from ₹1000 to ₹1 lakh
experience.  First, let us understand
what the setup is.  The setup is that I have divided my six
team
members into two parts.
Girls will get the most expensive
tickets and boys will get the cheapest ones and
they have to show their experience of that match.
Why this gender divide?  [ __ ] #shittag mens
rights.  No friend, I think you will realise
why I took this decision?  You
also know what civic sense is like
and I did not want to send a female team
member for a ₹700 ticket and something bad
happens.  It won't matter if it happens with the boy.
Uncle you are wrong.  But
anyway let's come back to the video.  So
first let's talk about the ticket booking
experience for the RCB vs Rajasthan
Royals match.  Which was attended by
Antara and Am.  But the problem arose right in the beginning
because
you can buy RCB tickets only from the official website.
Not from any third party vendor like
Paytm or District.  My
objective was to buy the most expensive ticket.  But
brother, these tickets are not available on the official website.
We had to go to a travel agency.
And you know what he
told us, a box ticket worth ₹42,000 will be
available in black for
₹19,000.
Antara asked why are the tickets in black so
expensive?  So the travel
operator said that you will
not get online tickets.  Such tickets are sold through us only.
Because everyone knows
that the demand is very high.  Whatever the
price, be it 500, 1 lakh or 2 lakh people will
buy it.  And you know
what else he said.  This trick is very important to
save tax.  So let's decide
that we will buy the ticket of GR Vishwanath Stand for
₹109,000.  But as soon as
we decided this the tickets got sold.  Then
we said okay give me the second most expensive one,
that too got sold.  So finally we
got Rahul Dravid Lawn
[Music]
ticket from Qatar Airways whose official price is
₹27,000 and we got it for ₹69,000.  what a
deal bro.  So now I bought the most expensive ticket
from Chaswami.  Now buy the cheapest
ticket.  So we bought the cheapest ticket for ₹2300, but
got the cheapest ticket in black for ₹6500 and
got the most expensive one available as well.  Now
we had to get the tickets in hand.  So,
a day before the match, Am and
Antara went to Rajaji Nagar Metro Station to get tickets.  He
said that we meet at the metro station at Rajaji Nagar.
Where we did not find the dealer
but found the dealer's friend who would give us the ticket.
Now I did not know whether he would give it or not.
We were just going on trust.  But
finally I got the ticket.  Yes finally.  Finally.
So the ticket is here.  Now the ticket booking
experience was so crazy that is why people
say that I want to watch the match from home.
But there are many restrictions at home also
depending upon your broadcast.
And that's why I want to talk about today's sponsor, VPA.
Through Not VPN you can watch many things which are
not available in India.  Like movies or
many different sports.  There are many TV shows
on Netflix, DNS Plus and HBO which are
not available in India.  I usually
use a VPN when I
travel because the
shows I want to watch might not be available at my destination.
And this is also good
for security if you want to hide your
IP.  Especially when you are using public Wi-Fi
in airports, cafes or hotels.  If you want to check out a VPN
go on vpn.com, you will
get a great discount on the 2 year plan and you will also get 4 months free
and there is a 30 day money back guarantee, so
try it, if you don't like it then cancel it, the
link is in the description, so check it
out and now let's come back to the video.  Now let us
go from Chinnaswamy Stadium
to Arun Jaitley Stadium.  Where Veena and Mohit
wanted to watch the match of Delhi Capitals
against KKR through the District app.  But
as soon as he logged in, 750 people were
standing there.  There were same clear instructions for them also
that brother, we have to buy the cheapest and the
most expensive tickets.  But friend, I could
n't find both of them on the District app.  Both were
sold out.  So we got the second
cheapest one and the mid tier one for Rs 7,500.  So it was
difficult to buy tickets in Delhi and Bangalore.  But the
ticket booking experience for Eden Gardens in Kolkata was
actually very smooth.  Adriya got a mid
year premium ticket without drama
on Book My Show and cheap tickets were easily available on Adi
and the price was just ₹900. This was the
cheapest ticket in all the three stadiums.
Now tickets were definitely available in black outside Eden Gardens
but we had no problem.
So now we have got tickets for all three matches.
Antara and Amay will go to Chinswami
Adi and Adraja to Eden Gardens and Mohit and
Veena to Arun Jaitley Stadium.  Now let's talk about
match day.  Who has Let's See?
Am.  Letts C.  In which it was
very easy to reach Swami.  Amma took the metro, Antara took the
auto.
Reaching the stadium was easy but
entering inside the stadium was another challenge.   There is
no way to enter at the train gate.  I
almost got killed.  It is very crowded.  There were so
many policemen but the crowd management was
very bad.  Now Antara and Am were
going to watch a cricket match for the first time so they did
not know what they could carry and
what they could not.  They are not even allowing banks
inside.  I have two phones.  There is a power bank.
I have my wallet.  Where should I put it
inside now?  And there are no lockers there either.
Dev just hung the bags.  Security is a little
lax here in the locker room.
Actually there isn't even a rocker room.  Someone has
put up a temporary tent here.
₹1 and open locker.
After dropping their luggage, both of them headed towards their gate.  We have to
go to this gate
in intake.  And there's a lot of trash here, friend.   The
smell is also very bad.  And look at this line.  The
line is also very long.  Now, you will
have to wait in line.  He checked me a total of four times.
Ok?  While going inside.   There is
no four times checking even at the airport.
Antara's entry was the smoothest.  There
is no need for any waiting.  My gate?   The
red carpet was laid out for him.
Obviously brother, if ₹70,000 have been given then the red
carpet should also be laid.  I will reach in 20 minutes.
7:30 p.m.  So
I have reached the stadium.  Our gate number is 15.   The
entry of both Mohit and Veena was very smooth
and Veena was very crazy excited
because this was her first cricket match going to be
live.  This is my first experience of
watching such a match in the stadium.  So let's see how
wood goes.  Mohit was
roaming around telling his taxi driver that it is
so difficult to get IPL tickets.  Look, to
buy this ticket, just three-four days
ago I had said that it would be Rs 1200 but it gets
sold out very quickly.  Now, I had
already scared them that nothing is allowed
inside the stadium.  So
pack properly and reach early so that there is no
problem in entry.
I have to enter from main gate 17 in front of Delhi Gate number five
and you can see that I have
reached gate number 17.  The place was very
crowded but the security check was easy.   The
experience of Adi and Adrishya at Eden Gardens was very smooth compared to Bengaluru and Delhi.  Now Eden is located
in Esplanade area of ​​Kolkata which is
considered to be the busiest area of ​​Kolkata so it is
easily available to get public transport and
as there is a lot of security and sign
boards it is also easy to get the gate.
Both Adi and Adraja meet
at Gate 3 where Adraja was about to enter.
This is the entrance to Gate Number Three
from where I am going to enter.
But Adi's gate was Gate 11 and the poor guy got
killed there.  Its been 15 minutes so far.  The gate was
not found.  Where is gate number 11?  Ojit here.
I discovered that it has a completely opposite side.
Gate number 11, can we go from here?  That
poor guy kept wandering here and there for 30 minutes.
But no policeman knew
where Gate 11 was.  It took him half an hour.  Then go and make
his entry.
But the experience has just begun, etc.  The
ticket is for ₹900 and he had to climb the mountain to
reach his seat.  These are the
stairs of the stadium.  Now I have to
climb to the top.  The poor guy kept climbing the stairs to
reach his seat.  The seating
line was so narrow that one had to push others to get in and out.
And these seats are a bit too narrow.  But
poor Adi's view was absolutely useless.
He says that he had no idea what was
happening on the pitch.  The
game is going on behind but more than the game, you
can see the Ganga behind.  So I will give 21.5 for the season.
Now it is obvious that brother, if you have
got the cheapest ticket, then you will have to suffer a little.
What is the story of Amey who paid ₹300 extra?   The
seeds that were there were concrete steps, they were
not normal steps, they were slightly bigger
steps, but they were directly bolted on them.  The
seating was like sitting knees up
and the seats were plastic.
No one was very comfortable.
Now the seats were useless but the view of the am was absolutely
crazy.
My view was honestly very
good because
I was sitting perpendicular to the pitch, I was sitting on the side of square leg
or point on point.  The
bonus was that
Virat Kohli was fielding right down in the second innings.
That means, wherever I was sitting,
right below me, he was
fielding like this.  People are crazy for Kohli.
Virat Kohli looked so good.  Because of that
I would give it four out of five.
[Praise]
Am's experience was better.  Does this logic
apply to Mohit as well?  All set
for the match.
When he reached the third floor of the West Stand
, he got a big surprise.
Brother this is for sale.  It's free.  Thank you
so much.  I am going to the third floor.  But right now
I got a free jersey down there.  I thought
they were selling it.  So I asked and
they said no it is free to show your
support for the team and I also got flags.
So I took both things.  And there was a
completely panoramic view from his seat.  Wow this
looks cool.  The
view of the ground was crazy but the
view of the stadium was absolutely ugly.  You can see that there is already
no crowd yet but
people have started spreading the smell.
Now the view was okay but so many people were standing
that I couldn't see, poor
Mohit was not feeling very comfortable
but it was okay for 3 hours, I guess the
view is good for one minute but hopefully people will vacate it
later and when he once sat on the seat
he realized that brother, these are very
bad seats, friend, the seats are okay comfortable, it will be fine for
3 hours but I guess it is
not that comfortable for long duration, but when he once sat on the seat
he said that friend, not bad for ₹100.  My
initial reaction was that the seats were
uncomfortable because they looked
uncomfortable.  Actually it
is not that uncomfortable.  So overall I would
give the seat three out of five.  The shocking thing was
that Veena spent ₹7500 but her
experience was not much different from Mohit's.
The view is
phenomenal as you can see right here on the
ground we are singing right here
Veena was sitting behind the cheer leaders and she
got the full IP package
[Music]
crazy crowd so much excitement and people are
dancing and singing with the view
I feel it is going to be a full package
because I am very close to
the pitch so for this I would like to
give it a rating of four out of five and out of Adraja's
15,000 tickets I think if there is any one
highlight of my seat then it was the view from my seat.  The
view was so beautiful that as soon as I
sat down, I was shocked that I would be able to see such a beautiful view and the
pitch so clearly; this was
not my expectation.  And on top of that, such a
nice breeze was blowing that there was no
issue of heat.  So the view and seating were
absolutely high class for me.  But still
I would give it a rating of four out of five
because the seats were a bit narrow.  But otherwise
maybe that was my highlight and that's why
I enjoyed the match so much.  But
right now the experience is not that crazy.
Adraja got a very premium experience for the ₹15,000 ticket.
Chair leaders,
robots and Preity Zinta were also seen.  The
owners sit just behind where Adriya was sitting and usefully Shahrukh Khan is
there.  Now unfortunately
Shahrukh Khan did not come that day.  Otherwise Adraja would have gone
mad.  The guy who was sitting next to Adiraja
said that he
is not a fan of KKR but a fan of Shahrukh Khan.
But Antara got the queen-like treatment
for whose seat I spent ₹70,000.   The
entry way to the lounge was very classy.
I did not feel at all that I had
come to watch a cricket match.  Because I had
always heard from cricket fans that the
stadium experience is very
bad.  It is very crowded and very
hot too.  But here I
also got a wet towel at the entry.
Like I've been to a spa.  Every seat had
an RCB flag and scoreboard.
Honestly my seats were quite comfortable.   It was the
usual plastic one but there was
much gap between two days.  So one could
easily sit comfortably for 2 to three
hours.  But then the question is, was
my experience worth the Rs 27,000 ticket?  The
straight answer is no.  Firstly the seats were
fine and the view was also there, meaning I could see the pitch as well.
But I was sitting so far away that
I could not understand what was
happening on the field.  And and I was completely
relying on this TV which was in my area and there was
a TV in front of me.  So after
considering both these things I would give
my seating and view three tasks.  I think
BCCI can do better.  Now the view was not so crazy that
one had to watch it on TV to
understand the match.  But the excitement was very
crazy.  But at least Antara was
getting AC.  So now all six team members have
sat on their respective seats.  It's been
an hour or two since the match.  Now everyone is feeling
hungry.  First of all Mohit went to eat food.
How much does a samosa cost, brother?  This is one for 50 and give me one for 100. Surprise surprise,
everything was expensive and of
poor quality. Vegetarian burger was
₹200 and there was a markup of ₹20 on everything,
because of which the cost of the cold drink was also
₹100.  How much does it cost?
This small bottle costs ₹100.  Cold
drink option.
Well, this is expected.  The main problem was
that Mohit was not getting water.   There
was no free water.  One had to go very far
and even there one had to buy water.
Brother, how much does a Bisleri bottle cost?  There
is a bottle.  Is it not allowed?  There is glass.
How much is that glass?  It is for 20 rupees.  Now
Mohit took a cold drink to extinguish the fire
but he could not find the dustbin anywhere.
Also ate a samosa worth ₹50.  But Mohit got the biggest surprise
when he went to the toilet.  Going to the washroom.
So let's see how the washroom is.
ONE ETERNITY LATER OH MY GOD.  Finding the washroom
itself is a scene.  How is your
experience so far brother?  In number one.
How do you like the facilities etc.?
Facility great shoot.   It was
such a bad experience, what can I even
describe.  God the washrooms were so dirty.
Very dirty washroom.  What can I say,
you have seen it.  It was pathetic.  It
was very dirty.  And this toilet experience is of the
cricket stadium of the country's capital, a
sport that the country is crazy about.  Honestly the
toilet is so dirty that I
want to give negative marks.  But since that is
not allowed I will give it zero out of
five.  Adi and Am also had a similar experience.
I literally can't open my mouth.   The
bathroom stings so much.  And because the
half ticket was the cheapest.  Nothing was
complimentary.  There was no water and
everything was overpriced.  To be honest,
I found the momos to be okay.  It was fresh and
hot too.  So for food I will give
four out of five.  The only thing is that you will
have to buy it and eat it.  I was also very bothered
by the food.  There was access to food between matches.  Don't go there, there were
people roaming who were selling food but
everything was overpriced, ice cream worth Rs. 45 was being
sold for Rs. 100, popcorn worth Rs. 50 was being
sold for Rs. 200. There were options, I mean there was a
problem when it came to subway, there were decent options, but I would say there were
not that many, but the
biggest problem was for Ammi. Water for ammi. 1
sec 1 sec 1 sec 1 sec
[Music] It was
as if a war had broken out for water. There was
only one water dispenser for the entire stand
and no one was serving it. To get
water in the stands, you had to go
down and drink water wherever you were sitting. And
what about Adraaj and Antara
who bought tickets worth thousands of rupees. And
this is the washroom, the ticket price is Rs.
11,000, we had to pay almost Rs. 15,000.
For this price,
it is not as neat and clean as you would expect a neat and clean washroom.
I don't see any supply here.   There are
no things like tissues and sanitary napkins
in this toilet and it smells very bad.  Brother,
he has bought a premium ticket by paying thousands of rupees.
Why are clothes hanging outside the washroom
?  This is the entrance to the washroom.  This is quite
a sharp place and we
can also see some clothes drying here.  Now
thankfully his ticket included a
complimentary meal with
unlimited supply of water and cold drinks from
7:00 pm to 11:00 pm.  The buffet experience was
absolutely splendid for me.  So
many food options and such tasty food.   It
was a complete full course meal.  So here
five out of five is made by closing the eyes.
Now let us come to our Queen's
experience.  Antara who
paid ₹70,000 for premium lounge access.   There was
a staircase right next to my seat that
went up to the upper lounge, where there were lots of
snacks and beverages.
Including there was also a beer counter.  But the
best part of that lounge was that the AC was on full
blast as it was very
hot in the bore that day.  Another interesting thing that
caught my eye was that on the big
wall at the back, there were framed jerseys of all the players who have
played for RCB till date.
And everyone was
standing with those jerseys and taking photos.  There was
also a jersey of Virat Kohli.  And it was a
good experience.
She could also see the field from the lounge.
She was so happy that she immediately made a video call
to Ame who was sitting in a cheap ticket.
Antara then went to another lounge
where delicious snacks were available.
Dinner buffet opens at 7:30.  Honestly this food
was quite decent.  There were plenty of options to eat in the lounge
once the buffet was open.  There was veg as
well as non veg.  But the most
disappointing part of the food was the masala
dosa.  Because I did
not expect such a disgusting masala dosa after coming to Bangalore.  And all
in all I think for food I would give it 3.5
stars out of five.
After destroying the Masala Dosa, Antara
went to visit the toilet.  This is the washroom and it
smells really good.  The toilet was under
construction but there was no smell.
But Antara's experience became better after
talking to the staff member there.  So I had to
use the washroom.  But my hands
were full.  I had a phone, a wallet and on
top of that, there was also an RCB flag.  And there was no
place to keep anything in the washroom.
But there was a lady
helper sitting outside the washroom.  Who after seeing all this
told me that you go, I will handle it.
And he kept one of my phones and the RCB
flag with himself.  And I could use
the washroom.  And it was a very sweet thing that
she did.  But brother Veena did not enjoy it that much.
In this category in which I am, everyone
gets a free food box and
beside it, as I had shown you earlier, there is
drinking water.  But that's a little too far from the
seed but let's see what's in the food box.
But right now I would
like to give it a rating of three out of five.  And
Veena also said that the washroom cleanliness was
just average.  So the wash experience
seems to be a little better than actually
it's actually clean and the expectations for this are
very low.  It is average clean but
it is clean.  Now all this was fine.  The crazy
thing happened when Veena had to go back to her seat.
And crowd management is actually bad.  It was
half time and it seemed like there was a
stampy situation here.
Manoj Changla, who had come from Ajmer to watch the match,
watched the entire match standing.  This is a crowd management shop.  The seat is
not available.  Those who
had tits, they are already seated in the crowd.  So
we are not able to sit on that seat.  We are
standing and watching.  Leave this matter aside,
Veena's lunch box was also
lying on the ground.  And when it was becoming clear
that Delhi was losing, the atmosphere became
completely useless.  After half time, the
whole vibe of this
area changes and the people have changed.  The people who were
sitting around me before half time are
not visible and the new
crowd is now standing on their seats.
Racist comments can also be heard and people are
shouting.  I have made him an uncle.
So the overall vibe has gone down a lot
after half time and
that is why the vibe rating is 2.5 out
of five.  People started leaving early and the
stadium became a garbage dump.
And this was not just Veena's experience.
Mohit also complained about the same thing.
Friend, one thing that is very frustrating
while watching a match is the lack of civic sense.
People who take beverages and snacks on the seats
, throw them there.   There are
dustbins everywhere, friend.  Go and
throw it in the dustbin.
This thing is very unnoticing.  Now regarding the garbage,
both Mohit and Veena agree.  But
Mohit said one thing which I
felt while watching the match today.  It’s that there is
n’t a very passionate home crowd.
Unusually home crowds in sports stadiums are
very die hard and passionate types.
But there is a very mixed crowd here.
You can see in my stand also, there are many
KKR fans.  And like if KKR is
hitting fours and sixes then everyone is
celebrating.  Same thing is happening in Delhi also.
So it doesn't feel fiercely
competitive.  The vibe is
not a very competitive sporty vibe.   It
means a bit like a fair.  It
is like a festival.  People are taking selfies, dancing.  There
is nothing wrong in this.  People are
enjoying and I have also come to enjoy.   It was
clear to Mohit that it was
not the case that people in Delhi were completely biased
towards Delhi.  He has just come to have fun.  Look
how funny this is.  This brother who is
sitting behind me.  He supported Delhi throughout the match.  Was
wearing Delhi jersey.  And now
Delhi is losing.  He has taken off his jersey.
And now they are supporting KKR.
So that's it.  This is what I was saying,
that people like this are not very hardcore
supporters.  Have come to have fun.
having fun.  Which is great.
[MUSIC]
He also spoke to a father and son, Kamal and Dev.  Will
you tell the people who will watch this video on TV that they
should come to the stadium to watch it?   It
is worth it, it is worth it.  You must gain experience.
You have that different thing that you will bury in your life.  One should
have this kind of experience once.
But there was no unbiased crowd in Bengaluru.  It
is on the side.  In the second innings,
Rajasthan Royals were being completely roasted.
Now Antara is not a crazy cricket
fan.  But I understood one thing.  The
craze for RCB in the city is no joke,
brother.  But the experience was
very energetic.  It was crazy crazy.   The
crowd would go silent with every four and six,
and go crazy after every wicket.
In the second innings it seemed that
Rajasthan would win.  But at the end
RCB was winning the match and in the last over they
needed 13 runs from just one ball.  Everybody became absolutely silent.
Just waiting for RCB to win the
match.
[Praise]
And a similar experience was seen in Kolkata also.
[Applause]
[Music]
KKR fans were enjoying this experience a lot.
Even if Punjab hit sixes and fours.
But brother, garbage is one thing that unites us all.
He sees that
when the match is over, people move towards the exit.
Now the exit was smooth for Amay and Antara.  The
commute was very easy.  That means
this Chinoswami is situated just next to the Cubbon Park Metro Station.  Yes, the metro
closes at 11:00 clock or 11:30.
But especially for the match
they kept a metro till ah late night 12:30.
Mohit said that exiting from Delhi was
actually a bit uncomfortable.  The
exits in Delhi were not disabled friendly.
A disabled man had to
go down three floors on his own.  Poor guys Adi and Adraja had
a spoilt spot
as it started raining and the match got
over early.
Everybody is coming inside now because of the rain.   The
premium exit was very smooth but
for the poor guy who came with the cheaper ticket, the
exit was very bad and
they stopped people for 30 minutes
[music].  In
fact, Adi said that many women were
also feeling unsafe.
A woman actually even complained
that a man was misbehaving with her.
But thankfully the police stopped that thing.   The
overall summary is that the vibes are
unmatched.  You will know that only in the stadium.
But the world's richest cricket
board is running one of the richest leagues in the world.
And most people don't have proper seats.  There
is no free water.  The toilets
are absolutely useless.  Come on BCCI I think we can
fix that.
And don't forget to check out the VPN
link in the description at vpn.com.
You are getting a good discount on the attractive two year plan
with four months free.