9 December
2024 Santosh Deshmukh is waiting in his Tata Indigo car
at a petrol pump in B District of Maharashtra.  This place is
30 Km.  Far away is Majajok village where
Santosh is a sarpanch.  At 3:00 pm
his maternal uncle's son Shivraj comes there.  Then
both of them go together in the car towards the village.
As soon as they cross a toll gate towards the village
, suddenly a
black Scorpio car comes in front of them.   The
license plate number is MA 444z 933
Six men come out of that car, they
break the glass of Santosh's car with a stone to
see
who is inside, then one man opens the door, takes the Sarpanch
out and starts beating him with a stick,
then these six men drag the Sarpanch and
put him in the Scorpio car and leave at
6:30 in the evening, 15 kms from their village.
Far away, the Sarpanch's dead body is found on the roadside
[MUSIC].
Now many of you might be wondering
why I am making a video on the murder case of a Sarpanch leader of a village in Maharashtra
?  Many murders happen in our country.
What is the need to make a video on this
?  I am making this video
because this
case is a very colourful example of
all the problems in our country and how
goons are given a free hand in our country.
How these goons work with politicians
and how due to the coordination between these politicians and
goons, work and business
cannot be done.  Piyush Goyal had
recently said that look at the innovations the Chinese companies are
doing.  Work on
developing electric mobility, battery
technologies, semiconductors is growing.
Artificial Intelligence is being
created for its own country and for its people.  Building
chips, AI models.  What are Indian companies doing
?  What should India do?  Do you want to make ice cream
or chips?  Indian
companies are fighting with the strongmen.  But
Santosh Deshmukh was also murdered by a strongman.
Valmiki Karad, who is this Valmiki
ji and why because of this Valmiki
a big minister of Maharashtra had to resign
and why if our country has to
progress then this rule of the powerful will have to end.  To
investigate all these things,
I read the 900 page charge sheet
regarding the murder of Santosh Deshmukh.  So let us know
about the goonda raj
in the beat district of Maharashtra.  Before we move on to the video,
if you're willing to invest in yourself for just a weekend,
I'd like to
recommend the free 2-day AI training program from
Outskill.  This is an AI focused education
program attended by top founders and
investors.  Normally the
cost of this program is around ₹5000 and it is
free for my audience.  This training will be held
this weekend i.e. Saturday and Sunday from
11:00 am to 7:00 pm.
That is 16 hours of continuous live AI
training.  In this training, you will learn
how to use over 20 AI tools to
automate various tasks.  If you want to do
data analysis without
coding,
how can you use Excel and presentations and how are no code
tools used?  How
can you develop AI agents and
how can you boost your productivity manifold?
Be it sales, marketing
, freelancer or business owner,
this training is relevant for many people.
More than 1 lakh people have taken this training
in more than 40 countries.
Book your slot in the link description and don't
forget to join the WhatsApp group where
you will get updates.  And remember, there is an
introductory call on Friday at 7:00 p.m.  So don't
forget to join it.  Now let's come
back to the video.
Massaj Jok is a small village in Kaj taluka of D District.
A Mumbai-based company, Avaada Energy, is
setting up a renewable energy project in this village.
In this project, she will install several wind turbines in the village.
One turbine requires about 7 acres of
land and it costs Rs 28 crore.
Avaada Energy has claimed that it will
invest ₹350 crore through this project in the Beat District.  All the wind
turbines together will generate 40 MW of power.  Due
to which, Wankhede Stadium
can power 10 IPL matches.  Now
Vada Energy has chosen the beat districts
because the wind potential is good there and
because in the traditional areas where such
projects are set up like Satara and
Sangli, there is a lot of competition now.  Now
a lot of land is needed for this project.
Therefore, Avaada Energy
started talking to the farmers of Massa village to acquire their land from 2023 itself.
Many villagers are
actually very happy because
around 150 people will
get jobs through this project.  But in May 2024,
problems started arising in this project.
Many senior employees of the project started
receiving calls from local strongmen and goons
demanding extortion money worth ₹ crores.
They threaten the company that either give
us ₹ crores or this project will be closed.
Which strongman is giving this threat
?
Valmiki Karad Valmiki Karad is a local
strongman. Valmiki from Parli area of ​​B District grew
up in a simple farmer's family but he hit the jackpot when he
became the right hand man of Dhananjay Munde,
a veteran leader of Ajit Pawar's Nationalist
Congress Party. Now Valmiki does
not hold any official post in the party but he
handles all the matters of Dhananjay Munde
in B District and Valmiki used this very thing to
increase his power in the district and to
start an extortion racket.  It is as if he has
started an organised criminal network.
Where many gangs
come under his control.  But he extorts money from many companies.
If any company or
person did not listen to him then
he would either file fake cases against them through the police or get
their entire business closed down.
About 15 criminal cases have been registered against Valmiki.
Attempted Murder,
Extortion, Cheating, Fake Writing,
Unlawful Assembly and many more.  In fact,
even after last year's Lok Sabha elections, a
case of attempt to murder was registered against him.  Now,
due to recovery, he has no shortage of money.
Be it high-end cars or land,
he lives a life of complete luxury.  In fact, a
BJP MLA claimed that Valmik
owns property worth more than ₹100 crore in Pune alone.
Now
how did Valmiki earn so much money?  And this is the recovery that
Valmik was doing when he called Avada Energy
and said give me ₹ crores or
else I will shut down your project.  On
May 28, 2024, at 11:00 am, the
project manager of Avaada Energy company was
kidnapped by Valmiki's men.  The
project manager did
lodge a complaint but the situation went from bad to worse.  A
few months later, on August 28 at
5:00 pm, the project manager
received a call from Valmiki.
Hey, I know your work is going on over there.   Either
you come and meet me here in Parley or
stop all your work.  So the
land acquisition manager of the company
tells Valmiki on the phone that I will come to meet you.
After 15 days, another call
comes from Valmiki and he repeats that you
come to meet me in my office.  On October 8, the
land acquisition manager of Shivaji Company
finally goes to meet Valmik.
what?  Should you tell my demand
to your seniors or not?  If you want to continue the work here then you will
have to give me Rs. 1 crore right now.  Otherwise all work will have to be stopped
in Beed.  If you are not able to do it then
give me the number of your senior.  But now these
threats have not stopped.
On November 29, one of Valmiki's goons
calls the company back and says that
Anna wants to talk to you.  Then at
1:00 pm that day, one of Valmiki’s
men named Sudarshan reaches the site of Avaada Energy.
Sudarshan is a 26 years old local goon
in Valmiki's team and everyone in the area
knows that Sudarshan basically does Valmiki's
dirty work.  hey did you talk to Anna
?  Hey, why do you want to create unnecessary trouble?
I have come here for only one thing.
Anna has told Bhim to stop all this work.
Ok.  Last time I
stopped your work.  You guys had
complained against me, right?
Anna just came to know about all this.  Hey, he has gone crazy.
Right now I know that your
work is going on at four or five more places.  Hey my whole
family, I will go straight to Anna now.
Anna has the
account of your minutes.  Now you see
what you have to do with Anna's demands
?  Shivaji who is the land acquisition manager of the company.
He
also gave a statement to the police regarding this incident that
Sudarshan had told me to
go and meet Valmiki.  If I had not done this the
company's business would have stopped.
And I would also get threats about my life.
Sudarshan again threatens that today
you will have to meet Valmiki.  So
out of fear, Shivaji goes to
meet Valmiki at 2:00 in the afternoon.  And here
Valmiki asks him,
what happened to what I told you?  Shivaji says
that whatever Valmiki told him, he has
informed his seniors and he will
remind them.  Now despite all these things the
threats did not stop but the company
refused to pay ₹ crores.  Then on December 6,
Shivaji gets a call.  Sudarshan is on the line
who asks if Shivaji is
in the office?  Then after a few hours a black
Scorpio car MA 44
z93 arrives outside the company gate.
Sudarshan and his three men are inside the car.
One of the men asks the security guard to
open the company gate.   The
security guard says that you let me talk
to an officer of a company and I will
open the gate for you.  Sudarshan then
threatens the guard and says I am Sudarshan Gore.
Do you have the guts to stop me?
Your mother’s.
Sudarshan and his men then get out of the car
and
break the gate and enter inside.  As a
security guard tries to stop them,
one of Sudarshan's men takes a stick and
starts beating him.  When other guards
try to help, the goons
beat them up too and threaten to
kill them if they interfere in their case.  Hearing this fight,
Shivaji reaches the gate.  Sudarshan
abuses him a lot and says, hey
either give me two shops or close down
your company Vinni.  At the same time,
an official of the company
calls Santosh Deshmukh, the Sarpanch of Masajok village to ask what is happening in the company.
Santosh Patil Rao Deshmukh was
a sarpanch of Massajok village in B District.   A
married man with two children, he was
involved in village politics since 2013.   In
fact his family has been involved
in the village for a long time.  His wife also
became Sarpanch in 2017 and after 5 years, he himself became Sarpanch.
Between 2017 and 24, his village
also received 19 awards for development.
Like, he got the award for the best water supply
and sanitation system in Marathwada, which is a
very big thing because in the Marathwada region, there is
less rainfall due to which water is
like gold.  Veteran politicians like Sharad Pawar
also praised Santosh.  By
saying that he is a
representative who does not get involved in controversies
but works hard for his society.
That is why when Avadha's
security guard called the Sarpanch and informed him that there was some
trouble here.  Immediately the Sarpanch
arrives there with some villagers and he
tells Sudarshan not to close the company.
People are getting jobs.  Otherwise,
how will they manage their expenses?  Sudarshan
then shouts back at the Sarpanch.  Hey Sarpanch,
we will deal with you, we will
not leave you alive, you bastard. But the Sarpanch tells Shivaji and the
other people of Abaddha that you do
n't worry, if anyone threatens you then I will help you. The
same evening, an FIR is filed against Sudarshan and his men for
scuffling with the security guards.
Within a few hours, Valmiki's men like
Sudarshan are taken into custody.
And he gets the belt immediately.  Now at this
time Valmiki's men keep calling the Sarpanch and saying
see this matter is mine.
Don't get involved in this matter otherwise you might even lose your life.  The
Sarpanch is scared.
And he also tells his brother, daughter and wife
about this fear.  His wife
says my husband is very scared.  Due to this fear,
he is living in Latur, 2 hours away from Massage Jok.
When Sudarshan
realises that Awada Energy is
not fulfilling the demand of Rs 2 crore and
now even the Sarpanch is supporting them,
then he goes to Valmiki.  Valmiki
tells him that if this continues, no
company will pay weekly to itself.  From now on,
whoever comes between them is
sure to be murdered.  Come on, start working.  Yes,
talk to Vishnu, he will assist
you.  So the next day Sudarshan meets
with some of Valmiki's men at a nearby hotel.
He tells them about the instructions given by Valmiki
and says that if the
Sarpanch comes back to Awada then Talab Tadashik.
Everyone should know what the consequences of fighting with us are.
Next day on 9th October the Sarpanch
and his maternal uncle's son are
going to their village Massa Jok in a Tata Indigo car.  As soon as
they cross a toll gate,
a black Scorpio immediately blocks their way.
Uncle's son Shivraj knows
that this car belongs to local goon Sudarshan.  The
goons throw the Sarpanch out,
put him in their Scorpio car and head towards Catch in the Beat District.
Shivraj immediately gets scared and
files an FIR against seven men for kidnapping the Sarpanch.
They reach Ganga Mauli Sugar Mill
in a desolate area located 14km from Massa Jok.  It
is far away.  He throws the Sarpanch out
and starts beating him with an iron rod and gas pipe.
Where a man continuously
beats the Sarpanch.  The second one holds the Sarpanch's mouth and
forces him to speak.  Everyone's
father is Sudarshan Gude.  Then he urinates on the Sarpanch's face.
They take off his clothes, pull his hair
and keep beating him.  Blood starts flowing from his body,
but the goons cannot hear the Sarpanch's screams.
And all these photos that you are seeing on your screen are
taken from the charge sheet only.   The
goons are recording this entire fight.
Then after beating him they pick up that Sarpanch.  They
put it in a Scorpio and
threw it away from the village at 6:30 in the evening.
Now, ever since Shivraj Sarpanch's maternal uncle's
son filed the FIR, the
police have been searching for the Sarpanch.  But they do
n’t get them.  But suddenly they
get a tip and within a few minutes the police
immediately reaches the location and
finds the unconscious body of the Sarpanch.
He is immediately taken to the sub-district hospital of Catch
but the doctor declares him dead.  It is
written in the post-mortem that his
body was completely cold.  Which means that it had been a
long time since his death.  The
injury marks on the body clearly
show that he has been physically assaulted.   It is
written in the post mortem that
due to multiple injuries, haemorrhage and shock occurred
which led to his death.  Then the
police starts its investigation.
First of all, two 21 year old young men who are
Valmiki's men are arrested.  On the
same day, the police also seize the black Scorpio
car that was used for the entire incident.
But there is no news about the main actors
Valmiki and Sudarshan.
Now during this other
men of Valmiki get arrested when police conduct
several raids in Nashik, Aurangabad and Pune.
Finally on 21 December Valmiki surrenders in Pune.
Now Valmiki is first arrested in a bus extortion case.
But
during the investigation a secret witness
tells the police that Valmiki is the mastermind behind this entire thing.
Witness says that if the
recovery money was not paid, Valmik would have not only
beaten the people but also killed them.   The
second witness tells the police that
Valmiki is the strongman here and this whole
district is his jungle.  Any company that
works in this district pays
extortion money to one or the other Valmiki gang.  After
obtaining all this information the
police finally files a murder case
against Valmiki.  But after a month
Sudarshan is also arrested.
Sudarshan Ghule, accused in the murder of Santosh Deshmukh,
confessed to the police.  On February 17, Masazo
villagers threatened to go
on a hunger strike if the case was
not solved.  The murder of a Sarpanch again
becomes a big headline in Maharashtra.
Because Valmiki
is a special man of Maharashtra Minister Dhananjay Munde.
Opposition parties say that
Dhananjay Munde will have to resign while this investigation is going on.
Finally on March 4th,
Dhananjay Munde submits his resignation.
Cabinet Minister Dhananjay Munde has
submitted his resignation.  Maharashtra CM
Devendra Fadnavis announced this some time ago.
Fadnavis has accepted Munde's
resignation.  He is
still an MLA but not in any ministerial post.
Kalidas Sapet, a
senior leader of a farmer union in Maharashtra,
says that Dhananjay is so powerful that no
one wants to speak against him.  His
extortion gangs have been operating in Beed for about a year.
But one thing is certain that
after the murder of the Sarpanch, the caste politics of Beed
came to the fore.  Valmiki Karad and Dhananjay Munde
both belong to the Banjari community.  An OBC
group while the Sarpanch is from the Maratha community which is
politically powerful and is considered upper caste.
Both the communities have been
living in Beed for many centuries.  But this case
showed the divide among communities.
Even many police officers
removed their surnames from their nameplates so that people
could trust them.  An interview with a resident of Beed
shows that our society has become
polarised.  When I invited a friend
to a tea shop, he refused to come there
saying that the shop belonged to
people from another community.  If we
talk about the case, cases were registered against Valmiki Karad and many of his
associates due to the three FIRs.
One of these cases is under Maharashtra
Control of Organised Crime Act (
MCOCA) which is a very serious and non-
bailable offence.  For this reason, he
is still in custody.  The next hearing of the case will be on
April 24.  The Sarpanch's family has
requested that this case be fast
tracked.  The Sarpanch's brother said that
we want justice.
This case can be settled in 6 to 7 months in the fast track court.
Therefore, we demand an application to the Exact Track Court through the CID.
Recently a new TV series Khaki has come
where a police officer takes charge in a new police station.
He was told that there is
a very dangerous goon in the area.
Chandan Mahato, it is his responsibility to
control him.  Chandan Mahato is a big
gangster who runs many extortion businesses.
As soon as the officer arrives at the post on his first day,
his subordinates serve him a mutton dish.  The
officer gets very impressed
and tells his colleagues, “This is an amazing
scene, friend.”  How much is meat per kg
here?  Then a subordinate of the
officer replies that who knows, big boss, I never
bought it.  So how do we know the price
?  That bhaiya ji sends us 2 kilos of mutton,
fish and chicken every day.  Who bhaiya
ji?  Chandan Mahato brother Chandan Mahato who is the
gangster of the area is the one who is feeding mutton to the police
and this is the story of our country, those who are the
protectors of justice are the ones eating the salt of the goons.   The
story that I told you in the last 15-20 minutes is not
just the story of a Sarpanch and a goon
but it is the story of our government.
And when you look carefully, you will find this same
pattern in many corners of the country.  Be
it the case of Aati Ahmed or
Valmiki Karad.  These people
are actually entrepreneurs.  Wherever he
gets an opportunity, he jumps at it.
But why are they getting this opportunity
?  Because the government is not doing its job.
Despite being convicted of murder in Bihar's Siwan district, Mohammad
Shabuddin ran his empire from inside the jail.
He had a room inside the jail
where he used to hold meetings and
resolve people's disputes.  why?  Because people
neither trusted the police nor the courts.
Because of this he will go to Baahubali only.
And that is why Atiq Ahmed's supporters used to say
that he is definitely a goon but he is our goon.
At least he will listen to us.  He
will do our work.  What about the police and the courts
?  What is the definition of government?
Is Valmik Karad Govt?   The
definition of government in political science is
any organization that has a
monopoly on violence and collecting
taxes.  So Valmiki is not Karad Government
but he is running a parallel government
because he is demanding recovery of Rs. 100 crores
from the companies of Maharashtra which is a
clear example of state failure when
security guards are beaten up.  Companies are
threatened and the Panchayat leader is
killed.  Political scientist Milan
Vaishnav has written in his book that the
Bahubali's will definitely seem like criminals to you and me
but many locals do
not consider them criminals because they are getting the
work of the locals done and to get all their work done they are
also extorting money from other businesses
and if any person
raises a question on their empire then they kill him.
These people are not outsiders
but they are part of the system and they
also support the political system.   The
logic is very simple.  Political parties
need money and muscle and these
strongmen leaders can give both to the parties.
Politicians don't tolerate them, in fact
they need such people and
if we want to end this system then
basically our government needs to invest in judiciary and police
so that people do
n't go to these goons and we
need this so that people like Santosh, who just
want jobs for their villagers, do
n't have to sacrifice their lives.
And don't forget to check out the
link in the skill description.
[music]