welcome to
hardtalk i'm stephen sacca the eu is
thought to have lost more than 10
billion euros to fraud over the last two
decades
and yet it's anti-fraud and corruption
agencies have long
lacked the teeth to root out the problem
could that
be about to change well my guest is
romanian lara kovaci
the eu's first public prosecutor she has
enhanced powers to tackle transnational
crime
but if member states refuse to play ball
how can she succeed
[Music]
lara kovichi in luxembourg welcome to
hard talk
thank you very much for the invitation
you have had almost
a year since your appointment as the
eu's
first chief public prosecutor
you are trying to deal with a very
urgent problem that costs the eu
billions of euros what have you actually
done so far
i took my office in 1st of november and
i started to organize together
with the small team that i found here to
in the beginning the administrative
issues that are necessary
to start eppo is necessary to have the
european prosecutors
it's those prosecutors who will work
here with me in luxembourg
and also we need to have the european
delegated prosecutors
the european delegated prosecutor is
those prosecutors who will
work in their national member states
would you agree would you agree would
you agree with me that the problem is
indeed very
urgent we are talking about the role of
organized crime in siphoning off
billions of euros from the agricultural
funds the cohesion
funds right across the european union
some countries
are particularly bad and yet you're
telling me after nine months
you really haven't begun work yet you're
just working out your administration
yes it is necessary to have a bpo
but in order to to start working in the
cases
we need to build the new office
this means that we we need to have all
the internal regulation
we need to have all the prosecutors on
board
and it's not a decision that only one
person can take it's a
shared responsibility between the
european commission
european parliament the council and the
national
uh authorities of each member state
participating to the european public
prosecutor office
yeah did it worry you when you realized
that some of the team you were supposed
to lead
were going to be part-time and that your
total staffing appears to number some
40 to 50 in your central office and then
a bunch of
local prosecutors in member countries
who at least according to the commission
were going to be working part-time
well we speak here about the possibility
for prosecutors to work full-time and
part-time
my wish is to have only full-time
prosecutors this is
very important for their independence
for their efficiency for the
responsibility i cannot imagine how a
european delegate prosecutor can work
for
our story ppo and during the the
pleading in the trial he has to
uh to go and to continue his activity to
and to work for the national prosecutor
office this is the reason why
in my consultation with the member
states i insisted to have only full-time
prosecutors
right the fact that they were talking
about part-timers it may be it's
symptomatic
of a problem at the heart of the eu
which is they've never
really taken rooting out systematic
corruption seriously we can see that
over many years if we look at the scale
of the problem and the response from the
eu
and their in particular their european
anti-fraud office olaf
we see that time and again uh
investigations have been begun but
they've not
led to prosecutions it's a fundamental
problem isn't it
it is the european public prosecutor
will be the first
uh prosecutor office at the european
level what we will achieve with that
we will have a unitary approach related
to this phenomena and in the same time
we will
solve this issue related to the
discrepancies between the member states
of course in this period i evaluated
the statistics and i saw there are some
member states on which
we have hundreds of cases in each year
but also we have some member states
where
only two or nine investigations per per
year was uh
made by the prosecutors yeah
we will solve this issue to be blunt
about it miss kaveshi it's clear that
some member states
are absolutely not serious about using
the information that's been dug
up by the eu's anti-corruption
investigators again if one looks
at the current situation with this olaf
anti-fraud office at the eu
they launched 541
cases which they said should go to court
in fact
only 308 of them did 171 of those were
dismissed
and there were only 137
indictments in other words many member
states are
simply not interested in taking
seriously this problem
yes having eppo we will solve this issue
because we will have the same priorities
but it's important to
to make a small comment related to a
love and to explain
that until now olaf did only
administrative investigations
they did not make criminal investigation
only the prosecutor can do that
so eppo will be the only body at the
european level
who can make investigation we will have
prosecutors
we are all participating member states
and this is very important when we speak
about this phenomena especially related
to financial fraud
sometimes the prosecutor the law
informers
enforcement are not focused on this type
of criminality in the
same way in an equal way in all the
member states
eppo will change that so having
a highest number of investigation in
some member states or less in another
member states doesn't mean that we don't
have problems
you we we cannot speak about usual
suspects
when we speak about the financial fraud
there are problems in
all the member states and having tppo
at the national level in each
participating member states
we it will be very good because we can
increase the level of protection of the
european funds
and of course we will investigate better
all right efficiently
this kind of crimes well i think it's
worth reminding people when you talk
about the eppo you mean
the european public prosecutors office
exactly so that's what you're leading i
think it's fair to say you got the job
because of your
pretty remarkable track record in
romania during your time
leading the anti-corruption director in
your home country romania i see that you
led the campaign against a whole bunch
of senior politicians the
former prime minister mr nastasi was
convicted
of corruption offences during your term
former or current ministers 43
parliamentarians 260 local officials
all were subject to investigation during
your time in romania are you going to go
for the big beasts across europe now in
your new job
of course we will investigate financial
fraud we will investigate powerful
people but what is important to say
is what i did in romania and what i will
do here in eppo
i will not to be alone i will have the
entire team
with me and this is very important we
will be prosecutors of 22 different
member states
and we will put together our experience
our knowledge and we will investigate
better this uh
phenomena but the problem together with
them i wanted to do a good job
well we'll get we'll get to the 22
states and why it's not
uh more in a moment but just to focus on
romania and whether you really made a
difference
you you were a controversial figure you
certainly uh
took on some of the most powerful people
in your country but if one looks at the
state of romania when you left the job
and you were fired by the government
eventually
uh when you left transparency
international
thought that romania was actually
performing worse it ranked 70th in the
world in terms of
corruption index in 2019 it was going
backwards
it was the second most corrupt country
in
europe uh just uh outdone by bulgaria
it doesn't seem to be honest that
despite your best efforts you made much
difference
well when we speak about to eradicate
corruption
or to reduce the level of corruption in
one country
i think it's not the only responsibility
of prosecutors
to to fight with this phenomena it is
necessary to have
an entire effort also the prosecutors
also to prevent corruption also to to
have good laws and to offer the enough
to
offer enough instruments to the
prosecutors to investigate those crimes
it is important to say that also the
mentality
and the entire society can contribute to
to decrease the level of corruption in a
country so
not only arresting or investigating
people
we can solve the issue of corruption in
one member state but
what is important now is that we will
have the european public prosecutor
office of the european level
and we will use uh all the
legal instruments that we have and we
will work
better because we will have also here in
luxembourg
at the central level financial
investigation
investigators case analysts and together
we can
analyze you we can aggregate and put
together
all the dots when we speak about the
course the crimes
when we speak about corruption and
especially when we speak about financial
uh
criminal let me stop you a minute
because people across europe are going
to be interested in how you're going to
do the job
and it is indeed notable that you had a
certain reputation in romania for
uh let's say pushing the envelope in
terms of investigative practice
you it seems we're prepared to use the
intelligence services in a covert
fashion to dig dirt on some of the
suspects that you were going after
and in the uh romanian constitutional
court some of your
methods were called into question do you
regret some of the methods you used
no it's not about the methods it's about
the working arrangement that we had
but at that moment based on the
legislation
we receive information from the secret
services
and we use those information to open the
cases
but it's important to say and to clarify
that
our investigations were made by the
prosecutors and by the police
officers and no one from the uh
officials from the service secret
service
did not work in our cases only the
prosecutors
to be honest with you police officers i
i'll be honest with you i i was very
struck by a former uh romanian prime
minister mr tariqanu
saying that under your watch the
anti-corruption agency
had not respected legal frameworks had
become
corrupt themselves and had become
a part of the political fight in romania
some critics called you
a part of securitate 2.0 because of your
cooperation with the security services
again i put it to you that if you bring
those methods to
your europe-wide prosecutor role
you're going to make many people very
unhappy
all our cases that we worked in romania
were checked and verified in the court
so at the european level we will work
according to the legislation
as i did it in romania all the time and
everything that
the prosecutors did in the cases were
checked
in the court by judges but with respect
to the constitutional the constitutional
court in january
uh 2019 concluded that you had created a
parallel justice system
existing outside the rules imposed by
romania's constitution
there is no any decision of
constitutional court saying that i
created a parallel state in romania
well i'm just i'm reading from one of
their rulings
of january 2019 now i know that
ultimately
charges against you were dropped but the
nonetheless it's a very serious
allegation that you created a parallel
justice system
the question really is do you believe
that in prosecuting
corruption and fraud that the ends
justify the means
if you read that decision based on
which the constitutional court revoked
me i should say
that i made a complaint to the european
court for human rights
and in this year in may the the
the judgment of the european court of
human rights said
that in that case my rights
were broken so i don't know
which kind of decision you you quoted
but i can say that in entire my activity
i respectfully i respect it all the time
the constitution i respected the
procedural criminal code
and all the nationals law but when it
comes to
saying i'm just asking you a simple
question now when it comes to rooting
out corruption do you believe as a
an aggressive prosecutor that the ends
do
justify the means now all the time in my
activity i respected the law and this is
the only principle that
i will have in the consideration and we
should have in the consideration
all the time to respect the law let me
ask you then now that you've gone from a
national role in romania to an eu
wide role rooting out corruption what
kind of cooperation do you think you're
going to get from a country like hungary
which already has made it plain it's
going to refuse to cooperate
and play a part in the european public
prosecutor offices
system they want no part of it alongside
some other nations including poland
sweden denmark island they basically
opted out and given that all of the
allegations
that we see about corruption and misuse
of eu money in hungary
how are you going to be able to operate
in hungary
we will operate based on the regulation
of the european public prosecutor office
and based on this regulation we can have
working arrangement with non-persistent
participating member state
including hungary and poland sweden
denmark and ireland and also with
third countries and we
started already to reach out to have
contacts with
hunger in poland we will continue with
the other non-participating member
states and we will have
working arrangement based on the uh
international cooperation instruments
that there are
available for prosecutors in their
activities let me ask you this what
hungary and poland are countries that
receive huge amounts of
eu funds in structural and cohesion
funding terms why do you think as an
experienced prosecutor
they might be keen to opt out of the
public prosecutor offices system
we will work with our colleagues based
on the legal instruments that we will
have
it is very difficult to say that we can
investigate
everything that it will happen in
hungary because they
in hungary and poland because they will
not
be part of the european public process
i'm asking you why
why miss kaveh why do you think that
they've opted out can you imagine
it is a political decision i cannot
comment i'm a prosecutor i can comment
only
based on my activity i cannot
answer why member state did not accept
to be part of
any dpo or not well let me ask you a
more specific question then i've just
been looking at some of the olaf
investigations in hungary what they
discovered and the
paperwork has been leaked so we know
it's uh it's directly from olaf
they discovered that there were for
example street lighting
contracts which were funded by the
european union which it seems
had been irregular in the way that
they'd been
tended for a company that was very
close to a close relative of the
hungarian prime minister
won these contracts uh olaf
as you've said in this interview
certainly wasn't capable of launching
criminal proceedings itself
in the future if that kind of thing
happens
in hungary will you be able to launch
criminal proceedings yes or no
we can launch proceedings only in those
cases
where uh together with uh let's say
take an example a hungarian person
is involved also a person from
participating member states
or if a part of activity is committing
on the territory on participating member
states
otherwise all the information that we
will have we have to send in hungary
see i'm just wondering what really has
changed from the very beginning of this
interview you've told me
you know this is a big new eu initiative
we've created a new office to really get
serious about anti-corruption and
anti-fraud but in the end
all of the cards are really still held
by the member states and your powers
only go so far as you get cooperation
from the member states and if you don't
get the cooperation you can't really
function
it's not exactly in this way we will
receive complaints directly here in
luxembourg at central level
we can have the possibility to
reallocate the investigation
from a member state to another member
state and
what is important is the quality and the
euro uh the professionalism of the
european delegated prosecutors
that will work for eppo the national
authorities has to
select those prosecutors and to propose
the european chief prosecutor to be
appointed
but it's important to say that they will
be independent in their activity
and they will make the investigations in
these cases
also it will be important because they
will not be limited by the national
borders
they can call for example a prosecutor
from romania can call
his colleagues from luxembourg to ask
for
information to find some documents to
find some proofs
and after that the colleague from
romania can use those proof directly
in the investigation without being
necessary to make any other formalities
so everything will be more efficient
more quick and uh in this way we will
protect better the
the european money the truth though if
you read
reports over many years from
transparency international from the
organized crime and corruption reporting
project and other ngos
is that eu monies have been siphoned off
and have entered the the hands of the
criminal
organized criminal elements including we
know
the mafia and other extremely powerful
organizations we also know that in
certain countries this involves
very powerful people close to political
power
so-called oligarchs as well do you
really believe
that you have both the power and the
political backing
to take these forces on
we will investigate of course all the
crimes related to the organized crime
and uh it's not necessary to have a
political backup because eppo will be
an independent prosecutor office the
prosecutor will be
independent so we need to do our work we
need to win the trust of the citizen
and we need to prove that the law is
equally for everybody and this will be
the role of eppo
to investigate also the powerful people
and to use all the the legal means that
we have to finalize our investigations
i'm tempted to ask you ms kaveh how
strong is your will on this matter i
know in romania
you took on powerful forces and you
faced personal threats you know what it
means to be
under a great deal of pressure but it
seems to me that pressure
as your job is now across europe that
pressure may get even more intense
well i'm used to work with pressure it's
not any problem for me and i'm sure that
it will not be a problem for the other
colleagues for eppo
there will be only good prosecutors here
very courageous very professional so
uh we will work together as a team and i
i'm sure that we will achieve what we
want so
it's not any problem if we will have
some
pressure are you really sure about that
you said in a recent interview
corruption
can be defeated do not abandon this
fight
experience across the eu would say that
rooting out
systemic corruption and which is cost
billions of euros to the european union
it's an impossible job
nobody's achieved it before it's not
impossible
we have to do our job and we have to
fight but
to eradicate corruption it's important
not to to to rely all the time only on
the work of prosecutors
it is the same with the financial
criminality
we have to work together in a team with
the other european institution
with the national authorities with the
entire society because in the end
each citizen can be a part
in this fight and can help the
the prosecutors to to fight with this
criminality
lara kovichi i thank you very much
indeed for joining me from luxembourg
thank you
[Music]
you