The hands that fired the guns in the Pahalgam attack are still
alive to this day.  The person who had
come to attack Pahalgam
turned out to be the SSG Para Commando of the Pakistani Army and this is how this thing came to light.
At the end of the attack, he took
selfies with the dead bodies and
went to the person who had recorded the video and asked him to talk about Palestine.
And as soon as he spoke
this thing came up.  They changed the location of their plan to attack the hotel to
Pahalgam.  Otherwise, the third terrorist who was the earlier
target,
entered Pakistan through the Attari border on a legal student visa.
Why did the demand for buying satellite images of the Pahalgam area before the attack suddenly double?
This is not normal.  When
these OGWs were caught and
questioned in a police style, they told
line by line that as soon as the attack took place, US's
Max Technology
immediately broke its partnership with Pakistan's company BSI.
This wasn't just any random firing.   By
choking the ground from three sides, the crowd was
gathered towards the Maggi stall saying,
you have so much guts that now you will
raise the domicile issue in Kashmir.
[Music]
Look, before we move ahead, let's talk about
India's increasing problems with increasing heat -
temperature and pollution.  India's
geographical location is such where the weather
remains hot and humid and due to global warming the
average temperature has increased by 1 degree in the last 30 years.
Dust, mud, heat,
all this remains for 10 months out of 12.
40% plus people in India have oily skin
and hence due to dirt, pollution and excess
sebum production, acne problems are increasing in oily skin.
See, the sebaceous glands in oily skin
produce more sebum.  And when this sebum
mixes with dirt and dead skin, the pores get blocked
and that leads to pimples.  So
for this today I would like to tell you
about Derma Touch Salicylic 2% Face Wash.   It contains
BHA which controls oil and
cures acne and Zinc PCF which
keeps the skin hydrated.  You will start seeing results in six to eight weeks.
Formulated with powerful actives, this face wash is
fragrance free and suitable for all skin types.
So it is
well suited for sensitive skin also.  Doctor recommended Indian
pharmacy brand dermach makes solid
products.  The starting price of this 4 plus rated face wash is
just ₹149.  It is
available on their website dermach.com and
on all platforms like amazon, Flipkart, blink and also at your nearest pharmacy
store.  So let's come back to the topic.
See, this is Jammu and Kashmir and
within Jammu and Kashmir, there is Anantnag
district, within which falls
Pahalgam.  And when you are 5 Km from Pahalgam.  If you
climb up, there
is a 800 meter long plain here, Baisar, which is
also called Mini Switzerland of India.
And this is the place where the
terrorists attacked in a planned manner on April 22
and this incident is
not like a terrorist came and just
picked up a gun and started shooting.  This time a
huge planning has been done in which multiple
groups have attacked using well coordinated strategies
and technologies like Ultrasats.
Now how was this attack carried
out?  How was the planning done?  Where did it happen?   If it
happened in Pakistan, then did multiple
proofs emerge?  I will tell you each and every thing
in this video and to
understand all these things we will have to go back a bit.
So look, I just
showed you the Baisaran area.  There is
a village on this side whose name is Gur.  This village
officially
falls in Bijhara block of Anantnag district and in a house of this village,
Adil Hussain Thokar, the
first terrorist of Pahalgam attack, was born.  Just
a few days ago his house was blown up,
but when he was born in the year 1992, no
one had even imagined
that in the future he would carry out an attack like Pahalgam
due to which a war like situation would arise between the two countries.
[MUSIC]
Network Successful Security.  Now when Adil was
growing up here, he first
took admission in Shah Hamdan Public School.  Then he completed his
12th class from Government Higher Secondary School, Beech Behara and by the year 2018, he
completed his MA from Rahmat Alam College, Anantnag and started teaching.
So till the year 2018, when he was in college,
his name did not come up in any anti-India activity.  But there was just one thing
that everyone noticed at that time, that
whenever a terrorist was killed in that area, he would
definitely go to his funeral.
Its name had
not been heard before in any other activity.  But
in April 2018 it started its real game.  On
29th of April 2018, what does this Adil
Thokar do?  He tells his family
that he has an exam and
for that he will have to go to Batgaon in Kashmir
and after giving the exam he will return home. The
family agrees to this and
sends him but two to three days pass
but Adil does not
return home, instead he disappears. The family members
call him back to back but he does
not talk to them. Then, fed up and tired, on the second
of May 2018, Adil Thokar's mother
Shahzada Bano goes to the police station and
registers a missing complaint.  Now, the
missing report was registered but
in reality, Adil had already made all the
planning.  Without telling anyone, he had
applied for a student visa for
higher studies in Pakistan in the same month i.e. April 2018.  And in a very short time,
i.e. in the same month, the Pakistan
authority grants student visa to Adil Thokar.
And
on the basis of this visa, Adil, on the pretext of having an exam at home,
reaches Pakistan in May 2018 via the Attari-Wagah border with a valid passport and valid student visa.  This
is his pic from that time.  Now he had
reached Pakistan but he did
not want to go to Pakistan for studies.
After reaching Pakistan, the first thing he does is switch off his phone.
He completely cuts off contact with his family and the people around him.
And the same day
Lashkar meets the leadership of Taba.  Lashkar-e-
Taba is the same militant organization that
carried out the Mumbai and Parliament attacks.  Now after reaching Pakistan, there is a
LED camp in Sawai Nala, Muzaffarabad
which is 30km from LOC.  It falls inside
POK.  Its training
starts here.  Daura e Sufa, Daura e Aam,
Daura Ekhas, all these, its training starts.  Out
of the nine strikes that were carried out in Operation Sindoor, the first
strike was carried out here.  Now Adil's
training continues here.  It is prepared to
attack further.   On the
other hand, the next month after this came,
i.e. on 28th June 2018,
a problem arose for Pakistan.  FATF
Financial Action Task Four.  This is an
international body which monitors terror funding across the world.
So
considering the activities of Pakistan, FATF put it in its grey list.
Before blacklisting, it is
put in grey list.  A chance is given to
improve.  Now this
was a huge problem for Pakistan because
due to this, the loans etc. that Pakistan gets from the IMF, World Bank
etc. would be stopped.
This would also have raised a survival issue for Pakistan.
So
after putting it in the grey list, FATF
gave guidelines to Pakistan that you should stop funding of
organisations like Lashkar-e-Taba operating in your country and
take action against them.  So to
show the world the FATF guidelines,
Pakistan took small actions.
They started submitting reports
that they have stopped funding and their
leaders of LET etc. were also
put in jail.  Now, after few months, on
14th of February 2019, Pulwama is carried out in India.
Everyone in India was very angry
and immediately after the attack, India had
all the proofs like
how Rs 10.43 lakh was
transferred from Pakistan to the account of Umar, the attacker.  By collecting all these proofs,
a dossier was prepared and
sent to FATF member countries like US, France, UK.  From 17 to 22 February, a
meeting of FATF was held in Paris
and a final warning was given to Pakistan
that if anything like this happens again, it will be blacklisted.
So now after this, the
activities of Lashkar Taiba, Jaish-e-Mohammed inside Pakistan
slowed down and there was peace in Pakistan as well
and then after 5 months, on the Fifth of August
2019, India removed Article 370 from Kashmir.
Article 37 Now after this thing happened,
Pakistan was trapped from all sides.
Here Article 370 had been removed.
Pakistan could not take military action.  Lashkar
Taiba, Jaish-e-Mohammed, all these proxies were under the
radar of FTF.  So,
to deal with this thing, multiple meetings are held in
Muridka, Pakistan where LeT has its head quarters.
Its solution is found and then
after some time a new plan is made
so that the fight in Kashmir
can be continued.  Pakistan
creates terrorist outfit under a new name.  The
Resistance Front TRF.   The
plan here was to change your name,
change your face and keep all your work the same
old.  Like normally you must have seen
that if a company whose name gets tarnished due to some fraud then
it opens a company under a new name and starts doing the same work.
So the same thing was done here as well.
So Article 370 is removed in August 2019
and after 2 months i.e. in October 2019,
The Resistance Front TRF is set up
and this same TRF later carries
out the Pahalgam attack.  This
TRF was created in such a way that it
gave the illusion of a clean local Kashmiri group.
These people remained from all over the world in which the
name of Pakistan was not mentioned anywhere.  And the
responsibility of running the entire system and operation within this TRF was in the hands of the same
old terrorists who were from Lashkar Taba Jaish Mohammad.
Only the name was
changed.  After the formation of TRF, hiring was
a big issue.  So for this,
in the initial phase, he started hiring some people from Tehreek Millat
Islamia, Ghaznavi Hind, Hizbul Mujahideen
and Lashkar-e-Taba.
And among
all the hiring that has been done,
one hiring is very important.
You must remember his name because
he is the actual mastermind of the Pahalgam attack.  His
name is Hashim
Musa.  This Hashim Musa is
an SSG Para Commando of Pakistan Army.  So the
Pakistan Army
terminated its service and gave it on loan to Lashkar
Taiba.  Gave it to LET on loan.
This means that now it will
execute all the operations of LET.
And see, this is
not a conspiracy theory.
This thing has clearly come to light in the initial investigation conducted by the NIA.
As many OGW statements have come,
India Today, Times of India, The New
Indian Express has been covering this thing from day one.
And in this, what is being said is that
NIA belongs to India.  These news agencies are
also from India.  So see, the crime has
happened inside India.  Investigation is
going on inside India.  So there will be no report from Tokyo.
And all these things that I am telling you
cannot be hidden.  In all the previous
attacks whether it was Pulwama, 2611,
Kasab who was caught, whatever proofs came,
whatever was said by NIA in the initial stage,
all those things were later proved and the
international community also accepted those proofs.
And before this,
how was the Pahalgam attack planned?
How did these people enter?  How was the coordination done?   Let me
tell you about it.  Before that, it is
very important to understand that India is
not the only country which
says all these things about Pakistan.
Organizations outside India whose
reports are accepted by people all over the world.  The
United Nations, International Wash Dogs,
Independent Intelligence firms have all said this
in their reports that Pakistan has
created a proxy battle field in areas like Kashmir by using terror outfits.
And the most dangerous part in this is
that the Pakistan Army and ISI do
not consider it terrorism.  Rather it
follows a calculated military doctrine.
Like in Afghanistan, the US CIA
ousted the Soviet Union by fighting a proxy war through local Mujahideen.  So they
believe that they will
take Kashmir from India just like this without fighting a war.  The report of the European
Foundation for South Asia Studies
says that the Pakistan
Army and its intelligence agency ISI have
an unholy alliance with terror groups.
They have given $25 to $250 million
to terrorist groups.  Some of their salaries are
given in the form of training, operational costs as required.
I have placed the link to this entire report in the description.
Apart from this, the US State
Department said that Pakistan's
ISI is still giving shelter to terrorist groups
which are focusing on India.
Congressional Research Service CRS.
Its report number
R41832 said on record that
Pakistan's ISI is linked with anti-India militant
organisations and is
secretly providing
financial assistance, training and
strategic guidance to organisations like Lashkar-e-Taba.
I have also
included this report in the description.  When you read beyond page number 23 to 24
you will know what praises have been
sung for Pakistan.  The
CRS report which was published in the US Parliament, US Congress
, also said
that there are 15 terrorist groups inside Pakistan.
Which have been divided into five categories.  The
dedicated task of one of the groups is to
spread terrorism in Kashmir.
These are all their names and you will find the link for this
in the description as well.  All these
reports are from outside India and if
you do not believe them then
former President of Pakistan Musharraf
accepted in an interview to CN that yes, we do
provide training to fight in Kashmir.
These are our heroes.
Former Pakistan PM Nawaz Sharif, while giving an interview to Dawn,
accepted that non-state
actors like Lashkar-e-Taiba carried out the
Mumbai attack using Pakistani soil.
Rest, you must have seen these famous photographs recently.  The
entire Pakistani leadership is standing with UN designated terrorist Hafiz Abdul Rauf.
And I am telling this in short.   There are
so many reports from the US Department of Defense Pentagon FADF.  The whole
night will pass and
in those reports only the connection with Pakistan and its
terrorists will be
told and all these are
reports from outside India.  So
whatever story I am telling you next,
you cannot reject it just by saying that hey,
this is an Indian YouTuber.  There
are reports from India.  India has NIA.  By
saying all these things you cannot remove Pakistan's link with
terrorism.  Let's
come back to our story.  So see,
till now Hashim Musa, who was a para commando of Pakistan Army, had
left the army and
started working with the operatives of LeT.
Adil Thokar, who had reached Pakistan from Kashmir, was
undergoing training there.
That means the two terrorists who were there on the day of Pahalgam attack were
working inside Pakistan.  And the third thing, TRF had
already been formed.  And
after the formation of TRF, the second thing they had to do was to
appoint a head of TRF and the head had to be someone
on whom they had trust for a long time, who was
skilled and local to Kashmir
so that their narrative of the war could be
executed in the same manner and
by having a local head, he would have local hiring and good knowledge of that area,
so it is a huge
advantage.  So for this they
selected Mohammad Abbas Sheikh, a
resident of Kaima village, Rampura, Kulgam district of Kashmir.
He was a very old and
trusted terrorist of LeT.  It was
involved in spreading terrorism with LeT since 1996.
So for this reason, Mohammad Abbas Shaikh was
made the head of TRF.  He is
also called the founder of TRF.  But
actually the founders of TRF were
sitting in Pakistan.
Along with TRF head Mohammad Abbas Sheikh, there lived another LET
trustee man named Sheikh
Sajjad Gul.  The planning of the Pahalgam attack
, the location that was set, the
shift from the hotel to Pahalgam, all the planning was done by
him.  He will come forward soon.  He
lived in Nawa Bazaar of Srinagar in Kashmir.
He had completed his MBA and had been
caught with IT extortion once before in Delhi.
Was involved in many attacks.  His brother was also
earlier a doctor in Maharaja Har Singh Hospital.
Currently he handles funding in Gulf countries.
So after doing all these things,
now from here Mohammad Abbas Sheikh and Sheikh
Sajjad Gul handle the entire network of TRF in Kashmir.
And then after this, the
responsibility of TRF's OGW network in Kashmir was
given to Farooq Ahmed.  Farooq Ahmed was a very
important man.  Till 2016, it was
in Narikot village, Kalaroos block, Kupwara district of Kashmir.  But
since 2016, he was handling the OGW network of Kashmir while staying in Muzaffarabad, PoK.
And the terrorists who were sent inside Kashmir by crossing the LoC were
also done by this Farooqui.  In fact, at
the time of Pahalgam attack, it was he who had made all the
terrorists who had come from Pakistan
cross the LOC.  And all the
OGWs who were involved in the Pahalgam attack and were
doing recce before planning it,
all of them were in contact with him.  See
OGW, I have told this in the old video.  Let me
tell you once again.
OGW Over Ground Worker.
People in Kashmir who hate India
but don't want to risk their lives by taking up arms
become OGWs.
They run their household comfortably like ordinary people.
Some drive auto, some
manage shops.  But
they help those who are terrorists.  They do all the work like providing them food,
shelter, army information,
sharing details of the area etc.
OGWs play a very important role in Kashmir.
Without OGW, this
terrorist organization became LET
, became Jaish-e-Mohammed.  It becomes very difficult for them to do all their work
inside Kashmir.  Now after this, when all these things are setup,
Farooq Ahmed
starts infiltrating terrorists from Pakistan
into Kashmir by making them cross the LOC.  in order to attack.
All the terrorists who were entering from the LoC were entering from the areas of Samba,
Katua, Rajouri and Punj.
And these had a set
pattern.
After entering the Kashmir border, OGWs used to receive them.   They used to
help them and
after reaching the border, instead of taking the direct Jammu route and
reaching Anantnag, they used to reach the
Kistwar area which you can see from here through the
route because there are
very dense forests and natural
caves here.  The average elevation is more
than 2000 metres above sea level.  So it is
very easy to escape.  It is very difficult to catch them here.
22 April 2025, the
day this attack took place.  Till date,
our forces are
searching and killing them in the Sunday area.  The fighting is still
going on in this area.  So see, by the year
2022, they had established their entire network
inside Kashmir.
TRF rebranded its model of terrorism.
Create online portals.
He used Telegram social media a lot.  A
Telegram channel was also created by the name of Tj RF in which
Kashmiris were made to join by sharing propaganda videos etc.  And then in
the meantime they started attacking inside Kashmir.
They
started targeting those who were non-local.  He killed him in
Har Singh High Street Market
area, 100 meters from Lal Chowk.  This
was the first attack of TRF inside Kashmir.  After this
he killed Ajay Pandita ji and
killed Akash Mehra.  Laborers who had come from every corner of India were
attacked.  Basically,
you can understand his model in this way that he was
working like a contract killer.
They were going and killing all the non-locals.
But the real shock they
faced came on 23 August.  Because on this
day, in Alochi Bagh of Srinagar, the
head of TRF, Mohammad Abbas Sheikh, who is also
called the founder of TRF.  He was
playing a cricket match with local people.  The
Jammu & Kashmir Police got to know about it
and they reached there and killed him.  The
day he was killed, in the same week, the
second hand command of TRF, as I had
also told you, Sheikh Sajjad Gul, was
made the head.  Here the head of TRF is killed.  On the
other hand, the situation in Kashmir was also
changing very rapidly.  For example, in 2018,
1,458 cases of stone platting were reported.
Whereas in 2020, it had come down to 255 and then
further reduced.  Further, in 2023 and 2024, the
official data of stone
pelting became zero.  Cases of 228 terrorists were registered in 2018.  On
the other hand, if we
talk about 2023, then TRF was able to carry out only 44 attacks.
Where 8.5 lakh tourists came in 2018.
This number increased to 31 lakh in 2023
and the next year 43 lakh tourists came.
Whereas in 2019, an investment of Rs 296.64 crore was made.
In 2022, an investment of Rs 153 crore was made in Kashmir.
A lot of money was being injected.
And the domicile laws had also come into force.
Due to which people from outside Kashmir
could also get domicile certificate made.  And the
main target of TRF was that
this growing trade and the
money that is coming to Kashmiris due to increase in tourists should be
stopped by attacking.  Due to this,
they attacked some non-locals and people who were issued
domicile
but the number of tourists was not decreasing.   The
hotels were full.  There were pony riders, auto
drivers, everyone was busy.
You must also listen to the interviews of local Kashmiris on YouTube
in which they openly say
that there was so much work that they did not have even a day's
rest.  A lot of money was coming in and a lot of
tourists were also coming.  So
things were changing so fast in Kashmir, to
deal with this, now the real game starts from here.
I told you about Hashim Musa in September 2023 that it was
revealed in the initial investigation that he
was an SSG Para Commando of the Pakistan Army.  So along with Musa and Ali Bhai,
not much details have come about Ali Bhai.
It is not known whether he was
in the Para Commando or not.  But these
Ali Bhai and Musa, both were
Pakistani citizens.  So
in September 2023, they were infiltrated into Kashmir through both Kathua and Sama sector routes.
After reaching Kashmir, with the help of OGW, these
Khari Mahaurs live in a safe house in Basantgarh.
This Moses had been
given very good combat training.  It
could survive in the snow in the forest for many days.  So the plan was that in
future any attacks would happen in Kashmir, Musa would
lead them along with Ali Bhai and
Farooq's 15 to 20 OGWs would help him.
So what it means is that the two main terrorists of the
Pahalgam attack that was to happen later had
reached Kashmir in September 2023.  After reaching Kashmir,
they execute their small operations.
And then in October 2024,
in the Pahalgam attack, he was the third terrorist who
fired guns.  Adil Thokar, about whom I told you in the beginning, had
gone to Pakistan on a student visa.  After completing his training, he also
enters Kashmir through this sector which was the Punj Rajouri area.   There was another
terrorist who did a favor and
came to Kashmir at the same time.  But there is no
confirmed report whether this is the same
Ehsan who was there on the day of the Pahalgam attack.
Now after reaching Kashmir, these people
attack non-locals for some time.
Especially those laborers who were
involved in infrastructure and development projects.
Like
they killed six labourers and a doctor at the G More Tunnel project in Gagangir.
Then attacks were carried out in Dera's street DK J.  So in
this way, every now and then these people were
sitting there and attacking inside Kashmir.
Now it was 2 months after this, i.e. in December 2024,
i.e. 3-4
months before the Pahalgam attack.  At this time, there was
a terrorist with him in Dachigam, Srinagar,
Junaid Ahmed Bhatt.  The forces surround him and
kill him in an operation.  And after his death, when
his body is checked,
a mobile phone is found near him.  Through which, the
instructions etc. that were coming from his Pakistan connections,
encrypted messages
etc., all of them are caught and
an image is found from his mobile.
You might have seen this image recently also.
This image went viral after the Pahalgam attack.
This image was
found from Junaid's mobile in December 2024.  But at that
time the Farses could not recognize that
Moses was also in it.  But when the Pahalgam attack
happened and later when the tourists
gave descriptions etc. and after the attack more
sketches were made, then this photo came out and through the
information of the OGWs who were caught,
it was found out that the person on the
right of this photo is Musa and the person
you are seeing next to him is Junaid
who was killed.  Now see, after this, when
all these people reached Kashmir,
reports also came about the arrangement of weapons.
American M4 rifles were used in the Pahalgam attack and these
M4 rifles were more advanced than AK-47.  These
include night vision devices, cameras, etc.
When
cartridges were recovered from the crime scene after the Pahalgam attack,
ballistic analysis of those cartridges was done.
It came to light that
guns like M4 carbines and AK-47 were used.
And
things have also come out about these American M4 rifles that when the
USA left Afghanistan, it had left behind weapons worth about $7
billion
in Afghanistan.  And these weapons,
including American F4 rifles,
all these weapons reached the black market from there.
And according to intelligence reports, the
chief of Jaish-e-Mohammed, Mufti Abdul
Rauf Asghar, was
given the task of arms, procurement and logistics.  He
smuggled these M4 rifles through the Khyber Pakhtunkhwa
region to Jaish-Mohammed's
headquarters, Markaz Camp, and
then from there, using drones, these
weapons were dumped in Kashmir. This
process of bringing weapons to Kashmir had been
going on for many years.  Now
see, after this a very unusual
activity took place and because of the style in which Pahalgam was
attacked, the curiosity of this incident
increased further.  What actually happened was that
some time ago in August 2024,
UN designated terrorist and
head of Lashkar-e-Taba Saifullah Kasuri
met Hamas leader Khalid Mashal in Doha, Qatar and at that time,
Pakistan's Pakistan Central Muslim
League (PMML) had also uploaded videos of this meeting.  At
that time no
one paid much attention to this thing.
But the real alarm bell rings on the
Fifth of February 2025.  What happens on this day is
that
Hamas leaders come to Shaheed Sabir Stadium in Rawalkot, Pakistan.  This was the
first time in history that Hamas
leadership entered PoK and
held a conference after reaching there.  The official name of this conference was
Kashmir Solidarity and Hamas Operation Al
Aqsa Flood
Conference.  And he held many
rallies here.  A lot of venom was spewed against India
and from here it started to seem that now
these people are going to do something in Kashmir and the
Pahalgam attack also
happened in Hamas style and after this meeting,
reports started coming that
after coming here, Hamas discussed the tactics of carrying out attacks inside Kashmir,
methods of encrypted communication and civilian targeting etc.
Now see, on the Fifth of
February, the Hamas leadership reached PoK and
a week later, another unusual thing happens there.  There is
a famous satellite company in the US called
Max Technologies.  So what
happens is that suddenly the
demand for high resolution images of the Pahalgam area of ​​Kashmir with this company
doubles.  Now Pahalgam is a tourist area.  There is no
battle field for the
demand to increase in this manner.  This was not normal.
Please pause this image and look at it once.  The highest number of orders for high resolution images were received
on February 12, 15, 18, 21 and 22 this year 2025.
These are those images.  Look, this
US satellite company Max
Technology provides high resolution satellite
images whose size is 30 cm.  to 15
cm.  Happens till.  They sell them to
approved government and defense agencies around the world.
Like in India, ISRO and
Ministry of Defense are its customers.  These
high resolution satellite images are
not normal.  With this, even the
smallest things on the ground can be seen.  Through these high
resolution images,
planning of attack, target verification etc.
all these things happen.  This image acts as a tactical
weapon in the battlefield.  For
this reason, they share their images only
with approved government agencies.  If
any private or random entity comes, we do not give him high resolution images.  They
give low grade images.
She is of no use.  Now the question
arises that
why is the demand for images of areas like Pahalgam so huge?  And
access to these images is not that easy.
So when investigation was done about this,
a new game came to light.  What happened was that
in June 2024, a Pakistani company
Business System Intelligence Private Limited
PSI entered into a partnership with the US satellite company
Max Technologies by agreeing to all its
terms and conditions.  Now, because of the
partnership, the Pakistani company
BSI got the advantage that it also got the rights to sell those high
resolution images which cannot be accessed easily.  This
means that this company
also got access which till now was
exclusive to approved government agencies.  If this Pakistani company
BSI wants, it can give its Pakistani clients to
them also.  And who knows,
that Pakistani client might even be a terrorist
organisation.  And the chances of this happening are
very high.  I am saying this
because the founder of this company,
Obaidullah Syed, also turned out to be a fraud.  What it was doing was that it was
illegally exporting high performance computing equipment and advanced software used for sensitive tasks like nuclear research and missile development to Pakistan Atomic Energy Commission (PAEC), without privy to the US.   The
US caught him red-handed and then the
US District Court for the Northern
District of Illinois
convicted him under 18 USC 371.  Now see,
in the first week of February 2025, Hamas holds a meeting
in PoK.  In the same month, the
demand for the image of the Pahalgam area doubles
and then 10 to 15 days later,
in March 2025, an announcement is made.   The
announcement was that PM Narendra Modi will
visit Kashmir next month i.e. on 19th of April 2025.  To inaugurate Vande Bharat.
Now, when this announcement was made, at that
time Musa, Ali Bhai,
Adil Thokar and others who had come from Pakistan and were in their group, were
inside Kashmir.  In the month in which this
announcement was made, i.e. March 2025, during this
entire month neither any orders for satellite images
came nor did Musa Ali Bhai do
any activity
inside Kashmir.  It is believed that
this planning would have been done in this month itself.
In the forests of Kishtwar, the head of TRF, Sheikh Sajjad Gul,
Musa Ali Bhai and Adil Thokar
might have done the planning in the month of March itself.
But the most
surprising thing in this was that all these people who were
communicating, whether among themselves or
inside Pakistan, no
one came to know about this communication
and why it was not known,
that is also discussed.  See,
earlier this Jaish-e-Mohammed, Lashkar Taiba and
all the terrorists who were there, during the 26/11
Mumbai attack, you must have
heard the conversation at that time, you have even read it on YouTube,
these
people were communicating with each other through Thuraya satellite phone, all of that was
caught, but this time they were given the
Ultra sets that are used by Pakistan Military and
sent to Kashmir,
Huai is a Chinese company which is
band in India, it had launched some special
smartphones, med 60 pro60
series and 11 Ultra, what they did in this was that
they put internal satellite antenna and specialized
chip in these phones.  The purpose of this was
that if the user has an emergency and there is
no internet, he can connect these phones to China's
Tiantong One satellite
network which is managed by China Telecom.  By
connecting to it, voice text
and video chat can be done without
internet.  Basically a normal phone gets
converted into a satellite phone.  And
these Ultra sets were brought into use
after upgrading them.  These ultrasets were being used in the entire planning of Pahalgam and
even on the day of the attack.
They were
not being caught because when
terrorists like Musa and Ali Bhai were sitting in Kashmir and
communicating with each other, what actually was happening was
that the military grade
encrypted radio signals used the Chinese satellite to bypass the Indian
cellular and satellite surveillance system
and then through it the
signals went to the server in Pakistan.
Due to which their communication could not be traced.
And hence it is believed that the
entire month of March and the entire
planning that was done could not be captured.
Their communications could not be captured.
Coordination was done sitting in Karachi, Pakistan and Muzaffarabad, POK
using these Ultra sets.  Where
every step was explained as to when, where and
how to complete the task.  These
ultra sets were recovered only once
in 2023 in an encounter in Surankot, from
a terrorist.  An
attempt was made to crack it.  In fact this
ultraset was also sent to western countries.
But it could not be cracked.
This was a big reason why their
communication could not be traced.
So Ultrasats were
used for communication and to find routes in the forests of Kashmir.
Earlier,
a lot of help was taken from the OGWs.
But this time less help was taken from oGW.  That was
done because they
also used new methods for navigation.  He
used an app called Alpine
Quest.
Which is used by trackers for offline navigation.
When there is no internet, we
use this to navigate in the mountains like Google Maps.  So
in this offline version of Alpine Quest
they used high resolution satellite images.
Because of which this Musa Ali
Bhai works without internet service and without the
help of OGW like Google Map.  In that
way, we were roaming in the forests of Kistwar using this Alpine Quest app.
Now after this, planning starts in the first week of April as to
how to
impact the trade of the tourists coming to Kashmir
so that the entire system which is changing
very fast in Kashmir can be disrupted.
So, in the first week of April,
they decided that the
luxury hotels near the Zabran Valley of Kashmir,
especially those which house foreign tourists, would be
attacked.  Basically they
wanted to impact the trade of Kashmir.  In a way,
this was a trade war against Kashmiris.
One more thing has been said in this that perhaps this
could also be the reason because PM Narendra
Modi was also to come to Kashmir at that time for
inauguration.  So at the same time, the
chances of high value targets like PM's delegates etc. coming to luxury hotels to be there will also increase.  Because of that, the
coverage of the attack will spread even more.
For this reason, these people had fixed a plan to attack the tourists who would be inside the hotel at this time.
Now after the target is fixed, let us
start this Reiki on the Fourth of April 2025.
Adil goes to OGW with Thokar to do Reiki.  The
Pakistani brothers Musa and Ali did
not go for Reiki.  When the Reiki was done, the
OGW would go and share the footage etc. with them
and then a plan would be made and
Reiki would be done on a daily basis.  Now when this
Reiki was happening, in the meantime, on the ninth of
April, there was a local resident named Rashpal.
Two to three terrorists enter his house with M4 rifles.
Now who were these terrorists?
This could not be confirmed.  But one thing was
confirmed that this was neither Musa nor Ali Bhai.
Now after entering Rajpal's house,
they ask for food, travel bag and umbrella.
Then he
asked for the phone from Rajpal.  Make a WhatsApp call from his phone.  They
go somewhere and talk in Urdu
and then break the SIM card and return Rashpal's
phone.  And
after that, when these people were going, they
asked Rashpal about the directions of all the areas around the region and
after asking everything, they left.  And the
next morning, i.e. on 10th of April,
Rashpal would go to the police and
tell them everything.  And along with this, at this time,
other small intelligence was also
coming to the agencies that terrorists were going to attack the hotel.
So, due to all these things, the
Jammu & Kashmir Police and the
paramilitary force together started a joint operation in Dachigam
Nishant and the nearby luxury hotels and
increased security.  The forces had started surveillance at all the
exit and entry points of the hotel.
Guest
verification had started.  The quick reaction
team was kept on standby.
Now at this time one more thing comes out
that the visit of Prime Minister Narendra Modi to
Kashmir
for inauguration is cancelled
and the reason given is that the weather in Kashmir is
bad.  Because of this, this visit will be
cancelled and will be done through video conferencing.
Now, after some time,
this hotel was the place where Musa Ali Bhai and
all of them had fixed their target that they would
attack the tourists of the hotel.  These people
cancel these plans.  Now, there is no clarity about whether this plan was
cancelled due to security reasons or
because of the cancellation of Prime Minister Narendra Modi's visit.
But the target of the hotel which was
fixed first is
cancelled.  Now for this these
people started Reiki again and
after doing Reiki, four locations were finalized in which the
first was Aru Valley.  The second was Betaab
Valley.  Thirdly, he selected the local amusement
parks
and the fourth was Baisaran Valley.  All the locations were such that
tourists could be attracted there so that the
growing economy
could be impacted by the tourists coming here.  Now in the
next step, out of the four locations that were selected,
they removed and
cancelled the location of the amusement park and the reason behind this was
that the Pahalgam Police
Station was just 500 meters away from this location.   That
means the police could have reached within a minute or two
and
they also dropped the Aru Valley location from their plan.  The
reason was that there was a
network problem here.  Secondly, the
connection with the road was very strong.  So it was
very easy for the forces to come and for the people to run away.
And there was the same issue in Betaab Valley also.
Security forces were nearby and the
terrorists had
very limited options for escape after the attack.
And then after calculating all these things
he finally selected
Baisaran Valley of Pahalgam.  The reason was that there was
no security presence here.  Secondly, the tourist footfall
here was comparatively higher than others.  The
car could not reach.  One
could reach there only by trekking or by horse.  It
took 30 to 40 minutes for the security forces to arrive.  The nearest base of CRPF's
Delta Company 116 Battalion was
4 to 5 km away.  It was on.  This map has
dense forests all around it, so it
was very easy to attack and escape into the forests and there were
no CCTV cameras.  So from here
they
fixed the location as Byasaran Valley of Pahalgam
and started preparations for it.  And
when this happens, the next day
news comes that the US Vice President is
coming to India and because of this news,
it was decided that the attack will be carried out when the US Vice
President is in India
so that the
news gets made all over the world.  Therefore the date of 22nd April was fixed.
Now as soon as the date was fixed, the
remaining terrorists were already
around the Baisaran area.  But on 21 April,
Musa and Ali Bhai, who were hiding in the jungle for so many days,
get the green signal
and both of them leave the forest of Kokernag on the same date, i.e. on the night of 21st April. The
route they take towards Baisaran Valley is
Kishtwar Daksham Larnu Chatpal Aishmukam.
For going towards 22 Run, in some reports you will
also find the Avantipura Taral Siriguwar Pahalgaon route mentioned
but in most reports
only the Kishtwar route is mentioned, so I
took that one. Now these people walk from here
and after walking continuously for 21 to 22 hours,
they had trained in such a way that
they walk continuously and after walking continuously for 21 to 22 hours, they
come and sit in the forests around Baisaran and wait to
attack.  Adil Thokar
was there in the area near Shri Gubara, so he was
already there.  So what I mean to say is
that now all the terrorists had
come and sat in the forests around Baisaran Valley
and were waiting in ambush. Now see,
Pahalgam is here and it is
5 to 6 km from here.  If
you trek up through the rough unpaved road, it takes around 1 hour
and after trekking you
reach this gate and as soon as
you enter through this gate, you can see a
green field of 800 meters long and 600 meters wide.
This plain is Baisaran Valley.  And the
terrorists were hiding and waiting in the surrounding forests.
So there is one entry-
exit gate from here and another entry-
exit gate of this ground from here.  This entire
area was given by the Pahalgam Development Authority
to a man from Bridge Bahra through
tender for 3 years for Rs. 3 crores.  So
he introduced the ticketing system inside this area.
Started zip lining
and also secured the area by putting fencing around it.
So it means that there are
two entry and exit gates in this entire area.  There
is fencing all around.
And security is
provided here during the Amarnath Yatra.  The rest of the time,
security is provided only when the tour operators or
hoteliers inform the authorities
that there are more tourists.
Now after this the
day of 2nd of April 2025 starts.  The
entry to Baisaran Valley opens at 9:00 AM and
tourists from Pahalgam start reaching
Baisaran Valley from their respective locations
and from the
main gate of Baisaran Valley, they buy tickets and
start entering Baisaran Valley
and gradually 1000 tickets were sold.
Meaning that there had been a footfall of 1000 people
in this area.  And now after this, it was
1:30 in the afternoon and till then there were about
400 tourists left inside this location.
All the rest had gone back.
No one had any idea
what was going to happen next.  Now, after 15 minutes,
i.e. at 1:45, the first terrorist, most
probably Adil Thokar, enters.
Look, whatever I will tell you here,
in this entire scene it will be difficult to say whether
Musa went from this side or Adil went from this side.
Because it could not be confirmed
from where Adil entered and from where Musa
entered.  Only this much has been confirmed that Musa,
Ali Bhai and Adil were there who
fired the guns.  And some terrorists were there as a
backup in the forest.  There were some
who did not have guns in their hands but were
mixed in the crowd.  Therefore, it was difficult to
say how many terrorists were actually there at that time,
but it was confirmed that Ali Bhai, Musa and Adil
Thokar were there who
picked up guns and killed people.  So this is how
a terrorist wearing a Kashmiri pheran
enters the ground from this side.  She had hidden it
etc. inside the Kashmiri pheran
she was wearing.  So he comfortably
enters among the public and
starts moving towards this entry-exit gate.
As soon as he reaches the entry-exit gate,
he takes out his gun and starts firing in the air.  It does
not use it on any person.  He continuously fires in the air
and
tries to lead the crowd towards the main entry-exit gate.
Now as the crowd
starts gathering towards the main entry exit gate.
So from the same side, from the forest side, which was over the fence,
two terrorists jumped from there and
stood there wearing military track suits etc. and most likely, they were
Musa and Ali brothers.  The public was thinking
that they were security personnel.  So see,
some terrorists came and fired randomly and
killed people.  It was not like that.  This was a
well planned trap in which both the
entry and exit points were properly blocked
and all the tourists were
surrounded from all sides.  And the area was very
large, so when all these things were happening,
some people who were on the other side could not know
what was going on on the other side.  He was
comfortably doing his zip lining etc.
Now when the crowd reaches the main entry-exit point,
those two terrorists, who
people thought were security personnel,
also start firing.
Then they gather all the crowd here
at this point where there are Bhelpuri, tea and food stalls.
Separates men and women.  All these things were done
within 50 meters from the main entry-exit gate.  Now
after separating men and women, they
ask the men whether they are Hindu or
not.  And then those who do not tell, they make them recite Kalma.
As soon as the terrorists came to Devashish Bhattacharya, he recited Kalma and the
terrorists left him and went to the other side.
A Christian was
standing nearby and he was
asked to speak on the issue of Palestine.  Some were forced to remove their pants
and then the Hindu tourists were
shot at close range.  Now, at this time,
Adil Hussain, who was a pony rider, had
brought the tourists for a tour.  A
terrorist shoots one of Adil's tourists, and
Adil begins arguing with him.  He
tries to snatch his gun.  So the terrorists
shoot three bullets at Adil Hussain and kill him too.
He had an M4 rifle.  It was an AK-47.
GP cameras were installed on their bodies and feet.  So they were
recording all these things and
taking selfies with the people who had died and keeping them in their phones.  There are
many more things which I will not be
able to tell and you will not be able to hear either.  So
these people did all these things for 20 to 25 minutes.
In all these things, 26 people
lost their lives.  This is his name.
And then
after all this was done, he forcibly snatched two phones from the crowd.
And
taking those phones, he jumped over the fence on the left side wall and ran away
into the forest.  Now
he has run away.  But there were people shouting all around on the side.  He was
asking for help for his family.  But there was
no help anywhere.  Then somehow at
2:30 pm, for the first time,
information reaches the police that terrorists have done all this in Baisaran Valley.  The
SAO of Pahalgam police station gets shocked
and it takes him time to reach Baisaran valley, so to
send help quickly, he
informs Abdul Wahid, the general president of all the unions of Kashmir,
that all this has happened and
help should be sent as quickly as possible.
As soon as Abdul Wahid comes to know about it, he informs the president of Pony Owners
Association, Rais Ahmed Bhatt.
His phone network was also not working, so
he
starts running alone towards Baisaran valley and whoever he meets on the way, he takes
them with him
and takes a shortcut through the jungle and
reaches before Farsas.  That
means that in such a huge crowd only five to
six people were able to reach out for help.  These people were
not even professionals, so they were doing the
rescue in whatever way possible, by sitting the victims on their backs etc.
Then somehow
SAO Riyaz reaches there and then
Rajesh Kumar, Commandant of the 116 battalion of CRPF, along
with his team of 25 people, reaches the site running on foot
and then the rescue operation
begins.  Helicopters etc. come.
Now as soon as this attack takes place,
shortly thereafter TRF
takes the responsibility of the attack and gives the reason that it has been done
because of the domicile issue that is being issued.
Now after this the entire
area is sanitized.
Statements are taken from the tourists with whom all these things happened.
Sketches are made.  The crackdowns begin.  Those who
were OGWs are caught.
Their statements are taken.  And the people who were
involved were caught and how the planning was done was
linked to it. And the
houses of the OGWs and terrorists who were being caught were being
destroyed.
Now the most important thing in this is
that TRF had already taken the responsibility
of this entire attack.  But on 25th of April
2025, United Nations Security Council
issued a press statement
criticizing this Pahalgam attack.  So in the
first draft of this press statement, the
name of Direct the Resistance Front TRF was written.  But as soon as
Pakistan saw the name of TRF written in it, it
opposed it.  Pakistan
said that the
name of TRF should be removed from this official press statement of the UN.
This is the original copy of that statement.  You can
pause and see.  The name of TRF is
not mentioned anywhere.  The Chinese Navy also blocked India's proposal to
blacklist the TRF in the UN's 1267 Sanctions Committee.
China's diplomat Chang Li
removed the name of TRF from the list at the request of Pakistan and
after removing the name, Pakistan proudly
told its parliament that it did
not allow TRF's name to appear.  Now see, the search operation is
still going on.  OGWs are being caught.
But those who had their hands on the guns that day and
who had killed Musa Ali Bhai, Adil
Thokar, all of them are still alive.  The
Indian Force is still searching for them in the forests of Kistwar.  The
operation is in progress.
I will let you know as more details come.  Lastly, let me
tell you once again that you
must try Derma Touch Salicylic 2% Face Wash.
Thank you.
[music]