As soon as Kohinoor reached the soil of England
, the Queen was hit on the head with an iron rod.
Kuldeep Nair reached Rajya Sabha, got 50 MPs
and Manmohan Singh ji to sign for Kohinoor.   The
Taliban also jumped in saying that the Kohinoor
is ours.  When the Queen received Kohinoor in front of the whole world,
she got a black eye
and an injury on her head.
What is there in Kohinoor that India,
Pakistan, Iran, Afghanistan all are saying that they
want it.
Bad times started for the person to whom Kohinoor went other than the female.
Kohinoor was of 795 carats but
in the end only 105 carats were
left.  Due to all these legal problems,
Kohinoor has not been
able to return to India till date.  In Article 3 of the Treaty of Lahore, it is
clearly written that
as soon as Kohinoor fell down from the turban,
Nadir Shah said no to it.
[MUSIC]
Now look, in business just earning money is
not enough.  It is important to understand timely whether the money is coming or is stuck
and where is it going.
Therefore, it
is important for businesses to keep track of accounts receivable and accounts payable.  Now if you do all this manually, it will
take time and mistakes will also
occur.  That's why smart businesses are using
Udu Accounting App.  Just upload the PDF
and the details are automatically fetched using AI and OCR.
Udu reads the details automatically
and you can also apply TDS from here.
Through the Aging Report in Udu Accounting App, you can know whose payment is
pending for how many days and their auto follow
ups are
automatically sent by Udu through emails and WhatsApp.  You can see all the important real
time details here on the dashboard
and financial reports are also
available here and complicated government
compliance like e-invoice, e-way bill,
GST filing, audit trail, everything is managed from here.
Apart from accounting, Udu
Pay offers 45 plus apps like invoicing, website builder, CRM,
e-commerce.  And the
best part first app is lifetime free.
With unlimited users.  Support and
hosting is also free lifetime.  So
simplify your accounting
with Ood Accounting app for free.  I have
given the link in the description.  So let's
come back to the topic.  Look, today there is
Guntur district in Andhra Pradesh, so
around the year 1306, this
entire area was a part of the Golconda region
and the Krishna river used to pass from this side.  The
Kakatiya Dynasty ruled over this entire area
and this Golconda
region was the only region in the world at that time
where diamonds were
mined.
Diamond mining had not taken place anywhere else before this.
What the locals here used to do was
extract diamonds on a daily basis using ancient placer mining, which was a technique.
Basically, in this technique, these people used to mine diamonds from the
alveolar deposits near rivers
using bamboo sieve
and the
diamonds were also traded from here all over the world
and this process continued for a long time.
Now what happens in a day,
what does a group do in the same year i.e. year 1306
?  I was mining in this area
and while mining I found a very
unique diamond.  At that time its weight was
793 carats.  That means
158.6 grams.  He had exceptional clarity.  The
clarity was at the level of what today we call a D grade diamond.
Now when they found this diamond, all these
people together went and gave this diamond to the
rulers of the Kakatiya Dynasty.
And then in this way, for the first time in the year 1306,
this diamond came to the rulers of the Kakatiya Dynasty, which later came to be
known as Kohinoor.  Look, in the details that
I am giving you, you will find more things
if you go on the internet.  But the
rulers of the Kakatiya Dynasty are
considered the first documented owners of the Kohinoor Diamond.
And for the sake of understanding,
I will now call this diamond Kohinoor Diamond.  But
its name becomes Kohinoor later on.
I will tell him now.  And let
me add one more thing in this before telling you further
that whatever details I am
telling you about Koinoor Diamond, there are
different stories and
different details about it.  But I have
picked only those details for which maximum
records and facts are available.  For example,
I chose the story of Golconda because it has the closest geological
evidence and the writers' records are related to
it.  For example, according to the evidence,
Kohinoor is a Type 2A diamond
in which there is no nitrogen impurity.
And it is mined using an ancient placer mining
technique.  And
according to the experts,
all the characteristics of this Koinoor diamond are
exactly like the diamonds found in the Golconda region.  And many
seismologists like Harsh K Gupta
have also officially confirmed that
Kohinoor is from the Golconda region.
Even in 2023, research was published in the Journal of Earth System
Science.
In which it was told that Kohinoor Diamond
originated from Kimber Light Pipe and the
colourful wines of Golconda region were
very famous for Kimber Light Field.
I am telling you this story on the basis of satellite images, geochemical analysis and the closest proofs that have been matched so far.
So what happens after this is that the
diamond reaches the rulers of the Katakia Dynasty.
And
one thing common among their rulers was that they respected their family deity
Bhadrakali ji a lot.  They also had a
huge Bhadrakali temple in their capital Warangal.
So when this diamond
came to Kakti rulers, they decided
that they will get it
installed in the left eye of Goddess Bhadrakali inside the temple.
And when this happened, after some time, this
superstition also spread in the surrounding area that
this was done because whoever will
own this diamond will rule very strongly
but his bad luck will start.
[MUSIC]
Only God and woman can wear this diamond without any
harm.  That's why this was
done.  Now look, the line I
just said that the diamond will bring misfortune,
people in the surrounding areas were talking about it.
Whenever there is talk of Kohinoor, this
line about misfortune and curse will always
come in front of you.  And let me tell you one thing about this
that if you go out to find its proof then
only one thing will come up that
this has been said in the Lost Hindu Text of the year 1306.
But its direct citation is
not mentioned in any Veda, Purana or any classical Hindu scriptures.
But the reference given by people is the
details given about Shyam Mantaka Mani in chapter 56 of Dasam Skandh of Bhagavat Purana.
People compare it with the story of Kohinoor's
misfortune and
this thing is also backed by Indian historians and research
scholars.  So, what I mean to
say is that actually this
story of curse and misfortune of Kohinoor Diamond is that whoever
gets it, bad times will start for him.
Only females can wear it.  This has
emerged as a secondary and tertiary source.
Meaning that its original source was not found
but British, Indian and French writers
and historians spoke so much about it
that people started writing about it again and again
which started being considered as proof.  So now
see, when Kohinoor diamond came to Kakatiya Empire, at
that time Kakatiya Empire was at
its peak.  Wealth, power, diamonds,
sports, strong administration, there was
no one to defeat them anywhere.  But
some time after the arrival of Kohinoor,
Alauddin Khilji of Delhi Sultanate sent his general
Malik Kafur to attack the Kakati Empire.  They
defeated them and took away
all the wealth and treasure of the umpire who had not lost for so long, including
Kohinoor, from
Warangal and sent it to their sultanate in Delhi.
And after reaching Delhi,
Alauddin Khilji had an official named Khwaja
[ __ ].  He was given the task to do the
valuation of all the treasure that had come from Warangal.
So at this time Kohinoor
appears and Khilji also asks
at this time, how much would it cost?  So
Khwaja [ __ ] who was given this task
says that this is a very unique thing.   There is
only one such thing in the world whose
price no one can calculate.  And
from here Khilji comes to know about Kohinoor.
Now this diamond had come to Khilji
but some time after its arrival,
Alauddin Khilji died.  Malik
Kafuz kills Khilji's children.  Then
he himself dies.  So many problems occur back to back that the
Khilji dynasty
collapses.  And then
after this the Kohinoor Diamond
went to the Tughlaq dynasty.  Then he lost too.  In this
way Kohinoor passed to multiple kings and
dynasties.  And because so many
kings had lost, the superstition spread
in the surrounding areas that whoever goes to it
brings misfortune.  So at
this time the general public
started associating Kohinoor with black magic.  Now
what happens next?  Passing from one king
to another, the Kohinoor Diamond
reached Babar.  Babur and his
son Humayun defeated Ibrahim Lodi and
brought this Kohinoor diamond with them.
And at this time, Babar's son Humayun had
also asked Babar that
so many people are after Kohinoor.  What is so special about it?
how much it cost?  So Babar had
said at that time that
this single diamond can bear the expenses of the entire world for one day.  At this time
it was not named Kohinoor.  Babar used to
call it Diamond.  Now after this,
Babar died on 26th of December 1530.
After that his son Humayun
takes over the throne.  But the entire umpire had
become weak.  Seeing the opportunity, Sher Shah
Suri attacks Humayun.
Now when Humayun gets upset and starts losing,
he runs away from there.  But while
running away, somehow he
keeps the Kohinoor with himself and to
save his life, he leaves for Persia (which is
Iran in today's date) in July 1544
so that he can survive.  Now when
Humayun sets out towards Persia with the
Kohinoor diamond, he stops in between to
perform ablution at the time of prayer and takes
out the Kohinoor diamond and keeps it on the side,
and in the process he forgets what the Kohinoor is.
Now Humayun became very
worried but he had
a courtier named Jauhar with him.  Luckily he finds it
and then somehow the
Kohinoor again comes to Humayun.
Now after this,
Humayun reaches Persia in the beginning of the year 1544.
Reaching there, King Tamasp
asks for help from them.
Tamask
keeps Humayun by providing him security.  And then when
Humayun remained safe for many years, he had nothing more to offer in return.
He gives his Kohinoor
diamond to Tamas.  So in
this way, the ownership of Kohinoor goes
out of India for the first time and
reaches Persia.  That means it reaches what is today's Iran.
But this
lasts for a very short time.  After this, many
things happen due to which
Kohinoor again comes back to India.  What happened was that the
control of Kohinoor was now
with Tamasp and Tamas was a
Shia Muslim.  The Sunni led Ottoman umpire was
moving very fast.  So Tamas became a
little insecure and he also
tried to bring
together all the Shia Muslims in the world.  So
at that time in India,
King Burhan Nizam Shah of Ahmednagar Sultanate was a very
powerful Shia Muslim in that area.
So Tamas wanted to unite them
so that all the Shias could be together.
In the year 1547, he sends his ambassador Mehtar
Jamal with Kohinoor and gifts it to
King Burhan Nizam Shah to join him
and in this way
Kohinoor comes back to India.
Now after coming inside India, Kohinoor
started getting transferred from one king to another.  Whoever was powerful, would take
possession of Kohinoor in some way or the other and then in this way
Kohinoor reached Shah Jahan around the 7th of July 1656.
When Kohinoor came to Shah Jahan, he became very
obsessed with it.  Shah Jahan had
kept it separately in a royal jewel box.  And there was a
famous diamond cutter named Hartsio
Borio in Shahjahan's court.  And Shahjahan gives him the task.
This rare Kohinoor that we have, please make it
beautiful somehow.
Whatever money is required for this, we will provide it.
After discussing diamond cutting with Shah Jahan,
Hartsio starts cutting and polishing Kohinoor
so that the reflection of light
increases further.  It
looked more beautiful.  But in doing this,
Hartsio reduced the 793 carat
Koinur to 280 carats.  And
when Shah Jahan sees this thing, he gets very
angry.  Far from paying the money, he
instead
imposed a fine of Rs. 10,000 on Hartancio.  And when it became
small, Shah Jahan got
Takht-e-Tosh made, the most expensive Peacock Throne in the world at that time.  It
was under process.  This was a very
unique peacock throne.  Inside it, Shah Jahan
placed sapphires, rubies, emeralds, pearls, several kgs of gold and unique stones worth more than 500 pounds.  The Peacock Throne was more costly than the Taj Mahal.
So the Peacock Throne was already
this expensive.  It was more expensive than the Taj Mahal.
After that, when Kohinoor was also placed on it
, the Peacock Throne became even more unique.
And this Peacock Throne was discussed far and wide.
And when the Peacock Throne was ready,
Shah Jahan placed the Kohinoor and
started sitting comfortably on it.  And soon
after this, i.e. in the year 1658, Shah Jahan's
son Aurangzeb removed Shah Jahan and
put him in prison in Agra Fort and became the king himself.
But after becoming the king, Aurangzeb did
one thing.  He did
not get the formal condolence done in Delhi and even refused to sit on the Peacock
Throne on which the Kohinoor was placed.
Some people
say this even today that this was the reason why
Aurangzeb ruled for a long time.
He did not die early.  And then
after Aurangzeb more kings came.  He also
used the Peacock Throne.  But by the time Mohammad Shah
Rangeela came, the Mughal umpire had become very
weak.  They were fighting amongst themselves.
Now at this time
Nadir Shah who was sitting in Persia
saw an opportunity here that the Mughals had become weak
and they had a lot of treasure.   It
is Kohinoor and taking advantage of the opportunity, Nadir Shah
attacks Mohammad Shah Rangeela in the year 1738.
[MUSIC]
17 Mark Major Turning
Point and Nadir Shah was not supposed to rule over India.
He had come to rob the empty treasury.
So after losing the battle,
Nadir Shah took away the entire treasure of Mohammad Shah Rangeela.  The Peacock Throne was
broken and all the
diamonds etc. studded on it were taken out.
Mohammad Shah Rangeela gave everything.
Gave away all the treasure.  But
he hid one thing, Kohinoor, inside his turban
so that Nadir Shah could not find it.  Now
Nadir Shah had already
heard a lot about Kohinoor.  He
tried to find out and found out that there was a courtesan inside Rangeela's court,
Noor Bai.  He
secretly told Nadir Shah that Rangeela had
hidden the Kohinoor in his turban.
Now there is a very old tradition in which the
king exchanges his turban.
So Nadir Shah deliberately
told Rangeela that we have to exchange turbans.  So
Mohammad Shah Rangeela shows a
lot of reluctance in the beginning.  But due to compulsion
he has to exchange his turban
and as soon as he is exchanging the turban.  The
Kohinoor slips out of his turban and
falls down.  And as it falls down,
Kohinoor comes out from Nadir Shah's mouth, which means Mountain of Light and
from here Kohinoor got its name, which people
call Kohinoor.
Alam Arai Nadri is the first authentic
source in which it was first
told how the name of Kohinoor was
used by Nadir Shah
and then after taking all the treasure, Nadir Shah
takes Kohinoor from India to
Persia and in this way
Kohinoor goes back from India.
Now after getting Kohinoor,
bad times started for Nadir Shah also.
They are also killed.  The entire
umpire becomes weak.  Nadir
Shah's treasury starts getting looted.
And at this time, Nadir Shah's
trusted guard General Ahmed Shah Durrani goes to
Afghanistan with Kohinoor
and starts his own Durrani Empire there
and in this way Kohinoor
becomes a part of the Afghan Royal Family
and then year after year it is passed on in the family
and in the year 1803, Kohinoor
comes to Shah Shuja Durrani and
as soon as Kohinoor came, bad times started for him too.
His cousins ​​rebel.   Due to
fear of which, he first gives Kohinoor to his wife
Wafa Begum and his brother Zaman Shah
and sends them towards Punjab under the protection of Maharaja Ranjit
Singh.
And as soon as he sends his wife and brother
here, the military commander of Shah Shuja
arrests him.  Now as soon as this
happens, Shah Shuja's wife Wafa Begum
goes to Maharaja Ranjit Singh.  She
asks him for help and tells him to
save her husband Shah Shuja.  In return,
I will give you the most precious thing in the world,
Kohinoor.  And this was the time when Maharaja
Ranjit Singh had asked him
what is so special about Kohinoor that it is so valuable
?  So Wafa Begum says at that time that
if five strong wrestlers
throw stones in all four directions and towards the sky, then the
distance covered by it if
filled with gold, even then it will still be
more than the value of Kohinoor.  And then
after this the deal is fixed that the most
precious Kohinoor will be given to Maharaja Ranjit Singh
and in return he will get Shah
Shuja released and bring him back.
And one more thing was fixed in exchange for Kohinoor
that Maharaja Ranjit Singh will give Rs. 3
lakh and 50 horses in exchange for it.  Now as soon as the
deal is done, Maharaja Ranjit Singh
uses his forces to rescue Shah Shuja
very quickly and bring him back.  Now the
deal was that after Shah Shuja returned,
Kohinoor was to be returned to him and his wife.
But both of them start showing reluctance.
But after multiple discussions, when Maharaja
Ranjit Singh put pressure on him and got the
house terraced, then Shah Shuja
officially
gave the Kohinoor Diamond to Maharaja Ranjit Singh around October 1813.
And Maharaja Ranjit Singh ji was
very happy after getting the possession of Kohinoor.
He liked Kohinoor very much.  So daily
whenever he went out, he used to tie this on his forehead.
But after this
he kept it in the royal treasury
and then wore it only on special occasions.
And
two more diamonds were placed next to this Kohinoor diamond.  This is his image.
Now after this, by the year 1830, the
influence of the British became very
strong in India.  And the
talk about the Sikh umpire's treasure and Kohinoor was spread
far and wide.  And the British also had their eyes on this treasure.  The
British had heard so much about Kohinoor that
in the same year 1830, British officer
W.G. Osborne himself went to the umpire’s court and
requested Maharaja Ranjit Singh to see Kohinoor once because he had
heard so much about it.  Once you show it,
it gets shown as well.
He has also written about this incident in his book
Court and Camp of Ranjit Singh.
And this was the time when the British
wanted to gain control over the Sikh Empire and its treasury at any cost.  But
at that time the Sikh umpire was very strong.
Now what happens in the meantime is that the year 1838
starts and Maharaja Ranjit Singh's
health starts deteriorating.  And
this was the time when Maharaja Ranjit Singh ji had
started making huge donations.  He
also asked to donate Kohinoor to the Jagannath Temple.
All these
things are mentioned in the Sikh Court of Official Record Ummad
ul Tawarikh.
So the donations were going on but
when it came to the donation of Kohinoor,
Beliram, the treasurer of Raja Ranjit Singh, got
upset and
refused to donate it saying that it was such a precious
diamond.  It is the property of the Sikh umpire.
This is not personal property.  Therefore it
should not be donated.  But then
amidst all this,
Maharaja Ranjit Singh died on 27th June 1839.
Then after this his son Kharak Singh
takes over the throne.  But Kohinoor is
not donated.  But as soon as
he becomes king and gets possession of Kohinoor
, someone gives him slow poison.
He also died on the fifth of November 1840.
Then Raja Naunihal Singh
takes over the throne.  They also get Kohinoor.  At the
same time, the Hazaribagh gate also falls on them.
They too die.
Then Kohinoor comes to Sher Singh.  He
too was executed on 15th of September 1843.
So in every house, people
started talking about the fact that this
Kohinoor is cursed.  Maharaja Ranjit
Singh ji had rightly said that it should be
donated to the temple.  And this whole
story of Kohinoor was
published in the daily newspapers and everyone in England also
read it.  Kohinoor had become
very famous in England also.  The Queen
also became very interested
in Kohinoor.  So after the death of Maharaja Ranjit Singh, the
Sikh umpires
started dying one after the other.  There was a leadership crisis and the
Sikh umpire became very weak.
Apart from his 5 year old son Dilip Singh, no
one else was left.  And then, out of
compulsion, 5 year old Dilip
Singh was made the king in the year 1843.  And his mother
Jind Kaur used to take care of all these things.
And the British found this to be the best time to
exert their control over the Sikh umpire.
And then on 11th of December 1845, the British
attacked the Sikh umpire and
took control of him.  And Maharaja Dilip
Singh's mother was put under
house arrest inside the fort and
he took all the political power in his hands.
And what do the British do after this?   He gets the
seven year old Maharaja Dilip Singh to
sign the Treaty of Lahore.  It
is signed twice.  I will tell you at once.  There were
many things in this treaty.
But through this treaty,
Kohinoor was officially
taken under the control of the British.
These things were written about Kohinoor in Article 3 of this treaty.
You please pause it and see once.
And because of the Treaty of Lahore,
Kohinoor was now officially
taken under the control of the British.  And
because there have been
huge battles over the control of the ownership of Kohinoor.
So on paper he
took it with him.  Along with this,
a ceremony was also organised on the 7th of December 1849
in which Kohinoor was handed over to the British in front of everyone.
And then after this, it was
planned to reserve Kohinoor for the Queen and gift it to her and it was announced
that now the rightful owner of Kohinoor will
be the Queen.  Now after this the next
task was to take Kohinoor to England to the
Queen.  But before that it was decided
that
Kohinoor would be gifted to the Queen to impress her.  So if we
tell her the interesting story behind this, she will be very impressed.
And for this task, Governor General
Dalhousie called Assistant Magistrate
Theo Matt Calfe and gave him the task to
find out about the history of Kohinoor and its factual
history as quickly as possible and submit a report and there
should not be anything wrong in it and in a very short time Matcafe collected details
about Kohinoor, from where it was
mined, what was its location,
how it came to Nadir Shah and the
story that was going around about its bad luck and misfortune, and
submitted a report,
but this was a story of miss, misfortune and bad luck.
All these things were
also being published in the newspapers of England.  So the
people of England were also very excited
that the Kohinoor was going to
come to our country in some time.  Now after this the
next task was to take Kohinoor from India to
England.  So firstly Kohinoor was
safely brought from Lahore Fort to Mumbai on the second of February 1850.
And then on the
sixth of April 1850, Captain Lockyer
took it in the British Royal Navy ship HMS Media and took it towards England.
Now Kohinoor is in the ship.  So that no
one gets suspicious about it, Kohinoor is
kept in a normal box and a lock is put on it
which has two keys
and one key is shared by Ramsay and the other by the Captain.
Now after this the
ship leaves for England
but after some time cholera spreads in the ship.
When the captain goes down to the bottom of the ship,
he finds two crew members
dead because of illness.  So
these people make some arrangements and
stay in Mauritius.  Treatment etc. is
done there.  But after leaving from there,
when we go a little further, we
also get stuck in a storm etc.  And then somehow, after facing
all the difficulties, it reaches
Poss Smooth Port of England on the second of July 1850.
And here in London, there was eager waiting.  There was
only talk about Kohinoor everywhere.  The
newspapers were
filled with details of Kohinoor only.
[MUSIC]
She's so excited.  Now what happens is
that on one side the Kohinoor had
just reached England.  On the other hand, the
Prime Minister of England, Robert Peel, was
going towards Constitution Hill on a horse.  Suddenly the horse throws him down and
crushes him, and he dies exactly on the same day on which
Kohinoor reaches England.
Now, on one hand, the PM has died.  On the
other hand, Queen Victoria
leaves Cambridge House and goes to the
house of her uncle Prince Adolphus who had died. All of a sudden,
a man named Robert Francis takes out an iron rod and
attacks Queen Victoria.
All this news was being published simultaneously in the news.  On one
side there was Kohinoor and on the other side all the
incidents that were happening were being published.  So people
started associating Kohinoor with black magic and thought that
bringing it might be a mistake.  Now on the
next day, i.e., third of July 1850, the
Queen had to receive Kohinoor.
John, who was the President of the Board of Control, had to
hand over Kohinoor to the Queen.
And when the Queen was receiving the world's most famous and precious
diamond, one of her eyes was black
and she had an injury on her forehead.  Now Kohinoor had
reached the Queen.  The Queen
finds the shape of Kohinoor a bit bad.
So at that time David Brewster was
also known as the Father of Modern Experimental Optics.  She gives the
task of correcting Konur's shape to them.
And in return David
Brewster took 8000 British pounds.  And by
correcting the shape and cutting of Kohinoor, it was
made more beautiful.  But
in the process of doing this its weight reduced again.
Now only 105.6 carats
i.e. 21.12 grams of Kohinoor was left.  Now this
thing had happened but after some time
in the year 1861 when Queen Victoria's husband
Prince Albert also dies then the
story starts again that
only a female can save herself from this.
Otherwise, if there is any male then it will bring a lot of bad luck for him.
So this was the time when
Kohinoor was put into the Queen's crown
so that it would remain exclusive only to the
female members of the British Royal Family.
And if there is any male member of the Royal Family then
he/she cannot wear Kohinoor.  In fact,
even today, only females wear it
in the royal family.  Now see, after this,
in the year 1947 when our country became independent and the
time came for the British to leave,
our government gave a formal
request that Kohinoor should be returned
to India, but the British
completely refused at that time.
Then there was no discussion about Kohinoor for a long time.
But then
what happens in the year 1953 is that the
coronation of Queen Elizabeth takes place.  At that time,
India once again
makes a request to take back Kohinoor.  But again the
request is rejected.
Till now, all the
requests for taking back Kohinoor were being made by India through formal discussions and
letters.
No court case was filed.  Now when all these
things were happening, in the year 1976,
Pakistan also jumped into it after seeing India.
Pakistan says that Kohinoor
is the heritage of Lahore.  Lahore was the
capital of the Sikh Empire at that time and it was through the Treaty of
Lahore that you people took Coonoor.
So give it back to us.  Now seeing this, the
Taliban also jumped into it.
He says that Kohinoor has also been a part of the Durani Empire.
So we
should get it back.  We have a right to it.  By doing this,
Iran also says that we should meet.
Now after seeing all these things the British
refused to allow it to all the countries.  He
rejects everyone's request.
He simply says one thing that Kohinoor has legally gone to
Britain.  Therefore, you have
no right over it.  Now after this, for a long time there was
no discussion about Kohinoor in India.  And then comes the year
1997.  At this time Kuldeep Nair, who was
also a journalist earlier, became an MP
in the Rajya Sabha.  And a year after becoming an MP, that is
in the year 1998, he gathered 50 more
MPs with him and got them to
sign a petition and again appealed to the British Government
that Kohinoor is a
symbol of colonial plunder.  It
should be returned to India as soon as possible.  And
these were the 50 MPs who had signed this petition.
Dr. Manmohan Singh was also present in this.
He also signed this
petition.  There is a lot of noise about
bringing back Kohinoor.  A lot of news is also made.
Looking at the public sentiments, the then external foreign minister Jaswant Singh had
said that Kohinoor would be brought back.
But the matter stops right there.  Then
after this comes the year 2002.  At this time
Queen Elizabeth's helper dies.
And a crown containing Kohinoor was placed on his coffin.
Now
all these things were being telecast live within India
as well.  And seeing these things the
common people of India start saying again.
Again she demands that Kohinoor
should be returned.  The Sikh community in India
also got very angry that
Kohinoor had been the legacy of the Sikh umpire for a long time.
It should somehow be brought back and
installed in the Amritsar temple.
At the same time, the officials of Jagannath Puri Temple
also
demanded that Kohinoor be brought back at any cost.
Maharaja Ranjit Singh's wish was
that Kohinoor should go to Jagannath Puri Temple.
And at this time,
these things were getting published in the newspapers almost every day and back
to back PILs were being filed in the courts so that the
Indian Government could somehow
put pressure on the British Government and get
Kohinoor back.  India has a right on this.
This is a part of India's heritage.  Out of
all the PILs, one
PIL was filed in 2016 by All India Human Rights and
Social Justice Front NGO.  He had
filed a PIL and requested the
government to take some steps.   The
case went on in the court for several days and on
behalf of the government, Solicitor General
Ranjit Kumar said that Kohinoor was neither
stolen nor did the British take it away forcibly.
This was given of his own free will.
So we cannot make such claims and if we
make such claims then tomorrow some
other country will take some thing or the other from us and
claim it.  Now as soon as this news
comes out, people's sentiments
start turning against the government.  The news starts getting made
and when the matter gets out of hand, then the
government reverses its stand
and says that India
belongs only to Kohinoor.  But there are difficulties in bringing it legally.
Challenges are still coming.
But we will take whatever steps are necessary to get it back.
And
actually, there were legal hurdles in bringing Konur back.  The
Antiquities and
Art Treasures Act of 1972 allows the government to
claim ownership of its valuable historical art.
But there was a problem in this as
it was applicable only for items manufactured after the year 1972.
India could not legally use it to
bring back Kohinoor.
And secondly, both India and
Britain have signed the UNESCO Convention
and its Article Seven allows that
a country can take back
its cultural items or treasures by taking legal action against another country.
But there was the same problem in this as well that
both the countries had signed this convention for the items issued after the year 1970.
So the matter got stuck here as well.
And
as per Article 1 of the convention which was signed by both the countries, there was
also a rule that if there is any item of cultural heritage, then
it will be seen
from which country that item originally came.
Like where did you find it for the first time or what is the proof of
that thing.  But here also the problem
arises that with time,
everything including the country's state has changed.  First there
was only India, then Pakistan was also formed.
Apart from that, Kohinoor has
travelled to every area from India to Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan
and was colonised by the British at that time.
So actually there is a conflict as to
which country it will be considered as at that time from where it originated.
But even after that the common people of India did
not stop.  Many PILs keep
going to Indian courts back to back year after year.
And then, fed up, the Supreme Court
dismissed the PIL and gave a statement that
we cannot get Kohinoor back by passing an order for a foreign country.
So
this problem arose here as well.  But even after all these things, the
pressure from the general public is so much
that the government has to give statements from time to time and
fight a legal battle
with the British government to bring back Kohinoor.
And it has happened many times that India has
put forward its arguments very strongly.
In which India says that the Kohinoor which was
given to the British was
not given willingly.  At that time Dilip Singh was very
young and the British put his mother under
house arrest and became the guardian themselves and
got the Kohinoor legally signed.  And
India repeatedly says that Kohinoor
is not just a diamond for India but it is a cultural heritage.  This is
an artifact for India which
represents the culture of India.
And India also says that no matter
how much the British say that they have a legal
right over it, the actual fact is that the
British colonized India and
misused their power to take Kohinoor to their
country.  In fact, the
proof of Archaeological Survey also clearly states that
Kohinoor originated in India,
within the Golconda region.
[Music]
And at the same time, the Indian
rulers have had the ownership of Kohinoor for the longest time.
But the British
have only one argument on all these things, that
we have acquired Kohinoor legally through the Treaty of Lahore.
This thing is clearly mentioned in Article 3 and for the last 150 years
Kohinoor has been a part of the Crown.
And if we give away Kohinoor like this, then all the
museums of the world, including the
museum in England, will become empty.  Because in
this way some country or the other will claim the artifact
in some other country's museum and
demand it back.
And
one thing I told you earlier was that the British had organised a
small ceremony.  After that he
took Kohinoor.  British officials also give reference to it.
And along with this the
British say that even if we give it, then to
whom should we give it?  Iran, Afghanistan,
Pakistan, India, so many countries are claiming
Koinoor.  Everyone is saying that
Koinoor is our heritage.  So who has the real ownership
?  This too is not easy to find out.
So these are all the problems due to which
Kohinoor could not be brought back.  But the demand of the general public
even today is that Kohinoor
is a part of India's heritage and the
government should bring it back somehow.
And along with this, its
superstition due to misfortune is
still talked about by people.  Still you will
find multiple writers who talk about its curses.
When Queen Elizabeth died on 8th of September 2022
and
after that King Charles, who was
a male, became the king.  So after that, in 204,
he was diagnosed with cancer.  So again the
stories about the curse of Kohinoor and black magic
started because even though the king did
not keep Kohinoor with himself but
after the death of Elizabeth technically the
ownership of Kohinoor had come to him.  One had
come by mail.  That is why all this happened and
people always give the example that
before Kohinoor came to England,
Asia, Africa,
Europe, America, Australia all came under the British Empire.
People used to say that the
sun never sets in the British Empire.  But if you look at today's date,
Britain has become a small
island nation and there are still multiple
writers who write that this has
happened because of the curse of Conur.  Now look,
in the end let me tell you once again that
you can simplify your accounting
with Udu Accounting App for free.  I have
given the link in the description.  Thank you.
[music]