welcome to
hard talk i'm stephen sack thanks to the
internet and this
the mobile phone our ability to inform
communicate and persuade has never been
greater and yet
public debate seems more toxic more
divisive than ever before so what's
happening are
intolerance and extremism winning out
over
reasoned debate well my guest today is
the american
neuroscientist philosopher and podcaster
sam harris he goes into intellectual
territory where few others
dare tread on race and religion he
generates
lots of heat what about light
sam harris in california welcome to hard
talk
happy to be here thanks stephen sam you
have an extraordinarily popular
podcast in which you talk with
leading intellectuals across the world
but you
also express your own trenchant opinions
in a host of books that you've written
which is more important more meaningful
to you
the conversation or expressing your
strong
opinion uh good question i think i
kind of split the difference there
because as i as you know i don't do
much in the way of standard interviews
i'm really i'm really trying to have a
conversation
every time i do a podcast so i take up
probably 40 percent of
the bandwidth in any in any interview so
it really is it's you know i get to hear
myself talk to my heart's content
and perhaps to the exasperation of
certain guests when you choose guests
for the making sense podcast which is
listened to by millions of people across
the world
do you like to bring people in with whom
you
know you disagree and disagree really
quite profoundly
occasionally yeah i mean you know a
little of that
goes a long way i mean depending on how
profound
the disagreements are but uh
i you know i think what's important is
to be able to talk about
substantial issues and significant
differences of opinion
in a way that's civil and that converges
on some kind of
solution i mean i think the only tool we
have for making
intellectual and moral progress is
conversation and it's persuasion if we
can't persuade one another
based on argument and evidence we really
i mean in the end we have no appeal but
to force you know or force of numbers or
you know i mean it's just
it really you know we shed the the
veneer of
of civilization pretty quickly and so i
i really do
view conversation as a kind of sacred
tool i'm just wondering why you have
such faith in conversation and dialogue
when it seems to me we live in an era of
digital communication where where
frankly
exchange of views and information is
easier than ever before and
everybody can put their opinion out
there on a platform and yet
far from easing uh humanity's ability to
get along
it seems to be polarizing dividing and
creating an ever
more toxic environment so your faith in
conversation may be misplaced
yeah we i didn't say i was an optimist
uh
i'm not i mean i just think i see no
alternative right i think it's the only
literally the only tool we have
uh i mean there's there is simply no
other way to influence the
the thoughts and opinions and behaviors
and intentions
of other human beings and so yeah but i
you know i'm quite worried that we have
created a
a kind of psychological experiment you
know that we've run
on all of humanity or most of humanity
all at once without anyone's consent
wherein we've created these a
circumstance where people can
be successfully isolated with respect to
to certain kinds of dogmas they can
pursue
any crazy idea to their hearts content
you know for
year after year and find support for it
online the internet is having this dual
function of
allowing us to get access to really the
totality of human knowledge
instantaneously but it's also allowing
our our sense-making to shatter
and and our epistemology to allow for a
kind of balkanization
of thought i want to turn to perhaps one
of the most
contentious debates frankly tearing
america apart right now that is
race and racism and how to
respond to what many people appears to
be the clear evidence
of discrimination at every level in
american society including
policing and the justice system you have
spoken out against
black lives matter you seem to regard it
as a
form of identity politics which you say
is a poison a poison in america today
why do you say that
well first let me say that i i
acknowledge that racism is still a
a tremendous problem in certain parts of
american society and you know globally
uh and that racism is is something that
we
absolutely have to oppose and
and criticize and i mean you know it is
a problem for which there is a remedy
and we have been
you know pursuing this remedy for for
many many decades
in the u.s but we've made a lot of
progress right and we're now living at a
moment
where we are having a kind of uh
moral panic advertised to us and and
black lives matter is one of the the
names of this movement and one of the
you know the the groups
you know it's a very loose group but
it's one of the groups that is
is um uh
making the most noise on this topic at
the moment and it it's as though we have
made no progress it's as though
this moment in american history
exemplifies the worst
uh symptoms of racism and uh
that's quite delusional i mean obviously
we've made a tremendous amount of
progress obviously this is one of the
least racist moments
in human history uh generally globally
and in in american history and um
but but but may i stop you yeah just to
point out that
the obvious that you sit with me we're
both
you know let's be honest white uh
middle-class
comfortable educated people who
represent
perhaps the the dominant uh grouping
in our respective societies and and who
are you
in the end to tell black americans
how they should feel right now because
so many of them look around the reality
of their own
lives their children's lives and see a
system which is systemically
racist not least when it comes to the
police and they feel
it is their right and their duty to
express
a level of anger frustration
and an unwillingness to accept that
which is surely understandable
well it's in part understandable but
what is really understandable is that
there's a lot of misinformation and
misunderstanding being amplified so so
if you're going to be
outraged over the
uh racist behavior of racist cops
or the racist consequences of systems
that that promulgate racism whether
there's any actual living racists around
to
to uh implement those systems uh well
it's not a choice is it we we are we are
surely duty bound to be no of course
right
i'm as concerned and as outraged as as
anyone
is about those things but i'm doubly
or additionally concerned that we not
find racists where they don't exist
right that would if you're going to find
racists everywhere you're you're going
to find the real racists
nowhere right i mean you're and you're
going to do an immense immense harm
uh in the process and so
to take you know the variable of police
violence it's very important if you're
going to worry about
uh the consequences of racism and the
way it's causing
black men preferentially to get shot and
killed
in america you have to find out whether
in fact that's happening
right whether in fact black men are
being shot
in greater numbers right in proportion
to uh
the numbers of encounters they have with
police officers and whether they're
whether they're if they're having more
encounters with police officers per
capita
there's any explanation for that other
than racism
right my concern currently in america is
that
any disparity you find whether it's with
respect to police violence or
employment or wealth or any any variable
of interest
and of great social importance currently
on the left
anywhere you go left of center
politically the only explanation that is
acceptable and this really does have the
the kind of the quality of a kind of
blasphemy test in a religion
the only explanation that is that is
acceptable this moment
is white racism or or systemic racism
now on the point of police violence it
just so happens
that the only data we have suggests
that while while african americans
have more encounters with the police uh
and there's there you know i think there
are obvious reasons for that
and they're actually in fact roughed up
by the police
more than than white americans are um
they're not killed more in fact they're
killed less than
than white americans are per encounter
which is to say that if you come under
the attention
of the police in america and uh they
draw their guns on you
uh your chances of being shot appear to
be slightly higher if you're white
at the moment but hang on it breaks
everyone's expectations this is
fascinating because it gets to the heart
of
your intellectual approach to lots of
things you know you are
i think a self-proclaimed rationalist
you say that you are
determined to be driven by the evidence
by data by the science not by
emotion and still less by things like
religion or any other faith-based
knowledge uh
belief system so so evidence matters but
if you look across the piece it's
you've relighted on one piece of
evidence but surely there's an
overwhelming tract of evidence about
incarceration rates what happens to
black kids in schools
what happens to black people in
employment how many jobless black people
there are
there is clearly a story in america
of systemic discrimination which black
people are saying
right now they will no longer tolerate
without expressing
their anger and when you make the point
you've just made it it does sound to
some like you're you're sort of lacking
a level of
compassion or even emotional
intelligence or ability to empathize
with the situation
of the other well well no the
first of all it shouldn't because i'm
concerned about the real suffering of
real people but the
we have to acknowledge that we compound
that suffering
when we give false notions
about its actual causes right so if
you're going to look at
and again and and i'm you know i'm on
record every time i touch this topic
acknowledging that uh we still need
criminal justice reform and the war on
drugs
in the united states in particular has
been a disaster and it's especially been
a disaster for the black community
all of those things uh should go without
saying and and there are changes that
need to be made there
but if you're going to again if you're
going to to ascribe
the status quo across the board the fact
that
that um uh there's the kind of wealth
inequality and equal inequality with
respect to
crime and violence in american society
that breaks along racial lines
if you're going to ascribe that to white
racism
or or white racist or policies that
white
that white people are not changing
because they advantage them right
you will continually stumble upon
errors of great consequence right it's
simply not the case
that there are white racists
with their racism producing the level of
violence we see in the black community
in the inner city in a place like
chicago the point that many black
americans are making right now and i'm
going to quote to you
the words of just ones his sincere
carabao who works as the social justice
coordinator at the american humanist
association he's addressed
your uh podcasts on this issue your
interviews with other people on this
issue and he says
sam harris's definition of racism places
an underlying emphasis on intention and
he says
that's how sam harris defines the number
of white people who are racist as a tiny
tiny minority however
says mr carabo when discussing racism
it is important to remember it isn't
about intent
it's about impact and in that sense it
involves
a far greater proportion of the white
community
well as stated i wouldn't necessarily
disagree with that intention isn't the
only thing that matters obviously if
there are
policies that in effect create racist
outcomes
whether anyone intends it or not we
should figure out what those policies
are and we should change them right so
that's
you know that is what people tend to
mean by systemic race to racism or
institutional racism
and i'm i'm completely on board with the
project of
discovering that and correcting for it
right but what
we have now in american society are
allegations of racism or
or uh the experience that people are
having millions of people are having
simultaneously of watching a video of
let's say a police shooting you know you
know in the
prototypical case it'll be a you know
white cop shooting
we don't have to imagine it sam we we
see it right now we're watching over and
over
jacob blake being shot in wisconsin you
know we don't have to use our
imagination
i would tell you that that that that
video
is not evidence in and of itself that
video is not evidence of racism right
you can be you can see videos of white
people being shot in precisely the same
circumstances
and um i mean we have a massive problem
of guns in our society
we have a massive problem of poorly
trained cops i mean that that video in
particular
against several of these problems one is
that that when someone
rushes to their car uh in defiance of
police commands and opens the door and
reaches in
in american society unlike in the uk it
is only rational
for the cops to assume that that person
is retrieving a gun
so he can turn around and start shooting
cops in the face which
which happens right and every cop knows
this to move on from race to
religion you're very well known for
having written a book end of faith that
espoused your belief that religion was
essentially preposterous but
amongst your believe views on religion
is a clear feeling that
islam is a more malign a more dangerous
set of beliefs than many other religions
and i just want to quote you something
you said
actually a number of years ago almost 14
years ago where you talked about
muslims in europe and you said muslim
immigrants show little
inclination to acquire the secular and
civil values of host countries
they exploit the values of those
countries to the utmost they demand
tolerance for their backwardness
misogyny their anti-semitism and their
genocidal hatred
preached in their mosques i i just
wonder again
if you're looking for calm considered
rational conversation
do you think your own words there are
helping
yeah well as you acknowledge that had
the kind of topspin one one
wrote with in the immediate aftermath of
september 11th right i mean this is this
is
my conversation my style of conversation
about islam has moved on from there i
wrote a book with
majid nawaz a fellow brit who used to be
a muslim extremist who is now
as rational and secular a person as you
could ever hope to find and we had a
kind of
debate uh that that that um
uh converged on a on a really a happy
conversation and a friendship
that became this book islam and the
future of tolerance so people can
get my my most recent framing of the
issues there
but you know i mean to your to your
fundamental point yes it is taboo
to say wherever you happen to stand in
culture whether you're secular or
whether you're religious
that religions are different with
respect to almost any variable we
we care about where they you know they
they claim different things
they emphasize different things uh there
are different points in
in in their history and their engagement
with modernity
and yes islam is it's not an accident
that jihadism
is a phenomenon in islam and it's not a
phenomenon in anglicanism or mormonism
or scientology i mean these i want to
know in the real world what this means
for you sam does that mean that when
donald trump
uh back in 2017 imposed that travel ban
which
was quite clearly aimed at muslims and
he listed i think it was seven
muslim majority countries which for
security reasons he said could no longer
travel to the united states
were you cheering him on on my on my
behalf my point is that you characterize
muslim immigrants
as a group of people within which there
will be a small minority you say
who are statistically going to be
jihadists which is precisely what donald
trump would say
yeah okay but the so yes hence the need
to vet
immigrants and refugees and have you
know honest conversations about
what we're looking for we're looking for
people who believe
specific things about martyrdom and
apostasy and blasphemy and the rights of
women and whether it makes
moral sense to hurl homosexuals off of
rooftops right and
people who are recruiting for isis are
happy to join isis or people who in your
own country will
drop out of medical school for the
pleasure of of going to to live in syria
so they might be able to martyr
themselves for isis right this is a
phenomenon of contagious ideas that we
have to speak honestly about
and it's not it's only happening in one
religion now
in addition to i mean the reasons why i
didn't agree with with
donald trump's travel ban is that one it
was completely incoherent because it was
not even targeting the countries that
posed the greatest
ideological risk at that point or that
were the the worst reservoirs of this
kind of jihadism
but two i i you know i have long said
that the most
valuable people on earth with respect to
dealing with this problem people we
most want in our societies are
secular muslims and moderate muslims and
and people who can actually bridge the
gap between
the you know the the non-muslim
community and the secular community
and the religious extremists who are who
are
albeit a minority but still a problem
within the muslim community so we need
people like majid nawaz and ayan hirsi
ali and
and you know dozens of other secularists
and
and moderates uh and apostates who i've
supported
and we need them to figure out how to
midwife this
this uh renaissance and within
the muslim community where in something
like enlightenment values take hold in
the widest possible way
uh it's obvious that i'm not going to
accomplish that it
requires somebody who's in the community
to do that generally people i think
associate you particularly with a a a
very strong brand of
atheism and there was that famous time
you debated with chris hitchens and
richard dawkins and you
you all of you said you know religion
is extremely corrosive and damaging
somebody then asked about spirituality
and while the others didn't really bite
you said actually no there is room
for spirituality in my life and i'm just
wondering
what that means for you ultimately
despite everything you say about
science and evidence and rationality
do you believe in some sort of higher
power
some non-human force at work well it's
not a matter of believing in a higher
power it's a matter of
experiencing the fact that that
consciousness
is intrinsically mysterious and it's
it's the context in which
all of our most wonderful
experiences appear right and it's always
the context of all of our suffering
and the mechanics of that is something
we can understand more and more
and and uh change our lives for the
better but it's also the context in
which
um human life can get better and better
and i think some some classically
spiritual values like
self-transcendence and unconditional
love right
are at the core of any movement in the
direction of of greater and greater
human well-being and should be at the
core of any
ethics we use to talk about those
possibilities so yeah i mean so
i have no doubt that it's possible to
become something like
the historical person of jesus whoever
that was or buddha or any of these great
patriarchs and matriarchs of our
religion so there's a baby in the
bathwater there that i think we don't
want to throw out
as atheists but the question is do you
ever have to believe anything
irrational in order to explore those
possibilities in yourself or in
in society and i think the answer to
that is quite clearly no i'm just
remembering
close to the beginning of this interview
you gave a hollow laugh and said i'm not
telling you i'm an optimist so
when you tell me that you do believe in
transcendence and you believe
uh that we can all turn ourselves into
better
beings by looking within and pursuing
love and all of that we're not doing it
are we i mean that is just as we look
around the world and around our
societies right now that is not
happening
uh well we're not doing it well i would
certainly agree yeah i mean many of us
are trying
and that's all we can do is is try both
personally
and i think most importantly
protect norms that allow us to
live by our deeper wisdom even when we
are
personally liable to fail right so we
want laws and tax codes
and norms of discourse that that anchor
us to our better selves or our better
possible
selves or make it easier for even
mediocre and conflicted people to behave
better and better right and what we have
rather often
are systems of incentives that are set
up
to make even very ethical people you
know
behave unethically right or even fairly
honest people
to behave dishonestly and to just anchor
back to the the
beginning of our conversation what i'm
most worried about in our style of
discourse
around these charged issues like race is
that it is causing
even fairly scrupulous and honest people
and well-intentioned people
to be dishonest and sloppy and actually
um practice a kind of of
politics of personal destruction uh
where
they never and effectively to behave
like psychopaths
you know on social media and in print
and and in
various journalistic encounters um
where they never would do this if if the
incentives weren't aligned that way
right so i i would like to change our
incentives around
conversations of the sort we we have
today
um and uh we yeah but we have a lot of
work to do
to do that i would agree with that and
sam harris in the spirit of
a strong belief in conversation i thank
you for being on hard talk thanks very
much yeah
pleasure thanks steven
[Music]
you