welcome to
hard talk i'm stephen sacker what is the
point of the world's
nuclear watchdog the international
atomic energy agency
its task is to ensure that countries
intent on developing nuclear power
do not use their programs as cover for
development of weapons of mass
destruction
but is it mission impossible well my
guest is the
relatively new iaea chief
raphael grossi from the continued bitter
arguments over iran
to north korea and saudi arabia is the
iaea another example
of a global agency undermined by
geopolitical division
[Music]
rafael grossi in vienna welcome to hard
talk
hello good to be with you it's great to
have you on the show let me begin with a
question that arises from
your relatively recent appointment how
important is it that you are
seen to be in the pocket of
no nation that you are seen to be
entirely independent
well i think that's essential and i
suppose
it comes with any prominent
international position
countries have their own agendas their
own interests
and they want to make sure that the ones
leading these institutions like the iaea
are truly independent in my case in our
case is even more so
because unlike other international
organizations
we are inspectors we are the nuclear
watchdog yeah
you absolutely are so i just wonder if
it was helpful to you when it emerged
that the united states had done a little
bit of lobbying on your behalf in the
runoff uh electoral election process
uh which the iaea conducted and you got
the job
against a romanian candidate the ua was
clearly lobby
the us rather was clearly lobbying on
your behalf was that counterproductive
damaging for you
no not at all and i would say it wasn't
only the u.s
it was many other countries i got a very
nice
two-thirds of the vote even more than
that
so it wasn't only the united states
it was 24 countries out of 35 so it was
a very nice ample win
but you need uh obviously the the
finances the hundreds of millions of
dollars a year to run your budget and
i guess it was very good news for you
when it became clear the us
was going to continue its full funding
of the iaea we've seen it cut funding
and indeed withdraw from other agencies
like the who so you need to stay on side
with the americans don't you
you need to stay on site with everybody
and let me tell you something you know
in terms of the uh of the funding
the issue of funding international
organizations has been a subject of
dispute not only now there have been
waves
where times moments where countries were
reassessing how they dealt with with
different international organizations in
the case of the iaea because of its
indispensable
role that it plays we have always had
a lot of support not only from the
united states many other countries
440 nuclear reactors
a lot of nuclear material out there and
somebody has to check
that this nuclear material as you said
in your introduction
is does not go in the wrong direction
the reason i'm asking all these
questions about your independence your
relationship with the united states is
that it was very notable
in early in the new year this year when
you took over
uh it did seem there was a ratcheting up
of the
pressure on tehran and the determination
to use information that had been leaked
it seems from israeli sources
to suggest to the iranians that if they
didn't become
much much more transparent about what
was going on in some of their facilities
and plans
you were going to get very tough with
them would you say that you brought a
new attitude to the leadership of the
iaea when it came to iran
i did bring a new attitude in general
but i would say
when it comes to to this uh one has to
bear in mind that as
as the beatles would say the iran issue
is a long and winding road
we've been we've known ups and downs
and it's a story that goes at least
20 years back uh in its present
configuration
so it's normal that we had uh bad
moments where there were moments there
were there
disagreements and actually this year we
went through a
difficult patch so to speak and i was in
tehran a couple of weeks ago
and was able to to solve these issues so
i would say there are moments different
snapshots
at the moment we are working well well
you refer to this trip
to iran that you undertook in august i'm
absolutely fascinated by this trip
because
as you say before the trip there was a
degree of tension in your relationship
with the iranian government but
after you issued a joint statement in
tehran
it seems there was a an outbreak of
goodwill on all sides and
if i'm not wrong you now say that you
believe the iranians are acting
in good faith with all of your
inspection programs
have i got that right let me let me say
i
i suppose you yeah you get it right in
general
i think the the non-proliferation effort
is a constant effort
you're never there you have to always
check
and you always prove that everything is
okay trust but verify as they said
so what what happened this year is that
i asked iran to let
us let our inspectors access a couple of
places
they didn't want to so that led us to an
impasse
or of sorts which wasn't
solved and i think people were concerned
that this would add up to other
conflictual situations and debates
around
iran therefore you know
it was important to solve this issue i
thought it was important to talk to them
directly
they were kind enough in receiving us i
i spoke to president rouhani to the
foreign minister
zarif and others there and and and
we were able together to come to an
agreement yeah well that thank
to say so uh mr grocery the iranians
seem thrilled by it afterwards president
rouhani said that his relations with you
and the iaea were quote
very good so i just want to get to the
heart of what you achieved because there
was a lot of discussion about this
so-called abadi nuclear weapons
development
site now revelations about this site had
emerged
after the israeli intelligence services
got hold of
a whole bunch of secret iranian files
and documents
yeah i want to be clear about this did
your since your meeting with rouhani
have your people
been to this abadi site
our people have been able to
re-establish
their inspection activities
one place we we visit i don't get into
the specifics of the place because
this is a confidential information but
we were able to go to one
and we are going to a second one uh in a
few days but let me say that
in terms of what what we achieved it was
important
but it it's it's not the end of the
story uh and i would like to
in order not to aggrandize what we what
we achieved what we achieved was to go
back to
the normal activity that we should have
we were able it was as if the you know
the power had been cut
and now the lights are on again and we
can see
so this is going to be it's not like we
were
in hell now before and now we're in
paradise
we are working again let me put it like
this yeah but i'm i'm going to push you
on the detail because the detail is very
important
number one it seems clear that you have
been operating from information
provided to you by the israelis can you
confirm that yes
or no no i cannot confirm
because of the following we have lots of
information we have
information that we gather from our
own inspectors we have information that
countries give us and we have con we
have information that comes from
third parties from other other actors
because it's important we never act on
the basis of information that we
that we receive we take at face value
and then we go and do stuff yeah
we have a a a a a team
a very large team of experts
in different technologies and areas we
go through the information
we shift it we analyze it we cross it
with
previous information we had and only
when we believe
that something is worthy of further
probing or questioning and this was the
case
uh with with iran on this on this matter
we do it right we have tons of other
information
on which we do not act well you you are
a veteran argentine diplomat and you're
proving to be a skilled diplomat in this
interview but the truth is you did get
significant information
yeah well you did get significant
information from israel you clearly
factored that into your overall
assessment you won't tell me whether
abadi was one of the sites you went to
but it's cl
pretty clear it was if i'm honest with
you i just want you to tell me
simply are you now getting a level of
cooperation
from iran that you have not seen before
since the jcpo the international
agreement
uh was signed back in 2015. is there now
a level of cooperation that you're
prepared to recognize
as different from tehran
i have the level of cooperation i need
now
as you said i'm relatively new so i
took over in december and already in
january
i had i had a problem so i had to solve
it
now i have a level of cooperation that
allow our inspectors
to work and we are going to see what we
see
see the big picture here is confusing
and it gets confusing because of the
deep geopolitical divisions over iran
because
the u.s and israel have yeah the us and
israel have one perspective on what's
going on and other countries
have a very different perspective so you
and you've told me about your
independence you can perhaps
clear up some of these questions for me
so
is iran in your view closer
or further from developing a nuclear
weapon today than it was at the
beginning of the trump administration
in january 2017
the question does not lend itself to a
yes or no and i explain
why not you have different metrics
stephen you have different metrics if
your metric is
how much nuclear material in this case
enriched uranium they have you may
draw the conclusion that they have
now more material than they had
not at the beginning of the trump's
administration but when
this administration decided to leave the
agreement which was only in march
2018. since then iran by way of
retaliation
decided on its side to start degrading
its observance and then that meant
that they started to enrich more but
again to complicate things further if
you compare that with the amounts they
had when the jcpoa
which is the acronym as you know for
this agreement was signed they have
considerably less so sometimes
this metrics can confound and confuse
people
what i can tell you is that we are
there to um prove and
to uh check that
iran does not get a nuclear weapon
you as i understand what you've said to
me and your wider reporting are saying
that iran
now has up to 10 times the amount of
enriched uranium that we're supposed to
be permitted underneath
not quite not quite not quite not quite
ten times
a little bit less but let's let's not
let's not fall out over
eight or nine or ten times the fact is
it has an awful lot more
enriched uranium than it's supposed to
have and you're grinning about it but
i'll tell you who's not grinning the
israelis aren't grinning
the donald trump administration is not
grinning and they say that as a result
of this
it is imperative that the european
powers
pull out of what remains of the jcpo
that international agreement
and follow with the us and impose
new tough sanctions on iran now you sit
in vienna at the iaea
you presumably have to take some sort of
a view on this who's right who's wrong
we are not a party to this treaty you
have to
understand we are not a party to this
arrangement agreement or pact
that is why i'm so interested in your
answer because you don't have a dog in
this fight but you can tell me whether
the euro exactly
this is why we verify this is why we
verify
and when they don't allow us to do our
job
we say it out loud and we demand
the access that is needed to prevent the
situation to degrade itself
into a point of no return
but my question still remains when you
hear this debate about whether what the
iranians have done in the last couple of
years represents
action and activity which must lead to
the wider international community
following the us
and reimposing tough sanctions your view
your opinion is what
our opinion is indispensable because we
tell the world
what's going on substantively what is
your opinion do you think given what you
see in iran
that the only way of addressing this
acquisition of enriched uranium
what the iranians are doing the only way
to address it
is to declare the jcpoa dead
and re-impose wider tough international
sanctions that's not up for me to say
frankly speaking and and i go back to
your
first comments i am
must be it's an essential quality that i
must
preserve i must be neutral
as i said to the iranians and to the
world when i came to this position
i will be firm with them but fair
so i cannot start taking political sides
and saying jcpoa is good or bad
sanctions yes or no we provide
with the neutral technical assessment
that allows
eventually those world powers that you
are mentioning
to come to the right decision yeah but
you know what mr grossly this is
fascinating because it gets to the heart
of whether
multilateral uh institutions such as
yours can actually function
in the 21st century world because on the
one hand the americans are now saying
that what is
what the iranians are doing is
outrageous and that anybody who
still backs the international agreement
and doesn't impose sanctions
is to quote the state secretary of state
mike pompeo
choosing to side with the ayatollahs
that's the american position
and on the other hand you've got the
chinese and the russians
who are saying absolutely no way we
won't
countenance the reimposition of
sanctions and if the iaea
dares to suggest that there are problems
with iran that
suggest the americans are right then
they will withdraw their support from
you
so you're caught in the middle you're in
a desperate squeeze
i'm caught between a rock and a hard
dress but this comes with my job
and what we need to do is to continue to
provide
the exact the exact snapshot of
what is going on and this is the
foundation
of any any decision people will know the
international community will know
when they are not observing uh their uh
commitments
or when they are not allowing the iaea
to work and to operate then there are
political persuasions
and opinions you have the the democrats
you have the republicans you have the
europeans
everybody comes to me and say what they
want my job is to be
the nuclear watchdog not more but not
less but the problem is
all sides are tempted to undermine your
credibility
and therefore frankly nobody can always
happen of course
that will always happen you know
sometimes you
let's take this here and this year is
very nice because it provides you
with a scientific example of what
happens
in the beginning of the year when i was
not getting the access
to to these locations and i was
reporting to
to the iaea what was going on i was
being described as a sheriff
and many other things so i was i was
tough
now i have an agreement and you yourself
are telling me rouhani is saying that
you have the best relation that could
ever be so you know i'm i
am i'm used to this i think it's it's
only
normal and in a way in a paradoxical way
it's a good indication that we are doing
just what we need to do
all right let's move on from iran
because you've got other big problems in
your entry
let's talk very briefly north korea now
you don't have people in north korea
they were kicked out
quite a few years ago that's a shame yes
well
but donald trump has pursued this
diplomatic process with the north
koreans apparently believing
that ultimately it can lead to the
denuclearization
in weapons terms of north korea
do you believe that because many people
think that's pie in the sky
well you know with north korea we've
known
before as as with with iran it's a long
process
we we had successes we had failures we
i mean the iaea the international
community the inspectors we were kicked
out of
from from the dprk back in 2009
cop figure 11 years without
an international presence there we have
some idea of what is going on
what is clear is that we will only be
able to return there and start
inspecting
once some form of a political
understanding is there there were some
in the past
which failed and the the latest
is the one that the united states and
north korea bilaterally have been trying
to attempt
for what i know uh from from secretary
pompeo
and the u.s government this is a process
that continues
i'm hopeful i i believe that it has to
succeed
and when it does we'll be ready to go
back and to go back
to a more different uh and more
complicated
i would say dprk because we're asking
but just just to be productivity was
quite limited
now they are a nuclear power station
well they most certainly are and just to
be very clear
very brief answer on this your satellite
imaging and everything else you do
from outside of the country suggest to
you that they are still
determinedly pursuing their
weapons program trying to develop more
sophisticated weapons miniaturize them
everything else
yes right well thanks for that now very
quickly one other
specific country saudi arabia how
worried are you by the saudi investment
in
enlarging their nuclear program and now
seeking out and using the help of
china in a very big way is that worrying
you because some people think that could
be
very alarming well yeah there's been
some
speculation in the press the reality is
and yet again
we tell things as they are and not on
the basis of speculation
the reality is that the kingdom of saudi
arabia has very
limited nuclear activity very limited
they have some research activities they
have now
bought a low power research reactor
which is very small they don't even have
it yet
and there have been and i suppose you uh
are referring to that there have been
some
uh press uh um articles
uh indicating that they they might have
some uh cooperation with other countries
on uh
on uranium mining we don't have any any
any concrete indication of that we are
in conversation
with saudi arabia to make sure that when
they
upgrade their nuclear program which is
as i said embryonic
we will be ramping up our safeguards
activities there so i'm not particularly
worried but i'm following actively
interesting
a final thought your bigger one of your
big ideas when you took over the iaea
seems to me to have been to stress to
the world that you want to see much
more uh expansion and development of
civil nuclear power because you think
it's part of the
decarbonization climate change solution
well you say it is so confidently but
how can you say that when
all of the stuff we've discussed today
suggests that there is such a very
difficult grey area where countries
expand their nuclear programs and they
they
run not only does the world run the risk
of hang on just
not only is it probably a danger to
nuclear proliferation in the long run
but it's also
a safety issue because we all know what
happened at fukushima
it's also a cost issue because nuclear
is extraordinarily expensive in capital
terms
and here you are telling the world that
we have to ramp up
civil nuclear production no no no no all
i'm saying all
i'm saying is that nuclear has a place
at the table
it is clear that for many countries 31
of them
including the united kingdom and many
others have in their mix
nuclear power and it is clear that we
have a
huge challenge in terms of climate
change
so to say that a source of energy which
is
basically clean which is saving us from
two gigatons per year
of uh emissions does not have a place
in the successful mix to
decarbonize the economy is simply
technically incorrect then countries can
decide whether they go for it or not
and the iaea is there to make sure
that this nuclear material which is used
to generate electricity
to cure people for the benefit of of the
many
is going to be done in the right in the
right way
all right raphael grossi it's been
fascinating talking to you thank you
very much for joining me on hard talk
thank you very much it's been a pleasure
[Music]
you