[Music]
welcome to
hard talk i'm stephen sacker the daily
street protest
demanding the resignation of belarus's
authoritarian president alexander
lukashenko
haven't yet tipped the balance against
his regime
lukashenka is still there the security
forces are still
doing his bidding so how is the
geopolitics of this
going to play out well my guest is
katanas nausea the president of
neighboring
lithuania will moscow's will
prevail in belarus or will people power
take the country in a new direction
[Music]
president guitarist in vilnius
welcome to hard talk
good evening mr president how do you
see the power dynamic in belarus
right now do you think president
lukashenka
has ridden out the storm yes of course
alexander lukashenko tries to buy the
time and tries to suppress
the protests of peaceful people
in the streets right now the people are
fighting for
their fundamental rights to have free
elections
to express the opinion about what is
going on in belarus
and unfortunately we see a lot of
violations
and discontinues and it brings very huge
concern
to all of us not only for neighboring
countries
lithuania latvia and estonia poland
ukraine
but also for european union
this is the reason why we started to
react very fast
and we proposed the plan of
de-escalation of situation
we consolidated our efforts together
with
presidents of uh surrounding countries
uh unfortunately alexander lukashenko
was
not ready to take this initiative
and he turned to roberts vladimir putin
probably this is the reason why the
situation
in last days and last weeks the theory
is deteriorating and we see
again the violations we see
just detained people disappearing people
and we see very selective and targeted
attacks against the
people or persons which are in national
coordination committee
so the situation is not home and it's
not
yeah the situation is certainly not calm
mr president
you just referred to alexander
lukashenko
as the president of belarus i want to be
very clear about this do you still
recognize his legitimacy as the head of
state or are you now
of the view that he has no legitimacy
because
as you said recently there was no
free fair election in belarus so is he
legitimate or not
i am talking about alexandre lukashenko
as person and of course we cannot
uh talk about the elections which took
place on august 9th as
fair and free elections so the result is
not legitimate and alexander lukashenko
is not legitimate president of this
country
but of course nobody can neglect and to
reject that
alexander lukashenko still has certain
power
and this power he is using unfortunately
in very bad direction and then we can uh
not agree on this you are the the
neighbor
of belarus you are where most of the
belarusian senior opposition figures who
have been forced out of belarus have
gathered not least svetlana ticonovskaya
who was of course the
candidate who ran against lukashenka and
she claims
she won that election had it not been
rigged so are you
saying that miss tikanovskaya is
actually the winner of that election and
are you recognizing her as the de facto
uh leader of belarus in exile
we can call here as the factor leader
but the problem is that the elections of
uh august 9th they're spoiled
and we cannot prove it by giving the
figures giving the result
and nobody can say what votes are
the votes indeed and what votes are the
fake votes
because the appearance rate in some
districts of belarus
during this election was more than one
hundred percent
so this is a problem to say what was the
real result
we can guess that uh madame zikanovskaya
was the winner of those elections we
treat here as a
national leader and she is
the leader of opposition movement right
now
she is in lithuania for the moment and
she is safe and safe together with
her family right so you are offering her
protection but i just wonder how
helpless how frustrated do you feel
right now mr president you
as you've said you've spoken out very
loud
against lukashenko for weeks now
but even today as we speak to each other
the belarusian paramilitary forces
are still continuing to repress the
protesters they are picking up
senior opposition figures on the streets
they picked up
another one a very short time ago maxime
znack that forum follows the
detention of maria colis kolesnikova
you know this is continuing your voice
makes no difference
uh so this is the reason why we need
actions
yes rhetoric is good but rhetoric even
strong rhetoric is not enough
we need actions and free baltic states
took the initiative and showed this
example
how to deal with lukashenko and
initiated the national sanctions lists
we have 30 persons in each of this list
including alexander lukashenko i
i am stressing that it's extremely
important
that other regions and countries
european union as a whole united states
united kingdom canada should
apply the same sanctions to the
belarusian regime
and yes we had the european council some
time ago
i was very satisfied with the with the
result of this council because there
were
strong commitments strong judgment of
the situation
all leaders spoken
about a very clear vision what to do
with
belarus but unfortunately so far we do
not see
the list of european union and according
to some
drafts i can say that there are 17
persons included
and lukashenko excluded from this list
so this is very this is mr president
let me stop you there this is very
important people around the world need
to hear what you think is going on
you're saying that as you understand it
the eu's
list of potential targets for new
sanctions in belarus
the individuals do not include
lukashenko himself now you baltic states
have already imposed
your targeted sanctions on a list of
individuals including lukashenko
so why do you think the european union
as a whole
is not following your lead
the logic behind is to leave
some room for possible mediation in the
future
we leave the door or the window open
for possible negotiations with alexander
lukashenko
of course including the representatives
of civil society
but i really have my doubts
that this is still possible we
see that this certain breaking point and
this breaking point is the contacts
of alexander lukashenko with the russian
president vladimir putin
and we see that lukashenko is just not
ready to have any mediation
especially from the side of european
union
and what is extremely important the
mediation
includes the representatives of civil
society if there are no representatives
of civil society
what mediation is it mediation between
lukashenko and putin we are not we are
talking not about this mediation we are
talking about
the mediation which includes every party
and this is not the case and i have very
big doubts that it will happen in the
future
because of unfortunately
a limited readiness of alexander
lukashenko to go this way let me be
blunt with you
why do you think the big powers in the
european union including france and
germany are not prepared
to go as far and condemn lukashenko
in the same language that you use
why you know we
are very close to belarus nation
not only in geographic sense but also in
emotional sense
we feel the pain of those people in the
streets of minsk and
other cities and other villages in
belarus
we see how they are suffering
we hear the stories about
violations about the tortures
and just we emotionally are very close
to them
maybe this is not the case if we are
talking
if we are talking about the countries
which are
really distant from from from uh belarus
but nevertheless it's extremely
important to find this common
denominator in european union and
sometimes it's
it's pretty hard to find this solution
even if they find the solution at the
political level
do you think and you just use the word
torture about what is going on with the
paramilitary forces
in belarus do you think
that right now alexander lukashenko is
guilty of crimes against humanity and do
you want to see him
prosecuted for what is happening right
now i'm mindful that your foreign
minister mr
linkovichus recently said that he
is seeing stalinist nk
nkvd methods being applied on the
streets of minsk
in 21st century europe if you are
serious about that then presumably you
want to see lukashenko in a courtroom
you know first of all we need clear
and detailed investigation
and this investigation is not possible
right now
if this investigation is over then we
can
name the persons who are guilty for
these violences
but you are totally right by saying that
it reminds us just soviet time
we see how they are targeting
targeting the people which are in
national coordination committee or
council
svetlana alexeyevich other members of
a coordination council i remember
the time about 40 50 years ago
and this time was in soviet union
rostropovich
solzhenitsyn they were
extradicted from the country and they
were
persecuted and we see the same story
here in belarus
so it shows that the people are
different
the new generations are coming but the
methods
of certain institutions remain the same
you're playing a dangerous game mr
president uh
vilnius where you sit today has been
described as
the second capital of the belarusian
opposition everything you've told me
today shows how determined you are
to speak out against lukashenko
and demand an end to his regime
you are going to be directly at odds
with moscow
and you know it and it is very possible
that you will suffer consequences as a
result of that
you know democratic values principal
values
does not have the price this is not cost
benefit analysis like in the economic
policy or
economic analysis this is the
principles fundamental values we
strongly believe in
we didn't forget our history
newest history of lithuania let me
remind you
30 years ago lithium declared the
independency
and it was a like dark
tunnel in our life and we had
hope that there will be light on the end
of this tunnel
and at that time small country
iceland far away from lithuania stepped
in and recognized our independency
and we didn't forget it we think that
now we must do the same the iceland
did 30 years ago but the danger is
you may be inadvertently assisting
vladimir putin he wants to portray what
is happening
in belarus's an exercise in meddling
from western interests the european
union
nato forces trying to move into
russia's sphere of influence and he says
that is illegitimate and dangerous
fought not just for minsk but for moscow
as well
by being so strident you may be
helping putin with his narrative
you know you can not push
anyone who is already hacked
by the beer so
i think this is a consequence of
economic policy
or economic model who
lukashenko implemented in the last 20
years and this
economic model was based on the cheap
energy resources coming from russia
cheap salaries or cheap labor force
and of course it's not sustainable the
russian economy is not competitive
and he it could be kept
above the water only with cheap energy
resources from russia what is now
going uh just we see height in deafness
adapt in depthness of belarus towards
russia about 50
of this debt belongs to russia and
we see economic trade ties very close
ties with russia
and of course in this situation luke
paschenko
loses its power and putin has
many instruments in many instruments
just to achieve his goal and his goal
is ultimate goal is to merge
both states into one body and
now he sees lukashenko
as very convenient partner who lost the
power
and he who is totally exposed to the
will
of vladimir putin
we should not blame the russian people
that
the situation is like this but what is
the end game here mr president you've
just said the russians want to see
belarus effectively merged with russia
by economic and political means and they
will use
whatever leverage they have over
lukashenka to achieve that in the next
few
weeks and months so what's the end game
if lukashenko looks like he
is going to be toppled do you believe
russia will intervene militarily
i think there is no need to intervene
militarily because they can use another
instruments
and probably they learn some lessons
from ukraine
so i think they will try to
intervene in much more subtle way
and much will depend on the
people of on the ordinary people which
are protesting in the streets and and we
have to help them
and european union and other powers
in the world should not stand
uh aside and just uh
expressing the rhetoric rhetoric is not
enough today
we need actions and we need actions as
quick as possible because
otherwise it will be too late i want to
ask you
a question based on a bigger picture
that is
whether you are worried right now that
the will
of the west and let's talk about both
the european union and nato
the will of the western powers to stand
up to vladimir putin
is not good enough not strong enough i'm
thinking for example
of the fairly muted reaction so far
to what the germans insist was the
poisoning
of alexi navalny on russian
territory i'm also thinking of the
american
decision earlier this summer to begin
withdrawing troops
from germany and president macron
recently saying that he fears nato
is brain dead do you fear that
the west is losing the will to confront
vladimir putin
i expect much more uh really i hope that
we have to find the real political will
to act
more much more decisively we do right
now
so this is a problem european union
was blamed many times that european
union reacts
to slow to late and too little so
let us to prove that the reality is
different
let us to take decisive measures
and i hope that it will happen nato as
an organization is
totally good for lithuania we think that
nato organization
the brain of nato is not dead
and we enjoy very good cooperation with
nato
on many levels on the level of
common military plans we have enhanced
forward presence in lithuania
several years in the row we
ourself we are very serious and
and responsible member of nato a lie of
the nato
spending two percent of gdp and we
expect
that other countries will do the same
will
increase the defense spending i don't
think that
the potential of nato is exhausted
i think that this is only one
organization
very effective organization of defense
and deterrence
mr president we're almost out of time i
want to raise one other issue
with you you've talked about your
discontent with the eu reaction to what
is happening in belarus but of course
the eu is preoccupied with other
challenges
not least uh ironing out all of the
problems connected with
brexit the british are due to end their
transition relationship with the eu at
the end
of this year and the hope is there will
be a trade agreement but right now that
looks very difficult not least because
the british government has just declared
that it is going to
pass legislation in the british
parliament
which ministers have explicitly said
will override elements of the withdrawal
agreement with the eu
and which will in fact violate
international law
now as a head of state of an eu member
how do you feel about what the british
government is currently doing
i feel not good and i regret the
decision
of united kingdom to leave european
union
but i respect this decision but now what
is going on to
renegotiate to correct the withdrawal
agreement
is just not acceptable
and this is really
pretty hard to talk about such things
because we have to respect what we
reached
during very long negotiation period with
big efforts of
maine negotiators and we achieved this
result
and it's just not appropriate to
reconsider this agreement right now and
a final thought all of the tough talk
right now from london from the boris
johnson government about how they
uh within weeks may well have to walk
away from
any effort to get a trade agreement and
accept that there will be no trade deal
with the eu
after december 31st of this year do you
see this
as just more political maneuvering and
bluffing
or do you take it seriously when boris
johnson says that britain
can regard no deal as a good outcome
is he being serious or not no deal is
not good outcome for
everybody for all countries for european
union
and for britain too so we are interested
and i'm talking not only about european
union but also about my country
we are interested to have the
process done and to have the united
kingdom as a good foreign trade partner
we are like-minded countries in
other fields too security defense policy
so let us cooperate in the future
and let us not undermine our good
cooperation until now all right well mr
president katanas naseeda i thank you
very much indeed for joining me from
vilnius
[Music]
so
you