This is a pencil. It's 7.7 mm
thick. This is the S25 Ultra. It's 8.2
mm
thick. And this this is the S25 Edge.
It's just 5.8 mm
thick. We got to talk about these ultra
thin foams.
Okay, so the obvious take is nobody
asked for this. Like these ultra thin
phones look cool or whatever. They make
for a snazzy commercial, but what we
really want is thicker phones that have
less camera bump but way more battery.
The universal thing that everyone wants
is more battery, not thinner phones.
Facts. This is true. And I I could just
end this video right here. But I
figured, what if we actually gave it a
shot? What if I actually daily drove a
phone whose biggest feature is how thin
it is? So, I did. Now, the thing that
won't shock you is that the rest of this
phone is very familiar. From the front,
it's literally a Galaxy S25 Plus. Same
size, 6.7 in display, 1440p, 120 Hz,
plenty bright, it's beautiful. It's got
this ultrasonic fingerprint reader,
still super fast. And then all of the
same software. So, it has the newly
updated 1 UI7 that I also just got on my
Ultra. and mostly like the vertically
scrolling app drawer is nice. Uh the new
extra swipes to get to quick settings is
kind of annoying, but pro tip, if you go
to notification panel settings and then
switch them from separate to together,
it no longer requires extra swipes to
get to quick settings. They're supposed
to be quick after all. But there's also,
of course, the iOS copycat stuff, too.
Maybe you've seen the obvious dynamic
island clone on other phones before.
Apparently, Samsung is not immune to it.
But there's three main things that are
actually new about using this phone,
which is the cameras, the battery, and
the thinness and lightness, which you'll
see what I mean. So, they've managed to
actually stuff the same main camera as
the S25 Ultra in this phone, which is
kind of crazy. Great camera, 200
megapixel sensor that bends down to 12
megapixel shots by default. It makes
these nice, sharp images in a big
variety of scenes. It's great. But then
unlike the rest of the S25 lineup, there
are no telephoto cameras on this phone.
Now, on one hand, I can argue it makes
logical sense, like there's less room
inside the phone here, and often a 2x
digital zoom from a good sensor is
actually better than a 2x optical zoom
from a crappy small sensor. But yeah,
you are definitely missing out on the
further zoom performance here, which
might not seem like much, but every once
in a while, having some far zoom does
come in very handy. I was just at my
cousin's graduation and I think every
single human there was zoomed as far in
as their phone could physically go. And
so then a phone with a telephoto feels
obvious. But instead the second camera
here is an ultrawide. Not the same
ultrawide as the ultra phone though.
This is a smaller 12 megapixel sensor. I
found it to still be very solid though.
Doesn't have any big weaknesses or
vignetting or softness issues like I
found on some of the iPhones ultrawides.
And it does macros as well. What you're
probably wondering more about though is
the battery. And yep, there's no way
around it. It's definitely worse. This
is a huge S25 plus-siz screen with a
smaller battery than the regular S25.
So, yeah, you notice it. It's 3,900 mAh,
which is enough to be fine. And you can
end the day with a bit of battery life
left on a light day. And there's a whole
ton of people that live most of their
daily lives with very predictable
charging opportunities. Like you might
be like me and have a wireless charger
at your desk at work in front of you all
the time. You might charge during your
driving commute. Maybe you're always
around an outlet when you're at home. So
it's manageable. But you got to think if
it's already 25% worse than the S25 Plus
as a starting point, then you already
know when this phone gets old, it's
going to be even worse. I'm sure someone
will do a scientific test and and get
exact values out of this, but I think in
general, if you are expecting six hours
of screen on time out of an A+ flagship
phone all day, convenient, then expect
closer to 4 and a half to five out of
this, not as hot. But all the sacrifice,
of course, was made in the name of
thinness and lightness because that
pesky graphite and copper that gives you
incredible all day battery life is also
so thick and heavy. And if only you
could just get rid of some of it, then
you could have this stunningly thin
piece of metal. And let me tell
you, it is really thin and light. It's
kind of crazy. I'm so sorry to say, but
there are there are a couple devices
that have come out in the past couple
years that are genuinely impressively
thin and light, and they feel just kind
of like this amazingly thin sheet of
metal that happens to have a screen on
it. Like the Galaxy Tab Ultra was one of
those. Uh, the new iPad Pro was another
one of those from this past year. And
this phone is another one of those.
Like, it's one of those things where,
okay, yeah, it looks a little thinner on
video. Whoop-dedoo. Snazzy commercial.
Great. I put it up next to another
phone. It makes it look thick. Cool. It
could do that. But then you hold it and
start using it, and that is the exact
moment that it starts being impressive.
Like I've showed this phone now to a
whole bunch of people in this studio and
out there in the real world and you know
looking at it even they'd be oh yeah you
know it looks kind of thin but then I'd
hand it to them and then then they'd be
super impressed when they actually hold
the thing. Now will that feeling go away
after a couple of months of using this
phone? Yeah, maybe a little bit. Uh will
this feel totally pointless to some
people once they put a case on the
phone? I think for some people yes.
Honestly, this phone with a case on it,
though, is still thinner than any
regular phone with a case on it. But
then, will this phone have durability
issues like a certain other thin phone
in the past? Well, I I feel like if
you're Samsung, there's no way you
didn't consider that. And so, this phone
has Gorilla Glass, ceramic, too, and
titanium for the frame. And so, I feel
like there's no chance they repeat the
bending in pocket mistakes of the past.
But only time will tell, I guess. I just
can't get over the fact that it's it's
holding the phone in person that has
sold way more people than any video or
photo comparison ever could, which I
understand probably is extremely ironic
considering I'm telling you this through
a video and I can't hand you the phone,
but you're just going to have to trust
me on this one. Also, this here is one
of the last phones Samsung used the Edge
name on. This is my Samsung Galaxy S6
Edge. And they call these older phones
edge because they curved the display
glass over the left and right edges,
giving it a kind of a bezelless
waterfall effect since screen to body
ratio was like a huge deal at the time.
And it also happened to make the rails
of the phone that you actually hold
extremely thin, which was a kind of a
unique feeling at the time. And this new
Edge phone, again, because of how thin
it is, is actually a unique feel in the
hand. And I do think it will actually
win some people over with the clear
obvious trade-off being less battery and
some serious table wobble with no case.
Now, I can't talk about the S25 Edge
without also talking about the elephant
in the room, which is the rumor of
future ultra thin phones, including the
alleged iPhone 17 Air coming later this
year.
And my thoughts about these are really
just revolving around one thing, which
is battery. Shocker. See, earlier this
year, I reviewed the OnePlus 13. And I
talked about some of the big things we
expect to see in smartphones in 2025.
One of which is a reall life battery
advancement, which we don't see very
often. This one is silicon carbon
battery tech. Essentially, it allows you
to have higher battery density and
faster charging, which means you can do
one of two things. You can either make
phones that are the same size that have
much much better battery or you can
unlock this new ultra thin phone form
factor and have roughly the same battery
as before. The OnePlus 13 did the first
thing. It had a 6,000 mAh battery in the
size of the normal flagship and it was
amazing. It had 7 hour plus screen on
time. It was great. This S25 Edge jumps
on the ultra thin thing, but it is not a
silicon carbon battery. Uh, so there's
some speculation why maybe Samsung
couldn't source enough of this new
battery tech to ship the number of
phones that they were planning to with
this model. Or maybe they're just a
little bit apprehensive about taking
risks in the battery departments after
getting burned in the past. Totally
fair. Either way, they jumped on the
ultra thin thing, but battery life
suffered. So, what about the rumored
iPhone 17 Air? Well, word on the street
is that phone also won't use a silicon
carbon battery, possibly for a lot of
the same reasons. The rumors I'm reading
now are pointing towards like a 2,800
mAh battery, which even in iPhone land
is just so much worse than the rest of
their lineup. And that is going to be
fascinating to see how they present that
and how they justify that. Either way,
look, I think I think ultra thin phones
can work with silicon carbon battery
tech. I think something like this with
like a 4500 to 5,000 mAh battery would
be amazing. Ultra thin phone lasts all
day. Great. And then they can also make
a regular size phone with a super long
battery life. And then people can pick
between the two. I just saw Realme made
a concept phone that's a totally normal
8 1/2 mm thick, but with a crazy 10,000
mAh battery and 320 watt fast charging,
which would be incredible. Now, yes, it
is a concept phone, so it's not real.
It's more of a demonstration of the
advancements of silicon carbon battery
tech. But that's the stuff that we're
hoping is on the horizon. Maybe S26 Edge
will get there. Thanks for watching.
Catch you guys in the next one.
Peace. Never. Ever.