[Music]
welcome
to hard talk i'm stephen sacker my guest
today
is a great british actress whose body of
work represents
a paradox in the public mind dame diana
rigg will forever be linked with
performances which were
almost a sideshow in her long career i'm
thinking of her role in
the avengers and as a bond girl both
attracted huge attention
but it's in the theater that she's won
critical acclaim
and a host of awards now she has an
iconic role in the hit series
game of thrones so how's it been dealing
with the
fickleness and unpredictability of an
acting life
[Music]
dame diana rigg welcome to hardtop thank
you
i want to ask you a pretty basic first
question is your approach
to acting today pretty similar to the
way it's always been or
has it changed pretty radically over the
years i think it's it's more or less the
same
i i did ask a friend of mine who's known
me for 50 years
because i'm surrounded by when you know
when you're working with younger people
the waves of ambition come across
to you and i asked this friend of mine
was i ambitious
and he said no you were always grateful
and i think that just about sums up
um my career i suppose the difference is
that
having done so much over such a long
period you
i'm imagining feel much more
confident about who you are and where
you're going and what you've already
achieved and i just wonder if that makes
a difference
yes it does of course it does i mean
i've
i've always loved working i don't
live to work i've always had a life
beside
my work so that it i've had a balanced
life because i
do look back now at my age you tend to
um and i've always had
a pretty full personal life as well as
thank goodness i've been so lucky with
my professional life
well already i'm getting a feeling that
you love what you do i guess you must
do it because you love it now because
you know when you started you had to put
bread on the table you know that was
your job and now you do it i guess
simply because you choose to because
it's fun
yes but also um
i i simply don't understand people
who who um decry what they do
actors you know talk about where we're
children really at heart or we're
half formed or we're really living out
fantasies on the stage
and it's it it's it's very belittling to
a profession which actually goes back to
640 bc um
i mean one of the tropes is that actors
are people
uh sort of deeply insecure and in search
of an identity because that's why
they're drawn to a job where
they can play other people all the time
inhabit other people i take exception to
that
i mean not great exception i just think
they're foolish when they
speak like that because i think if if if
you do
justice to the acting
you have to you you have to have a
profound knowledge
of of the human condition um
and and of yourself because what happens
when you
accept a part is you have to measure the
distance between yourself
and that part and you have to fill it
fill it with truth i mean sarah sidon
said i look upon a part to see if it is
in nature and if it is then i know it
can be played
so you have to turn that written page
into nature so on that basis are there
many parts that you've turned down
because you just didn't believe in them
no
i feel like generally i've generally
thought oh if i don't believe
in this it's a bit of a challenge really
i've got i've got to
i've got to uh make it believable
and actually talking about belief
um it's one of the most moving things
about
uh again our profession being in the
theater is that
people come to believe they lend you
their belief
they don't come cynically they want to
believe
and this is a great great uh
gift that they give us you've talked
about the theater and we'll talk a lot
more about the theater but i i i
want to in a sense start in the here and
now and then weave backward through your
career
the here and now to many people is all
about
a role you have found in one of the
biggest
tv series of our age that is game of
thrones
now it's full of young sort of starlet
actors but it also has a rather
wonderful part for you
how um how did it feel getting involved
in something that's become such a a
current cult
i i wasn't aware that i was getting
involved in something so huge
i really had no idea um as ever i was
deeply
grateful to get the part and i and to
get such a good part too
i really enjoy doing it i mean is she
your your part i think she's called
a lady is it a lena tyrell
she's um something of a harridan oh yes
i'm yeah she's she's also pretty evil
i'm good at evil
let's see how good of evil you are this
is a little taster of this evil lady
well watch a little clip let's let's
look at it on the screen
you came to dawn because you needed our
help what is your name again
barbara
you look like an angry little boy don't
presume to tell me what i need
forgive my sister what she likes in
diplomacy
shut up dear anything from you
no good let the grown women speak
the lannisters it's a fantastic little
clip because it gives a real sense of
your strength and
meanness yeah but it's also down to the
script writers
i mean thank you to them for a good
scene yeah well it's interesting because
uh you know i've on hard talk
interviewed quite a number of actors
female actors over the years who've
bemoaned the dearth
of great parts for women as as they get
older and progress
through careers have you experienced
that or is that not your experience i
i've
truly been lucky i really have
and i think um in a sense i
sort of uh developed and
and and become a better actress as i've
grown older
do you think it's because some actors
female actors are too picky i mean
you know because it is it's again it's
become something of a cliche almost and
i
quote you one brilliant actor kristen
scott thomas
who says you know i know all the stories
of older women not getting
jobs in film can be so very boring but
it is true it's a disaster
well i think i think she's talking about
film uh is that different
i think it is different and and i can't
comment because my film career is
pretty well negligible i've done the odd
film but
i'm not famous for film my film work
well we'll get to film work because
there is one particular role you played
which
has gone down in history because it was
a bond movie and everybody remembers
bond movies but
i don't want to get there just yet i i
want to stick with
in a sense the way in which game of
thrones
mirrors something you did early in your
career which was another cult
tv series and that is the avengers
very different eras different styles but
there's something
actually quite similar about the way
both
captured the spirit of an age would you
agree yes
i think so i mean she emma peale i do
hate the name
oh talk about cliche but anyway
emma peale was way ahead of her time and
the reason for that
was that um originally it was two
fellows
it was um patrick mcnee and another
actor whose name escapes me
and he dropped out and on a blackman
took over and they didn't change the
script
so it was a part written for a man that
ended up being played by a woman and
maybe that's why so many people have
said my god this was revolutionary it
was a really
proper strong independent equal part for
a woman
that's right and that's because that
actually wasn't supposed to be for a
woman exactly that's how it happened
yeah and you took over from honor
blackman you were very young i mean you
sort of paid your dues
in theater provincial theater the rsc as
well doing shakespeare and then suddenly
you were plucked out of all that and
told
you you were going to have this really
rather glamorous part in a in a new
tv show i left um i was with the royal
shakespeare company for five years and i
would sort of work my way up
and uh to play leads and um
and i i left uh because i
sensed i had to broaden myself i didn't
want
just to be a shakespearean actress and
the world of television was there
sort of beckoning in a way and i was
incredibly lucky to get an audition and
and
and to get the part well for those on
the planet who don't remember the
avengers
and that sort of 60s sort of style that
it encapsulated
let's have a look at a clip of m appeal
supersleuth
in the avengers and in a very particular
uh
getter let's have a look
give me the gun back up
[Music]
give me the gun
[Applause]
that's sweet it's compelling stuff i
mean
obviously i'm not going to mess with you
in the studio given what i've just seen
but um how do you feel about watching
that now because if anybody mentions
your name i think the first images
conjured up
are of the catsuit and of em appeal and
uh
do you like that or is that actually
quite frustrating no i
i'm i'm again i'm very grateful
the only frustrating part about it was
the suit was
oh god it was uncomfortable and it took
me a good half hour to go to the lava
trick
getting out of that thing you know
peeling it off
um but it i'm very grateful to it and
really
it it it suddenly projected me
in beyond
years of work in the theater yeah i mean
that that
is frustrating in a way for somebody who
loves theater so much
that you know you can cut through and
reach a massive audience
with a only two years as it was yes on
that show in a way that
years and years and years of classical
theater
yeah and um i went back um
i think it was after the second year i
went back to stratford
to do 12th night to say look hey i can
put bums on seats
and in fact i was doing the two um
together i was filming the avengers and
doing 12 tonight
just one thing about that that intrigues
me because they've been all sorts of
different analyses
uh of what m appeal represented and a
lot of it is
seen through a sort of feminist prism
some feminists say she was fantastic she
was revolutionary because
she was a strong independent
phenomenally capable woman who was an
equal partner with a man
and others have said oh yeah but how
terrible that this sort of independent
woman had to be put in high heels and a
cat suit and looked so very glam you
know
men didn't have to go through all that
do they want hairy legs i mean
you know you can't of course it was if
you're playing the lead on
on in a television series um
and and in that sort of series uh why
not present glamour at the same time as
uh self-sufficiency i don't i don't see
any problem with that
as a very successful actor in your
20s 30s getting more and more successful
would you would you say you
had feminist instincts um i've always
had feminist instincts where
parity of of
salary is concerned i mean i think an
awful lot of it is
um still a huge issue today it is a huge
in hollywood there are campaigns of
women actors where we've watched um the
tennis players
fight their fight um actresses are
constantly fighting in in
uh america about it i mean catherine
hepburn uh
kicked it all off many many years ago
and it's absolutely ridiculous chasm
between men and women
sure is it true that you discovered on
the set of the avengers that
the male cameramen were earning more
than you
yes and then when i um complained
and it hit the newspapers i was dubbed
incredibly mercenary and
in those days i wouldn't be now you were
friends with patrick my knee who was
your co-star
was he being paid much more than you i
never asked him
we never got there i didn't want to put
him in that situation
i was it was my fight and i had to fight
it by myself
here's another thing that i'm interested
in looking back is wonderful looking at
the old footage
we talked about game of thrones and
today's young acting stars in games game
of thrones
are plunged into a world of celebrity
uh and they become magazine fodder and
everything else
it was a different era in in the mid
late 60s when you were doing
the avengers i wonder if there was an
element of that for you
and how you felt about the celebrity
culture that may have come your way
i i was completely unprepared for it
completely
um i think nowadays the young are
prepared for it because
they see it all around them they read it
in the magazines and everything
i i know i i was naive very naive
and no idea and the the fan mail was
flooding in i didn't have a secretary um
it mounted up i put it all in the back
of my mini and drove around with it
feeling
so guilty did you like it no i felt me
guilty because i
first of all i didn't have the
photographs to send back which is what
they're all
wanting i didn't know how to set about
dealing with fan mail at
all and it took me a good long time to
to work it all out
i think people get help now in in the
sense that maybe the studios help them
or
somebody helps them but i just have my
mother yeah you've also said i i like
this comment you said you
when you're acting with the game of
thrones cast you sometimes look at them
and you think
darling hearts of the young ones darling
hearts you have no idea what the rest of
your life is going to be like unless you
put in a proper apprenticeship
and if i sound like an old bag banging
on like this then that's what i
am yeah it's true do you feel that
today's generation of
successful young actors aren't really
sort of putting in the world they're
suddenly catapulted
into um this this world of series
and it is one world but it isn't the
only world
and um i i think you know that
what i've always believed is the stage
gives you longevity
i think um film the more a film will
spit you out at a certain age the more
of television will spit you out at a
certain age
but theater never does that
and they really need
to step on stage and discover what their
true worth
is through the audience
yeah fascinating talking of film
you say film can spit you out as an
actor so easily but
there are certain roles that live long
in the memory and i think you
can lay claim to one of them uh
with your role in one of the bond movies
yes
on her majesty's secret service which is
remembered i suppose partly because it
was the only
bond role played by george lazenby but
also because your female
character the love interest was actually
quite different from most
bond girls it was a deeper character a
more human character and actually
ended up with a marriage between your
character and
bond himself let's just see how you
played the role alongside bond
no sign of them yet or of someone saying
thank you
thank you tracy you've got sharp eyes
and beautiful
earlobes what were you doing so near bis
gloria
now i have a new interest in life with
the sports egg very wholesome just one
winter sportsman
and bar told me where to find him
[Applause]
just keep my mind on your driving
there you are tracy de vincenzo i
believe your character was called
was that fun because a lot of women
who've played in bond as
quote unquote bond girls get pigeonholed
and i wonder whether you felt you did or
whether you escaped that
no no no not at all really not i mean i
think uh yeah no not
i can't afterwards say it was quite
difficult playing alongside
george george was difficult and
there's no mistake about it um
and as a result he was not invited back
um
but nonetheless i really wasn't up to it
no he was perfectly good he really
really was
i i think i mean i haven't seen it for
ages apart from that cut
um i thought he was yes he was good
um but he was just so difficult off and
demanding and um
and the producers thought enough you
know uh
film folklore has it that because your
relationship with him was
quite difficult you you ate garlic
before the yeah
that was that was so silly he accused me
of that and
in fact he actually accused you of yeah
he did and in fact
what happened was that i'd had uh
mistakenly i'd had uh pate chicken liver
patty for lunch
and they'd put garlic in it but i didn't
i didn't mean to
and i'm absolutely certain that prior to
the um
the snogging scene i'd i'd actually
done everything that actors do clean
your teeth and chew gum and spray and
all that kind of stuff
but he thought because he was paranoid
by this time he thought i'd done it on
purpose
which i hadn't i wouldn't dream of doing
so i'm so glad we've cleared that up
well i'm glad
too because it's lingered for 25 years
let me ask you about confidence and
security stroke insecurity in the acting
profession you you
have said over the years that you look
back on on
the roles you played and the the life
you led as a younger actor and
and you wished you'd been more confident
and
happier in your own skin yes um
you actually it it uh lack of confidence
is a form of self-torture
it's ridiculous and i forget who it was
either
olivier if somebody said it's it's uh
you're you're
you're being selfish when you're worried
and and worrying about yourself you know
um because
acting is is giving out
and being um unconfident is
sort of hunging yourself and a bit
inward looking
um and i'd sort of think i wasted time
not having enough confidence and is that
because you had a wonderful period
i guess in the 1990s when you won a host
of awards for a really huge part
that was just such a glorious time i
mean thanks to the director jonathan
kent with whom i worked
one after the other you know medea
federer um hippolytus uh mother courage
it was he who put me up there and he who
showed
faith in me uh and i have
nothing but gratitude for that period of
my life because it really was
wonderful and i i was very very lucky
not many actresses get the opportunity
to play these parts one after the other
i mean how lucky was that well i don't
think it's luck is it it's talent but
also a great thing that you seem to have
done is you seem to have
come to a clear understanding that that
you know
theater has its ups and downs and that
you can get bad reviews
and in the end it's better to sort of
shrug your shoulders or laugh at them
than get deeply wounded by them yeah
you've got to you've got to move on
just move on have you had lousy reviews
that stick in your mind
well uh the worst one um was when i did
um on broadway avalon eloise and
we did a nude scene uh keith michelle
and i
um we had sort of uh what do you mean
nothing knickers off and
deeply uncomfortable and absolutely
horrible and cold
and there was a um what was he always
called john simon he was small rather
ugly hungarian gentleman
who said i uh diana rigg is built like a
brick mausoleum with insufficient flying
buttresses
we'll try and get over that i can
imagine you would remember that
how to how to play the nude scene
afterwards i mean just
horrible but what's beautiful is you
you've
you've found the humor in it and also
you've now turned it into a stage
you know you've collected all these
horrible reviews not just of yourself
but many many other great actors as well
and you you've
got this book which has one of the best
titles ever of
no turn unstoned i mean it's become
quite a thing in itself isn't it yes it
has yeah
um the point about bad notices
is that you have to be able to they've
got to be funny for a kickoff
and mine is uh but also to be able to
quote them is is cathartic
it sort of halves the pain to get a
laugh at the end of it
do you think some actors are too serious
about this just a bit
trade of theirs just a bit yeah about
themselves as well
i mean there's a lot of laughter in in
this profession
a lot and um i think
yes to be too serious
is a grave mistake we're almost out of
time i don't think anybody around the
world would forgive me unless you tell
me
exactly what's happening with game of
thrones i can't
i think well give me the whole plot but
when are you going back to filming
oh yeah later on this year yeah in fact
in a couple of months i think i haven't
got the script yet so i don't know
what's happening do you know if you're
going to be killed off because there's
so many killings in games
no i haven't got a clue i do know that
they're going to well they've announced
that they're going to finish it next
year
right yeah so so it obviously has a you
know it is ending
then you'll find something else yeah
absolutely damn diana rick it's been a
pleasure thank you for being on hard
talk
thank you thank you very much indeed
[Music]
you